<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Apache Incubator</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1641276</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562062599</id>
      <parentid>560639250</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-29T04:13:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>94.97.71.33</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Current Sub-projects */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2012}}

'''Apache Incubator''' is the gateway for [[open-source]] projects intended to become fully fledged [[Apache Software Foundation]] projects.

The Incubator project was created in October 2002 to provide an entry path to the Apache Software Foundation for projects and codebases wishing to become part of the Foundation's efforts. All code donations from external organizations and existing external projects wishing to move to Apache must enter through the Incubator.

The Apache Incubator project serves on the one hand as a temporary container project until the incubating project is accepted and becomes a top-level project of the [[Apache Software Foundation]] or becomes subproject of a proper project such as the [[Jakarta Project]] or [[Apache XML]]. On the other hand, the Incubator project documents how the Foundation works, and how to get things done within its framework. This means documenting process, roles and policies within the [[Apache Software Foundation]] and its member projects.

==Current Sub-projects==
{{div col|2}}
; [[Apache Ambari|Ambari]]: Ambari is a monitoring, administration and lifecycle management project for Apache Hadoop clusters.
; [[Apache Amber|Amber]]: The Amber project will deliver a Java development framework mainly aimed to build OAuth-aware applications.
; [[Apache Any23|Any23]]: Anything To Triples (any23) is a library, a web service and a command line tool that extracts structured data in RDF format from a variety of Web documents.
; [[Bean Validation]]: The Bean Validation project will create an implementation of Bean Validation as defined by the Java EE specifications.
; [[Apache Bigtop|Bigtop]]: Bigtop is a project for the development of packaging and tests of the Hadoop ecosystem.
; [[Apache Celix|Celix]]: Celix is an OSGi like implementation in C with a distinct focus on interoperability between Java and C.
; [[Apache Chukwa|Chukwa]]: Chukwa is a log collection and analysis framework for Apache Hadoop clusters.
; [[Apache Clerezza|Clerezza]]: An OSGi-based modular application and set of components (bundles) for building RESTFul Semantic Web applications and services.
; [[Apache Corodova|Cordova]]: Apache Cordova is a platform for building native mobile applications using HTML, CSS and JavaScript (formerly Phonegap). The project entered incubation as Callback, but decided to change its name to Cordova on 2011-11-28.
; [[Deft]]: Deft is a non-blocking, asynchronous, event driven high performance web framework running on the JVM.
; [[DeltaSpike]]: DeltaSpike is a collection of JSR-299 (CDI) Extensions for building applications on the Java SE and EE platforms.
; [[Devicemap]]: Apache DeviceMap is a data repository containing device information, images and other relevant information for all sorts of mobile devices, e.g. smartphones and tablets. While the focus is initially on that data, APIs will also be created to use and manage it.
; [[DirectMemory]]: DirectMemory's main purpose is to act as a second level cache able to store large amounts of data without filling up the Java heap and thus avoiding long garbage collection cycles.
; [[Apache Drill|Drill]]: Drill is a distributed system for interactive analysis of large-scale datasets.
; [[Droid (robot)|Droids]]: Droids aims to be an intelligent standalone robot framework that allows to create and extend existing droids (robots).
; [[EasyAnt]]: Easyant is a build system based on Apache Ant and Apache Ivy.
; [[Empire-db]]: a data persistence component that allows database vendor independent dynamic query definition as well as safe and simple data retrieval and updating
; [[Etch (protocol)|Etch]]: A cross-platform, language- and transport-independent framework for building and consuming network services.
;[[Adobe Flex|Flex]]: a [[software development kit]] (SDK) released by [[Adobe Systems]] for the development and deployment of cross-platform [[rich Internet application]]s based on the [[Adobe Flash]] platform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mail-archives.apache.org/mod_mbox/incubator-general/201112.mbox/%3CCAEWfVJmMq390Hinafg%2Bjik8VqboYG1ixe_gnz5O2bV5q5mtKPw%40mail.gmail.com%3E |title=Flex to join the Apache Incubator |publisher=Mail-archives.apache.org |date=2011-12-30 |accessdate=2012-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Flume: Flume is a distributed, reliable, and available system for efficiently collecting, aggregating, and moving large amounts of log data from many different sources to a centralized data store.
; [[Giraph]]: Giraph is a large-scale, fault-tolerant, Bulk Synchronous Parallel (BSP)-based graph processing framework.
; [[Hama]]: a distributed computing framework based on [[Bulk Synchronous Parallel]] computing techniques for massive scientific computations.
; [[HCatalog|Apache HCatalog]]: a table management service to provide unified access to Pig, Hive and MapReduce data
; HISE (Human Interactions Service Engine): an open source implementation of WS-Human-Task specification (Web Services Human Task). This project has retired and is no longer actively developed or supported.
; Isis: The Isis project will be an extensible standards-based framework to rapidly develop and enterprise level deploy domain-driven (DDD) applications.
; [[JSPWiki|Apache JSPWiki]]: a Java-based [[wiki software|wiki engine]]
; Kafka: Kafka is a distributed publish-subscribe system for processing large amounts of streaming data.
; [[Kalumet]]: Kalumet a complete environment manager and deployer including J2EE environments (application servers, applications, etc.), software, and resources.
; Kato: Kato is a project to develop the Specification, Reference Implementation, and TCK for JSR 326: the JVM Post-mortem Diagnostics API.
; Kitty: Kitty is a lightweight, production focused, Java-based application server performance diagnostic and management utility.
; [[Log4php]]: a logging framework for PHP
; [[Lokahi]]: a management console for Apache HTTP Server and Apache Tomcat
; [[Lucene.Net]]: Lucene.Net is a source code, class-per-class, API-per-API and algorithmatic port of the Java Lucene search engine to the C# and .NET platform utilizing Microsoft .NET Framework.
; [[Apache Mesos|Mesos]]: Mesos is a cluster manager that provides resource sharing and isolation across cluster applications.
; [[NPanday]]: NPanday allows projects using the .NET framework to be built with Apache Maven.
; Nuvem: Nuvem defines an open application programming interface for common cloud application services, allowing applications to be easily ported across the most popular cloud platforms.
; [[ODF Toolkit]]: Java modules that allow programmatic creation, scanning and manipulation of OpenDocument Format (ISO/IEC 26300 == ODF) documents
; [[Oozie]]: Server-based workflow scheduling and coordination system to manage data processing jobs for Apache Hadoop
; [[Openmeetings]]: Openmeetings is a web conferencing solution.

; [[PhotArk]]: open source photo gallery application
; RAT (Release Audit Tool): a comprehension and auditing for distributions and source code
; S4 (Simple Scalable Streaming System): a general-purpose, distributed, scalable, partially fault-tolerant, pluggable platform that allows programmers to easily develop applications for processing continuous, unbounded streams of data.
; SIS (Spatial Information System): a toolkit that spatial information system builders or users can leverage to build applications containing location context.
; [[Stanbol]]: A modular software stack and reusable set of components for semantic content management
; Tashi: An infrastructure for cloud computing on big data.
; VCL: Virtual Computing Lab. Framework for creating, dispensing and running virtual images.
; [[VXQuery]]: A standards compliant XML Query processor.
; [[Apache Wave|Wave]]: Wave is a rich, distributed, near-real-time collaboration platform which allows users to work together.
; [[Apache Wink|Wink]]: a framework for creating and consuming RESTful Web services
; Wookie: a W3C widget engine with Google Wave and Open Social Extensions.
{{div col end}}

==Projects Graduated from Incubation==
{{div col|2}}
; [[Apache Abdera|Abdera]]: An implementation of the Atom Syndication Format and Atom Publishing Protocol.
; [[Apache Accumulo|Accumulo]]: a sorted, distributed key-value store based on [[Google|Google's]] [[BigTable]]
; [[Ace]]: A software distribution framework based on OSGi that allows you to manage and distribute artifacts.
; [[ActiveMQ]]: A robust and high performance Message Orientated Middleware provider which will be integrated into Apache Geronimo but also be usable from inside any JVM.
; [[Apache Airavata]]: Software Framework for executing and managing computational jobs on distributed computing resources.
; [[Apollo]]: A robust implementation of the OASIS WS-ResourceFramework (WSRF) family of specifications
; [[Apache Aries|Aries]]: The Aries project will deliver a set of pluggable Java components enabling an enterprise OSGi application programming model.
; [[Apache Beehive|Beehive]]: Extensible Java application framework with an integrated metadata-driven programming model for web services, web applications, and resource access
; [[Apache Bloodhound|Bloodhound]]: Bloodhound is a software development collaboration tool, including issue tracking, wiki and repository browsing.
; [[Buildr]]: Buildr is a simple and intuitive build system for Java projects written in Ruby.
; [[Apache Cassandra]]: Cassandra
; [[Apache Cayenne|Cayenne]]: Robust Persistence
; [[Apache Chemistry|Chemistry]]: Content Management Interoperability Services (CMIS) for Python, Java, PHP and .NET.[
; [[Apache Click|Click]]: Component based Java Web Framework
; [[CouchDB]]: CouchDB
; [[CXF]]: The CXF project will create a SOA services framework by merges the ObjectWeb Celtix project and the Codehaus XFire project.
; [[Deltacloud]]: Deltacloud, cloud API (REST) and abstraction framework
; [[Derby]]: Java relational database
; [[Apache Directory|Directory]]: Directory projects.
; [[ESME]]: Enterprise Social Messaging Experiment (ESME) is a secure and highly scalable microsharing and micromessaging platform that allows people to discover and meet one another and get controlled access to other sources of information, all in a business process context.
; [[Apache Felix|Felix]]: Implementation of the OSGi R4 specification.
; [[FtpServer]]: A complete FTP Server based on Mina I/O system.
; [[Geronimo]]: J2EE Container
; Gora: Gora is an ORM framework for column stores such as Apache HBase and Apache Cassandra with a specific focus on Hadoop.
; [[Harmony]]: Compatible implementation of J2SE
; [[Hermes]]: A robust implementation of the OASIS WS-Notification (WSN) family of specifications
; [[httpd-CLI]]: CLI integration project for httpd server
; [[iBATIS]]:The iBATIS Data Mapper framework makes it easier to use a database with Java or .NET applications. iBATIS couples objects with stored procedures or SQL statements using a XML descriptor.
; [[Apache Ivy|Ivy]]: A java based tool for tracking, resolving and managing project dependencies.
; [[Jackrabbit]]: Content Repository API based on JSR 170
; [[JaxMe]]:Implementation of JAXB, the specification for Java/XML binding
; [[Java Data Objects|JDO]]: JDO2
; [[jUDDI]]: Implementation of a Universal Description Discovery and Integration(UDDI) registry
; [[Apache Lenya|Lenya]]: Content Management and publishing system based on Cocoon
; [[Libcloud]]: libcloud is a standard client library for many popular cloud providers, written in python
; [[log4cxx]]: Logging for C++
; [[log4net]]: Logging for .NET
; [[log4php]]: Logging for php
; [[Lucy]]: A loose port of the Lucene search engine library, written in C and targeted at dynamic language users.
; [[MerlinDeveloper]]: Merlin eclipse plugin merged with an existing eclipse plugin already at avalon.
; [[mod-ftp]]: FTP protocol module for Apache httpd 2.x
; [[MRUnit]]: MRUnit is a library to support unit testing of Hadoop MapReduce jobs.
; [[Muse]]: A robust implementation of the OASIS WSDM, Management using Web Services (MuWS) specification
; [[MyFaces]]: MyFaces is a framework for building Java Server application GUIs based on JavaServer Faces (certified implementation of JSR-127).
; [[Nutch]]: Web Search Software
; [[Apache_ODE|Ode]]: Orchestration Director Engine
; [[OFBiz]]: The Open For Business Project (OFBiz) is an open source enterprise automation software project.
; [[OGNL]]: Object-Graph Notation Language implementation in Java
; [[OODT]]: A grid middleware framework for science data processing, information integration, and retrieval.
; [[OpenEJB]]: OpenEJB EJB Server and Container
; [[OpenJPA]]: OpenJPA is an open source implementation of the Java Persistence API
; [[OpenWebBeans]]: JSR-299 Implementation
; [[PDFBox]]: PDF library (reading, text extraction, manipulation, viewer)
; [[Pig]]: Pig is a platform for analyzing large datasets.
; [[Apache Pivot|Pivot]]: A platform for building rich internet applications in Java.
; [[Pluto]]: JSR 168 Reference Implementation
; [[Qpid]]: Qpid provides multiple language implementations of the Advanced Messaged Queuing Protocol (AMQP)
; Rave: a web and social mashup engine.
; [[River]]: River : Jini technology
; [[Apache Roller|Roller]]: Roller blog server
; [[Sanselan]]: The Sanselan Project is a pure-java image library for reading and writing a variety of image formats.
; [[ServiceMix]]: The ServiceMix project will create an ESB and component suite based on the Java Business Interface (JBI) standard - JSR 208.
; [[Apache Shindig|Shindig]]: The Shindig Project is an OpenSocial container.
; [[Apache Shiro|Shiro]]: Security framework.
; [[Apache Sling|Sling]]:Sling is a framework to develop content centric web applications based on the idea of modularizing the rendering of HTTP resources.
; [[Solr]]: Full Text Search Server
; [[SpamAssassin]]: Mail filter to identify spam.
; [[Sqoop]]: Sqoop is a tool designed for efficiently transferring bulk data between Apache Hadoop and structured datastores such as relational databases.
; [[stdcxx]]: The Apache C++ Standard Library project is a complete implementation of the ISO/IEC 14882 C++ Standard Library.
; [[Apache Subversion|Subversion]]: Subversion is an open-source version control system, with a long and detailed list of features.
; [[Synapse]]: Web Services Mediation Framework
; [[Tapestry]]: Alternative framework to JSP and Velocity scripting environments
; [[Apache Thrift|Thrift]]: Cross-language serialization and RPC framework.
; [[Apache Tika|Tika]]: Content analysis toolkit
; [[Tobago]]: A JSF based framework for web-applications.
; [[Traffic Server]]: A scalable and extensible HTTP proxy server and cache.
; [[Trinidad]]: JSF Component Library
; [[Tuscany]]: Service Component Architecture implementation
; [[UIMA]]: Framework for analysing unstructured data.
; [[WebWork 2]]: A Java web-application development framework
; [[Whirr]]: Whirr provides code for running a variety of software services on cloud infrastructure.
; [[Apache Wicket|Wicket]]: A web application framework that focusses on bringing plain object oriented Java programming to the web tier
; [[Woden]]: Implementation of WSDL 2.0
; [[XMLBeans]]: XML-Java binding tool with 100% support for XML Schema and full Infoset fidelity
{{div col end}}

==Dormant Projects==
; [[JuiCE]]: OpenSSL based JCE provider. Project going into dormant status after lack of community interest.
; [[SocialSite]]: SocialSite is an OpenSocial-based headless social networking server and a set of OpenSocial Gadgets that make it easy to add social features to existing web sites. Server provides admin console for configuration, gadget approval and management. Gadgets can be combined to form complete UI for social networking with [[friending]], group management and message support.
; [[TripleSoup]]: SPARQL endpoint for your webserver. Project entering dormant status after failing to get traction.

==Projects Retired from Incubation==
{{div col|2}}
; Agila: Extensible Business Process Management (BPM) engine core. (Project activity transferred to another Incubator project - ODE)
; Alois: ALOIS is a log collection and correlation software with reporting and alarming functionalities.
; AltRMI: A transparent Remote Procedure Call bean.(Development stalled and the project activity transferred to JRemoting)
; Axion: Relational database engine written in Java.(Project remains at Axion Tigris.org)
; [[BlueSky Open Platform|Bluesky]]: Distance learning collaboration tool.
; Composer: Embeddable IoC container
; Depot: Integrated tools for automating downloading, publishing and managing software artifacts, along with tools for manipulating their metadata.(Project closed after development stalled.)
; Graffito:Portal oriented Content Management System
; Heraldry: Identity for the rest of us.(Project retired. Some activity moved to OpenID.net)
; Imperius: Rule-based Management Policy Engine(Although the Apache Imperius project was successful in building an SPL implementation and had a successful release, there is not sufficient community energy to warrant continued development of Imperius at the Apache Software Foundation.)
; Kabuki: An AJAX toolkit
; Lokahi: A management console for Apache HTTP Server and Apache Tomcat projects on a framework extensible to other ASF projects.(Retired due to inactivity. Some talk of moving parts of the codebase to Tomcat)
; Lucene4c: Lucene for C.(Progress stalled as developers ran out of free time and motivation.)
; NMaven:.NET integration for Maven. Failed to build active community. (Efforts moved to NPanday. Other similar projects are NMaven and Byldan @ Codeplex )
; Olio: Web 2.0 evaluation kit
; RCF: JSF Component Library.(Never got started, so retired)
; Stonehenge: Stonehenge is a set of interoperability scenarios for Service Oriented Architecture and Web Services that demonstrate interoperability between multiple systems including Apache Axis2, WSF/PHP and Microsoft WCF. The code also demonstrates good practice for standards-based interoperability.("The Stonehenge project pretty much accomplished what it originally set out to do and then really didn't find a way to transition to something that is longer lasting and able to develop a community around it." )
; TSIK: (Failed to gather community momentum. Cancelled at request of Sponsoring TLP)
; wadi: a robust hetorgeneous clustering engine used to cluster geronimo, tomcat, jetty and other containers eventually.(Proposal withdrawn by creator; project continues at Codehaus)
; WSRP4J: Implementation of OASIS Web Services for Remote Portlets (WSRP)
; [[Apache XAP|XAP]]: Declarative framework for building Ajax-powered web apps
; XMLBeans/C++: C++ equivalent of Apache XMLBeans.(Failed to get traction)
; Yoko: A COBRA server.
; Zeta Components: Zeta Components is a high-quality library of loosely coupled PHP components. Zeta Components were retired from incubator 2012-04-20 and are now found at [https://github.com/zetacomponents GitHub] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Zeta Components page at Apache|url=http://incubator.apache.org/projects/zetacomponents.html|accessdate=21 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://incubator.apache.org/ Apache Incubator]
** [http://incubator.apache.org/projects/ All projects in incubator]
* [http://wiki.apache.org/incubator/OpenOfficeProposal Apache Incubator OpenOfficeProposal]

{{apache}}

&lt;!--Interwikies--&gt;

[[Category:Apache Software Foundation|Incubator]]
[[Category:Computing websites]]</text>
      <sha1>oh7w31p7ibqm8h7tg4yfpmqly2lcm9q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>