<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>GraphLab</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33544408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>557668745</id>
      <parentid>555110482</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-31T11:24:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Peter Kaminski</username>
        <id>9381</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>/* GraphLab Inc. */ typo fix: rasied -&gt; raised</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
{{multiple issues|
{{Orphan|date=January 2012}}
{{primary sources|date=November 2011}}
}}

{{ Infobox Software
| name                   = GraphLab
| logo                   = 
| screenshot             = 
| caption                = 
| collapsible            = yes
| developer              = [[Carnegie Mellon University]] 
| status                 = Active
| latest release version = v2.1
| latest release date    = {{release date|2013|05|12}}
| latest preview version = 
| latest preview date    = 
| operating system       = [[Linux]], [[MAC OS]]
| size                   = 
| programming language   = [[C++]]
| genre                  = [[graph]] processing framework
| license                = [[Apache License|Apache 2.0 Licence]] 
| website                = http://graphlab.org/
}}


[http://graphlab.org '''GraphLab'''] is a [[graph]]-based, high performance, distributed computation framework written in [[C++]]. The GraphLab project started by Prof. Carlos Guestrin of Carnegie Mellon University in 2009. It is an open source project using Apache License. While GraphLab was originally developed for [[Machine Learning]] tasks, it has found great success at a broad range of other data-mining tasks; out-performing other abstractions by orders of magnitude. &lt;ref&gt;Joseph Gonzalez, Yucheng Low, Haijie Gu, Danny Bickson, Carlos Guestrin (2012). "PowerGraph: Distributed Graph-Parallel Computation on Natural Graphs." Proceedings of Operating Systems Design and Implementation (OSDI).&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Yucheng Low, Joseph Gonzalez, Aapo Kyrola, Danny Bickson, Carlos Guestrin and Joseph M. Hellerstein (2012). "Distributed GraphLab: A Framework for Machine Learning and Data Mining in the Cloud." Proceedings of Very Large Data Bases (PVLDB).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Motivation ==
As the amounts of collected data and computing power grows (multicore, GPUs, clusters,
clouds), modern datasets no longer fit into one computing node. Efficient distributed/parallel
algorithms for handling large scale data are required.  The GraphLab framework is a parallel programming abstraction targeted for sparse [[Iterative algorithm|iterative]]
graph algorithms. GraphLab provides a high level programming interface, allowing a rapid deployment of distributed machine learning algorithms.&lt;ref&gt;Y. Low, J. Gonzalez, A. Kyrola, D. Bickson, C. Guestrin and J. Hellerstein. GraphLab: A New Framework for Parallel Machine Learning. In the 26th Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI), Catalina Island, USA, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; 
The main design considerations behind the design of GraphLab are:
* Sparse data with local dependencies
* Iterative algorithms
* Potentially asynchronous execution

Main features of GraphLab are:
* A unified multicore and distributed API: write once run efficiently in both shared and distributed memory systems
* Tuned for performance: optimized C++ execution engine leverages extensive multi-threading and asynchronous IO
* Scalable: GraphLab intelligently places data and computation using sophisticated new algorithms
* HDFS Integration
* Powerful Machine Learning Toolkits

== GraphLab Toolkits ==
On top of GraphLab, several implemented libraries of algorithms:
* [http://docs.graphlab.org/topic_modeling.html Topic Modeling]- contains applications like LDA which can be used to cluster documents and extract topical representations.
* [http://docs.graphlab.org/graph_analytics.html Graph Analytics]- contains application like pagerank and triangle counting which can be applied to general graphs to estimate community structure.
* [http://docs.graphlab.org/clustering.html Clustering]- contains standard data clustering tools such as Kmeans
* [http://docs.graphlab.org/collaborative_filtering.html Collaborative Filtering]- contains a collection of applications used to make predictions about users interests and factorize large matrices.
* [http://docs.graphlab.org/graphical_models.html Graphical Models]- contains tools for making joint predictions about collections of related random variables.
* [http://docs.graphlab.org/computer_vision.html Computer Vision]- contains a collection of tools for reasoning about images.

==Award Winning Software==
A solution based on Graphlab collaborative filtering library won the 5th place in [http://kddcup.yahoo.com/workshop.php ACM Yahoo! KDD CUP challenge], track1, out of more than 1000 participants.  LeBuShiShu team used a mixture of 12 different algorithms and deployed 10,000 CPU hours on [http://www.psc.edu/machines/sgi/uv/blacklight.php BlackLight supercomputer].&lt;ref&gt;Yao Wu, Qiang Yan, Danny Bickson, Yucheng Low, Qing Yang. Efficient Multicore Collaborative Filtering. In ACM KDD CUP workshop 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the utilized algorithms and techniques are now part of the [http://graphlab.org/pmf.html GraphLab Collaborative FIltering Toolkit].
==GraphLab Inc. ==
[http://graphlab.com GraphLab Inc.] company was founded by [http://www.cs.washington.edu/people/faculty/guestrin/ Prof. Carlos Guestrin] from University of Washington on May 2013 to continue development support of the GraphLab open source project. GraphLab Inc. raised 6.75M$ from Madrona and NEA. &lt;ref&gt;GraphLab CrunchBase Profile http://www.crunchbase.com/company/graphlab&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* [http://graphlab.org/ GraphLab Webpage]

[[Category:Data mining and machine learning software]]</text>
      <sha1>1vxropb3jq7fnhg1pk2gx9pnugzu7in</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>