<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>List of bioinformatics companies</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8386893</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562919037</id>
      <parentid>562918929</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-05T02:31:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.253.87.73</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Dynamic list}}

This is a list of [[bioinformatics]] companies.

* [[Accelrys]]
* [[Applied Maths]] provides the softwaresuite [[BioNumerics]] for powerful databasing, integrated networking and a wide range of analysis and decision-making tools, including data mining, querying, clustering, identification, statistics, and much more.
* [[Astrid Research]] Astrid Research Inc. is a bioinformatics company that provides software products and services for genomics research.
* [[Elsevier BIOBASE|BIOBASE]] provides [[biological database]]s, bioinformatics for expression data, promoter and pathway analysis and KPO services
* [[BioDiscovery| BioDiscovery, Inc.]] provides software for DNA copy number, methylation, expression from microarray and NGS platforms, with solutions for cancer and constitutional genomics.
* [[Biomatters|Biomatters Ltd.]] is the [[New Zealand]]-based company that creates the [[Geneious]] software suite.
* [[Biomax Informatics AG]] bioinformatics services
* [[CLC Bio]] Bioinformatics workbenches.
* [[DNASTAR]] provides DNA sequence assembly and analysis, including Sanger and next generation sequence assembly and gene expression analysis.
* [[Gene Codes Corporation]]
* [[Genedata]] provides software products and services for data analysis and storage in [[Expression profiling|Transcriptomics]], [[Toxicogenomics]], [[High-throughput screening]] (HTS), [[Genomics]] and related disciplines.
* [[Geneious]] combines many DNA and protein sequence analysis tools.
* [[GeneTalk]] provides a web-based platform for human sequence variant analysis and interpretation for diagnosis of inherited disorders. Variant files ([[Variant_Call_Format|VCF]] format) can be filtered and reduced for convinient interpretation of the data. The community of scientists, clinicians, and human geneticists can help in interpreting the data.
* [[Genomatix]] offering biology driven analysis pipelines for microarray analysis, ChIP on Chip and Solexa/454 data. Multiple tools and databases for analysis of gene regulation. Comparative genomics and most complete and quality checked genomic annotation for 17 species.
* [[Genostar]] provides streamlined bioinformatics: [[sequence assembly]], mapping, annotation transfer and identification of [[protein domains]], [[comparative genomics]], structural searches, [[metabolic pathway]] analysis, modeling and simulation of biological networks
* [[Ingenuity Systems]] is a provider of information and custom services for life science researchers, computational biologists and bioinformaticists, and life science industry suppliers
* [[Inte:Ligand]]
* [[Integromics]] is a global bioinformatics company that provides bioinformatics software for data management and data analysis in genomics and proteomics. 
* [[Invitrogen]] provides [[Vector NTI]], a desktop bioinformatics suite supporting data record handling and curation, data discovery, reagent design, and experimental validation tool sets.
* [[Korea Computer Centre Sinhung Company]]
* [[MacVector]], providing MacVector and Assembler. MacVector is a Macintosh application that provides sequence editing, primer design, internet database searching, protein analysis, sequence confirmation, multiple sequence alignment, phylogenetic reconstruction, coding region analysis, and a wide variety of other functions.
* [http://www.medhaid.com Medha Innovation and Development], is an bioinformatics company provide rAlinger and Big data analysis services in bioinformatics .
*[[ Ocimum Bio Solutions]] is a bioinformatics company with a variety of software products and also consulting practise ( bioitconsulting.com ). Commercial software available from Ocimum include Genchek, Genowiz, OptGene, iRNAchek, Ascenta, BioExpress, Genesis and Oligostar.
* [http://www.omixon.com/ Omixon BioComputing Solutions] specializes in the analysis of targeted Next Generation Sequencing data. 
* [[Premier Biosoft|PREMIER Biosoft International]] is a bioinformatics company with an expertise in software development, marketing and bioinformatics consultancy for in-silico experiment design. PREMIER Biosoft has authored software for [[PCR_primer#PCR_primer_design|pcr primer &amp; probe design]], [[DNA microarray|microarray]] design, glycan structure identificatin, plasmid map drawing and [[tissue microarray]] data analysis.
* [http://www.qfab.org/ QFAB Bioinformatics] is a bioinformatics facility that provides bioinformatics and biostatistics services for life science researchers to analyse and manage large-scale genomics, proteomics and clinical datasets.
* [[Qlucore]] Qlucore Omics Explorer is a bioinformatics software program.
* [[Rosetta Biosoftware]]
* [http://www.significo.fi Significo Research]
* [[SimBioSys]] develops the eHITS software for molecular docking (flexible ligand docking &amp; fast pre-docking), pharmacophore modelling, de novo design and retrosynthetic analysis software tools
* [[SRA International]], a systems integrator and consulting company, has a large bioinformatics practice for professional services, primarily aimed at the Federal Government market.
* [[Strand Life Sciences]] offers for micro array gene expression analysis, computational chemistry, data analysis and visualizations.
* [[TimeLogic]] offers DeCypher FPGA-accelerated [[BLAST]], [[Smith-Waterman]], [[HMMER]] and other sequence search tools.

[[Category:Bioinformatics companies]]
[[Category:Bioinformatics]]</text>
      <sha1>5w7n84up5nnfvhpvehichapyfgtym9c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>