<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Michael Stonebraker</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21888796</id>
    <revision>
      <id>540607485</id>
      <parentid>539140859</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-26T12:45:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 8 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q92758]] ([[User talk:Addbot|Report Errors]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox scientist
| name              = Michael Stonebraker
| image             = Michael Stonebraker 1.jpg
| image_size        = 
| alt               = 
| caption           = Michael Stonebraker at UC Berkeley in 2009.
| birth_date        =  {{Birth date and age|1943|10|11}} 
| birth_place       =
| death_date        = &lt;!-- {{Death date and age|YYYY|MM|DD|YYYY|MM|DD}} (death date then birth date) --&gt;
| death_place       = 
| residence         = 
| citizenship       = 
| nationality       = 
| fields            = 
| workplaces        = [[University of California, Berkeley]],&lt;br&gt;[[University of Michigan]],&lt;br&gt;[[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]
| alma_mater        = [[Princeton University]],&lt;br&gt;[[University of Michigan]]
| doctoral_advisor  = Arch Waugh Naylor
| thesis_title = The Reduction of Large Scale Markov Models for Random Chains
| thesis_url = http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=56kTMAEACAAJ
| thesis_year = 1971
| academic_advisors = 
| doctoral_students = 
| notable_students  =  [[Diane Greene]]&lt;br&gt;[[Joseph M. Hellerstein]]&lt;br&gt;[[Clifford A. Lynch]]&lt;br&gt;[[Margo Seltzer]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dale Skeen]]&lt;ref name="mathgene"&gt;{{MathGenealogy |id=31091}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
| known_for         = [[Ingres (database)|Ingres]], [[Postgres]], [[Vertica]], [[Streambase]], [[Illustra]], [[VoltDB]], [[SciDB]]
| author_abbrev_bot = 
| author_abbrev_zoo = 
| influences        = 
| influenced        = 
| awards            = 
| signature         = &lt;!--(filename only)--&gt;
| signature_alt     = 
| website = {{URL|csail.mit.edu/user/1547}}
| footnotes         = 
| spouse            = 
}}'''Michael Ralph Stonebraker''' (born October 11, 1943&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?arnumber=04309174
|format=pdf
|accessdate=2009-07-14
|publisher=IEEE
|work=TRANSACTIONS ON SYSTEMS, MAN, AND CYBERNETICS,
|title=Contributors
|year=1972
|month=Sept
}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is a [[computer scientist]] specializing in database research.
Through a series of academic prototypes and commercial startups, Stonebraker's research and products are central to many [[relational database]] systems on the market today.   He is also the founder of a number of database companies, including [[Ingres (database)|Ingres]], [[Illustra]], Cohera,  [[StreamBase Systems]], [[Vertica]], [[VoltDB]], and Paradigm4.  He was previously the [[Chief Technical Officer|Chief Technical Officer (CTO)]] of [[Informix Corporation|Informix]]. He is also an editor for the book ''Readings in Database Systems''.

Stonebraker earned his [[bachelor's degree]] from [[Princeton University]] in 1965 and his [[master's degree]] and his [[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]] from the [[University of Michigan]] in 1967 and 1971,&lt;ref name="brakerphd"&gt;{{cite thesis|degree=PhD|first=Michael Ralph |last=Stonebraker|authorlink=Michael Stonebraker|title=The Reduction of Large Scale Markov Models for Random Chains|publisher=University of Michigan|date=1971|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=56kTMAEACAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; respectively. He has received several awards, including the [[IEEE John von Neumann Medal]] and the first [[SIGMOD]] [[Edgar F. Codd]] Innovations Award. In 1994 he was inducted as a [[Fellow]] of the [[Association for Computing Machinery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://portal.acm.org/author_page.cfm?id=81337493529 |title=Michael Ralph Stonebraker - ACM author profile page |format= |work= |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1997 he was elected a member of the [[National Academy of Engineering]].

Michael Stonebraker was a Professor of Computer Science at [[University of California, Berkeley]], for twenty-nine years, where he developed the [[Ingres (database)|Ingres]] and [[Postgres]] relational database systems. He is currently an adjunct professor at [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]], where he has been involved in the development of the Aurora,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/s00778-003-0095-z}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[C-Store]], [[H-Store]], Morpheus, and SciDB systems.

== Major projects ==

Stonebraker's career can be broadly divided into two phases;  his time at Berkeley when he focused on relational systems, and the past decade at MIT where he has developed several new data management systems.

=== The Berkeley years (1971&amp;ndash;2000) ===

Stonebraker joined UC Berkeley as an assistant professor in 1971.  It was there that he did his early pioneering work on relational databases in the Ingres and Postgres projects.

==== Ingres ====
In 1973, Stonebraker and his colleague Eugene Wong decided to start researching relational database systems after reading a series of seminal papers published by [[Edgar F. Codd]] on the [[relational model|relational data model]].{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}

Their project,  known as INGRES (Interactive Graphics and Retrieval System),&lt;ref name="ingres"&gt;{{cite doi|10.1145/320473.320476}}&lt;/ref&gt; was one of the first systems (along with [[System R]] from [[International Business Machines|IBM]]) to
demonstrate that it was possible to build a practical and efficient implementation of the relational model.  A number of key ideas from INGRES are still widely used in relational systems today, including the use of B-trees, primary-copy replication, the query rewrite approach to views and [[integrity constraints]], and the idea of rules/triggers for integrity checking in an RDBMS.  Additionally, much experimental work was done that provided insights into how to build a locking system that could provide satisfactory transaction performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://redbook.cs.berkeley.edu/redbook3/lec2.html
|accessdate=2009-11-24
|publisher=Joseph Hellerstein
|title=Relational Roots
|year=1998
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the mid-1970s, Stonebraker's team had produced, using a rotating team of student programmers, a usable relational database system. At the time INGRES was considered "low end" compared to IBM's System R, as it ran on [[Unix]]-based [[Digital Equipment Corporation|DEC]] machines as opposed to the "[[big iron]]" [[IBM mainframe]]s.{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}

By the early 1980s, however, the performance and capabilities of these low-end machines were seriously threatening IBM's mainframe market, and with the threat came the ability of INGRES to become a viable, "real" product for a large number of applications. INGRES was offered using a variation of the [[BSD license]] for a nominal fee, and soon a number of companies took advantage of this to create commercial versions of INGRES.{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}

These included Stonebraker, who with fellow Berkeley professors Larry Rowe and Eugene Wong helped found Relational Technology, Inc., later called '''Ingres Corporation'''. Subsequently sold to [[Computer Associates]], Ingres was re-established as an independent company in 2005.  Other startups based on the INGRES code line include [[Sybase]], founded by Robert Epstein, a student on the INGRES project, and [[Britton Lee, Inc.]] [[Sybase]]'s code was later used as a basis for [[Microsoft SQL Server]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://redbook.cs.berkeley.edu/redbook3/lec1.html
|accessdate=2009-11-24
|publisher=Joseph Hellerstein
|title=Motivation &amp; DBMS Architecture Overview
|year=1998
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Postgres ====

After founding Relational Technology, Stonebraker and Rowe began a "post-INGRES" effort, to address the limitations of the relational model. The new project was named '''POSTGRES''' (POST inGRES),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1145/16856.16888}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was designed to add support for complex data types to database systems and improve end-to-end performance of data-intensive applications. Postgres provided an [[object-relational database|object relational]] programming model in which fields could be complex datatypes, and where users could register new types as well as scalar and aggregate functions over those types. POSTGRES was extensible in a number of other ways, making it easy for programmers to modify or add to the optimizer, query language, runtime, and indexing frameworks. These features improved both database programmability and performance, and made it possible to push large portions of a number of applications inside the database, including [[GIS|geographic information systems]] and [[time series|time series processing]].  This had the effect of substantially broadening the commercial database market.

POSTGRES was also offered using a BSD-like license, and the code forms the basis of today's [[free software]], [[PostgreSQL]].
Stonebraker also led an effort to commercialize the code, creating '''Illustra''' which was purchased by [[Informix]]. PostgreSQL has been used as the basis for a number of other startup companies, including [[Aster Data Systems]], [[EnterpriseDB]], and [[Greenplum]].

[[Informix]] acquired Illustra in 1996, and Stonebraker became Informix's CTO, a position he held until September 2000.

[[Informix]] integrated Illustra's O-R mapping and [[DataBlade]]s into the 7.x OnLine product, resulting in Informix Universal Server (IUS), or more generally, Version 9.

==== Mariposa and Cohera ====

After the Postgres project, Stonebraker initiated the Mariposa&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/s007780050015}}&lt;/ref&gt; project which became the basis of Cohera Corporation.  The main idea behind Mariposa was to build a [[federated database]] over an economic model of resource trading, in which data distributed across multiple organizations could be integrated and queried from a single relational interface, governed by site-specific policies that would charge for data processing and storage.  These economic policies allowed traditional ideas in [[query optimization]] to be carried out over competing sites, and also served as the basis for data storage, replication and movement within a federation.

Cohera's initial mission was to commercialize ideas from the Mariposa project, but eventually focused on a Business-to-Business Catalog Management application implemented on top of the core federated data integration engine. Cohera's intellectual property was purchased by [[PeopleSoft]] in 2001,
and used as the basis of PeopleSoft's Enterprise Catalog Management.  PeopleSoft was in turn purchased by [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]] in 2004.

=== The MIT years (2001&amp;ndash;Present) ===

Stonebraker moved to MIT in 2001, where he began another series of research projects and founded a number of companies.

==== Aurora and StreamBase ====

In the [http://www.cs.brown.edu/research/aurora/ Aurora Project], Stonebraker, along with colleagues from [[Brandeis University]], [[Brown University]], and [[MIT]], focused on data management for streaming data, using a new data model and query language.  Unlike relational systems, which "pull" data and process it a record at a time, in Aurora, data is "pushed", arriving asynchronously from external data sources (such as stock ticks, news feeds, or sensors.)  The output is itself a stream of results (such as windowed averages) that are sent to users.

Stonebraker co-founded [[StreamBase Systems]] in 2003 to commercialize the technology behind Aurora.

==== C-Store and Vertica ====
In the [[C-Store]] project, started in 2005, Stonebraker, along with colleagues from [[Brandeis University]], [[Brown University]], [[MIT]], and [[University of Massachusetts Boston]], developed a parallel, shared-nothing [[column-oriented DBMS]] for data warehousing.  By dividing and storing data in columns, C-Store is able to perform less I/O and get better compression ratios than conventional database systems that store data in rows.

In 2005, Stonebraker co-founded [[Vertica]] to commercialize the technology behind C-Store{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}.

==== Morpheus and Goby ====
In 2006, Stonebraker started the Morpheus project, along with researchers from the University of Florida.  Morpheus is a [[data integration]] system which relies on a collection of "transforms" to [[Data mediation|mediate]] between data sources.  Each transform provides a queryable interface to particular web site or service, and Morpheus makes it possible to search for and compose multiple transforms to provide a new service or a unified view of several services.

In 2009, Stonebraker co-founded Goby,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.goby.com/ | title = Goby}}.&lt;/ref&gt; a [[Local search (Internet)|local search]] company based on ideas from Morpheus, for people to explore new things to do in free time.

==== H-Store and VoltDB ====

In 2007, with researchers from [[Brown University]], [[MIT]], and [[Yale University]], Stonebraker started the [http://hstore.cs.brown.edu/ H-Store] project.  [[H-Store]] is a distributed main-memory [[online transaction processing|OLTP]] system designed to provide very high throughput on transaction processing workloads.

In 2009, Stonebraker co-founded, and currently serves as CTO of, [[VoltDB]] a commercial startup based on ideas from the [[H-Store]] project.

==== SciDB ====

In 2008, along with [[David DeWitt]] and researchers from [[Brown University]], [[MIT]], [[Portland State University]], [[SLAC]],  the [[University of Washington]],  and the [[University of Wisconsin-Madison]], Stonebraker started [[SciDB]] &lt;ref name="scidb"&gt;{{cite doi|10.1145/1807167.1807271}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="scidb2"&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/978-3-642-22351-8_1}}&lt;/ref&gt; an open-source DBMS specially designed for scientific research applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/09/13/michael_stonebraker_interview/
 | title=SciDB: Relational daddy answers Google, Hadoop, NoSQL
 | work=The Register
 | author=
 | date=2010-09-13
 | accessdate=2012-01-11 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==== NoSQL ====
More recently, during 2010 and 2011, Stonebraker has been a critic of the [[NoSQL]] movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1145/1721654.1721659}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1145/1978542.1978546}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1145/1629175.1629197}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Students==
In addition to his contributions to academia and industry, Stonebraker has trained more than 30 students who have themselves contributed significantly to academia and industry. Notable students include:&lt;ref name="mathgene"/&gt;
* Michael J. Carey (faculty at UC Irvine, formerly at U. Wisconsin Madison, NAE Member and ACM Fellow),
* Robert Epstein (founder and former VP of Engineering of [[Sybase]])
* [[Diane Greene]] (co-founder and former CEO of [[VMWare]])
* Paula Hawthorn (founder of Britton-Lee, formerly VP of Engineering of [[Informix]])
* Gerald Held (former VP of Engineering of [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]])
* [[Joseph M. Hellerstein]] (faculty at UC Berkeley)
* Anant Jhingran (VP and CTO for [[IBM]]'s Information Management Division)
* Curt Kolovson (Sr. Staff Research Scientist at [[VMware]])
* [[Clifford A. Lynch]] (executive director of the [[Coalition for Networked Information]])
* Mike Olson, former CEO of [[Sleepycat Software]] and current CEO of [[Cloudera]]
* [[Margo Seltzer]] (Professor of Computer Science at Harvard, founder and former CTO of [[Sleepycat]])
* [[Dale Skeen]] (founder of [[Tibco]], founder and CEO of [http://www.vitria.com/ Vitria])
* Daniel Abadi, (co-founder and Chief Scientist of [http://www.hadapt.com Hadapt])
* Marti Hearst (Professor at UC Berkeley)

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*{{Cite web
|url=http://s2k-ftp.cs.berkeley.edu/nasa_e2e/mike.html
|date=1995-12-23
|title=Michael Stonebraker | publisher = University of California | location = Berkeley, CA, USA
|accessdate=2009-07-14
}}
*{{Cite web
|url=http://www.csail.mit.edu/user/1547
|title=Michael Stonebraker
|work=User Profiles
|publisher=MIT | location = MA, USA
|date=2009-07-09
|accessdate=2009-07-14
}}
* {{Citation | url = http://www.dbms2.com/category/michael-stonebraker/ | chapter = Michael Stonebraker | title = DBMS2 | last = Monash | first = Curt}}, a series of recent interviews and comments about and by Stonebraker.
*{{Cite web
|url=http://publications.csail.mit.edu/abstracts/abstracts07/stonebraker-abstract1/stonebraker-abstract1.html
|title=Morpheus: A Data Integration Toolkit
|work= CSAIL Research Abstracts | publisher = MIT | location = MA, USA
|accessdate=2009-11-22
}}
* {{Citation | url = http://www.goby.com/ | title = Goby}}, a new search engine to find fun things to do in one’s free time (co-founded by Stonebraker)

{{Authority control|VIAF=92584235}}
{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Stonebraker, Michael
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = American computer scientist
| DATE OF BIRTH     =1943-10-11
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Stonebraker, Michael}}
[[Category:American computer scientists]]
[[Category:Database researchers]]
[[Category:American computer businesspeople]]
[[Category:Princeton University alumni]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Association for Computing Machinery]]
[[Category:SIGMOD Edgar F. Codd Innovations Award winners]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1943 births]]
[[Category:Informix]]</text>
      <sha1>bhunnl002fr1hrylt6owlf5jjbaphpq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>