<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Wikipedia:Contributor copyright investigations/Barnstarbob</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>37818398</id>
    <revision>
      <id>537176250</id>
      <parentid>537170788</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-08T06:29:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MER-C</username>
        <id>1749459</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>closing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{NOINDEX|visible=yes}}
{{divbox|fawn|Contributor copyright investigation|
This [[WP:CCI|CCI]] cleanup subpage has been opened because concerns of multiple point infringement have been substantiated and further steps are necessary to address the serious risk of [[Wikipedia:Copyright violation|copyright violation]] from the listed contributor. Listings are not intended to imply a presumption of bad faith on the part of any contributor, as copyright laws vary widely around the world and many contributors who violate [[WP:C|Wikipedia's copyrights policy]] do so inadvertently through not understanding it or the United States' laws that govern it.

'''If you are here because of a note on an article's talk page explaining removal of text''', please do not restore any removed text without first ensuring that the text does not duplicate, closely paraphrase or plagiarize from a previously published source. You are welcome to use sourced facts that may have been removed to create new content in your own words or to incorporate brief quotations of copyrighted material in accordance with [[WP:NFC|the non-free content policy and guideline]].}}

==Instructions==
'''All contributors with no history of copyright problems are welcome to contribute to clean up.''' 

''If contributors have been shown to have a history of extensive copyright violation, it may be assumed without further evidence that all of their major contributions are copyright violations, and they may be removed indiscriminately in accordance with [[Wikipedia:Copyright violations]].'' However, to avoid collateral damage, efforts should be made when possible to verify infringement before removal. 

When every section is completed, please alter the listing for this CCI at [[Wikipedia:CCI#Open_investigations]] to include the tag "completed=yes". This will alert a clerk that the listing needs to be archived.
*&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{CCI-open|Contributor name|Day Month Year|completed=yes}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;

===Images===
*Examine the images below. For free images:
**Does the image look non-free? Is it likely the uploader is the copyright holder?
**Is the image properly licensed and sourced? Be aware of images that say "this image is licensed under X" without specifying who created it.
**Do a reverse image search using [[Google Images]]. Check the license of the source page. Compare the last modified time with the (Commons) upload time.
**Do a Google image search for phrases that describe the image's contents.
**See [[Wikipedia:Guide to image deletion#Addressing suspected copyright infringement]] on dealing with cases of possible image copyright infringement. There is no need to open a [[WP:PUF|possibly unfree files]] listing. Administrators may delete images from multiple point infringers presumptively in accordance with [[Wikipedia:Copyright violations]]. Evaluators who are not administrators may section images into a "deletion requested" section for administrator attention.

*For non-free images, determine whether each image meets our [[WP:NFCC|non-free content criteria]].
**Note that Commons does not accept non-free content.
*Annotate the listing with the action taken, e.g. if the image was tagged no source write "no source"; if the fair use claim is deemed ok you can write "OK fair use".

==Background==
&lt;div class="boilerplate metadata" style="{{divstyleblue}}; padding: 0.1em;"&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;font size="3"&gt;'''Barnstarbob'''&lt;/font&gt;
*{{User5|Barnstarbob}}
*{{User5|Vegavairbob}}
*Reported by [[User:George Ho|George Ho]] ([[User talk:George Ho|talk]])
*Now that this user is blocked indefinitely for sockpuppetry, there are uploads that are tagged as public domain. However, this user made no adequate proof that "PD" images are either free or unfree. [[:File:55 Chevy BelAir.jpg]] is tagged as possibly unfree, and his talk page has [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Barnstarbob&amp;oldid=526085577 many notices about possibly-unfree files]. [[User:George Ho|George Ho]] ([[User talk:George Ho|talk]]) 23:49, 2 December 2012 (UTC)
&lt;/div&gt;

__NOINDEX__
{{ombox |image=[[File:Wikipedia-logo-blank.svg|40px]] |text= This page has been [[Wikipedia:Deletion policy#Courtesy blanking|blanked as a courtesy]][[Template:Courtesy blanked|.]] 
}}</text>
      <sha1>snnhdfsbyiwv2nnzfrlkmdsajy6bpdv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>