<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>WiseWindow</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30741710</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532504232</id>
      <parentid>501198851</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-01-11T07:26:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BG19bot</username>
        <id>14508071</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fix for #61.  Punctuation goes before References. Do [[Wikipedia:GENFIXES|general fixes]] if a problem exists. - using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8853)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=May 2011}}

{{Infobox company
| company_name = WiseWindow
| company_logo = [[Image:Wisewindow logo.png|180px]] |
| type =
| founded = 2007
| location = Orange County, CA
| key_people = Rajiv Dulepet, CIO and Founder

Marshall Toplansky, President
Sid Mohasseb, CEO
| products = MOBI
| num_employees = 20
| homepage = http://www.wisewindow.com/
}}

'''WiseWindow''' is a private [[data]] provider of unstructured "big data" sentiment, used in real-time business intelligence. The company, now part of KPMG is based in [[Irvine, California]] and has 25 full-time employees. WiseWindow's patented [[web analytics]] system, Mass Opinion Business Intelligence (MOBI) analyzes and classifies comments made online and distills the information into a pre-defined, structured database. The company has shown "the predictive value of cluster analysis by applying it to social media content."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/2010/07/26/cluster-analysis-predictions-technology-social-media.html The Predictive Power Of Social Media - Forbes.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Products ==
MOBI methodology combines online measurement, cloud computing and market research that provides live consumer sentiment data around brands, products and purchase influencing factors using decision-supported information from millions of unsolicited opinions. WiseWindow’s MOBI is used by companies in the airline, alcoholic beverage, automotive, consumer electronic, health care, news media, entertainment, political and retail industries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.readwriteweb.com/enterprise/2010/01/social-media-is-a-poor-label-f.php&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tmcnet.com/voip/0410/a-look-into-the-mind-wisewindow-leverages-open-source-cloud-computing-to-gauge-opinions.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

MOBI VIBES 3.0 visualization tools were launched in November 2011. MOBI combines cloud computing, deep website crawling, relevance recognition and statistical natural language analysis to allow business decision makers to quickly get a real-time look at their brands and their competitive set. By collecting, analyzing and classifying the billions of unbiased consumer comments made online annually from across the web, MOBI distills the data into a usable form providing an up-to-the-minute view of consumer sentiment.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}.  It lets users view sentiment data by demographic, geographic and attitudinal segment, and provides a normalized benchmark of sentiment within a vertical market through its MOBI Sentiment Index.

== History ==
WiseWindow began developing its core technology in 2007, based on the work of its founder, Rajiv Dulapet, while he was a research fellow at Stanford University. The premise of WiseWindow is to utilize mass opinions expressed on the Internet to develop business intelligence that is useful to companies and to develop more accurate forecasts of consumer behavior.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wisewindow.com/index.php?option=com_k2&amp;view=item&amp;layout=item&amp;id=49&amp;Itemid=106&lt;/ref&gt;

WiseWindow acquired the marketing research firm Core Strategies in 2009, which was founded by Marshall Toplansky. With the acquisition, the company adapted and productized its technology to be able to  calibrate  Mass Opinion Business Intelligence (MOBI) data with traditional forms of quantitative and qualitative market research, and provide on-going tracking metrics that are of use to marketers and operating management within client companies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pr.com/press-release/132492&lt;/ref&gt;

KPMG acquired Wise Window in April, 2012.  The three co-founders have integrated Wise Window's MOBI technology into KPMG's data analytics practice. The financial terms of the acquisition were not made public.

== Partnerships ==
During the 2010 mid-term elections WiseWindow partnered with political blog [[The Daily Beast]] to present the "Election Oracle" which used MOBI technology to accurately predict 36 of the 37 Senate races and 98% of the House races.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-11-08/midterm-election-results-internet-predicted-outcomes/ Midterm Election Results: Internet Predicted Outcomes - The Daily Beast&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; They also teamed up with The Daily Beast to create the "Oscar Oracle" to predict the outcome of the 2011 Academy Awards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thedailybeast.com/newsmaker/awards-countdown/?cid=sexybeast:mainpromo1 Awards Countdown - The Daily Beast&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Wise Window election data is being used by both Reuters and CNN for the 2012 presidential election.

== Awards ==
In 2009, WiseWindow won the Edison Award for Best New Product for its mass opinion brand tracking system.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.edisonawards.com/Winners2009.php Edison Awards 2010 honoring innovation in the development and launch of new products and services&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, WiseWindow's MOBI won the TechAmerica Orange County High-Tech Innovation Award in the Internet E-Commerce category.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.techamerica.org/htaoc&lt;/ref&gt;  Also, it won an award for innovation in the internet arena from the University of Pennsylvania Wharton School.

== References ==
&lt;!--- See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{official website|wisewindow.com}}

[[Category:Business intelligence companies]]</text>
      <sha1>1akawg4mdwf4nto8uarhldimr8ehj9z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>