<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Altoros</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23396970</id>
    <revision>
      <id>527819432</id>
      <parentid>523012370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-12-13T05:43:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Aboutmovies</username>
        <id>2602832</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed [[Category:Companies based in Massachusetts]]; added [[Category:Companies based in Sunnyvale, California]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company|
  company_name   = Altoros Systems|
  company_logo = [[File:Altoros Logo.gif|209px|]]|
  type   = [[Privately held companies]]|
  foundation     = 2001 |
  location_city    = [[Sunnyvale, California]] |
  location_country = [[United States]] |
  num_employees  =  over 200 (Q1, 2012)|
  key_people       = Renat Khasanshyn (CEO), Andrei Yurkevich (President) [http://altoros.com/management_team.html]|
  industry       = [[Software Product Line|Software Product Development]]&lt;br&gt; [[Big Data]]   |
  Website       = [http://www.altoros.com/ Altoros Official Site]}}

'''Altoros Systems''' (also spelled as "Altoros" or "Альторос") is a global software product development company. Headquartered in [[Silicon Valley]], the company runs offices in U.S., Norway, Denmark,&lt;ref&gt;[http://altoros.com/pdf/altoros_midtjyllandsavis.pdf Silicon Valley og Silkeborg Valley] - [[:da:Midtjyllands Avis|Midtjyllands Avis]], a Danish daily newspaper, publishes an article about Altoros, settled down recently in Silkeborg Valley. {{Language icon|da}}&lt;/ref&gt; UK,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mobiletoday.co.uk/News/14285/ISellMobile_launches_free_app.aspx "ISellMobile launches free app"] An article in the Mobile Magazine by Noble House Media, the famous UK publisher of mobile magazines, mentions contribution of Altoros to iSellMobile, a free app&lt;/ref&gt; Argentina, Ukraine, and Belarus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dir.salon.com/story/tech/feature/2004/04/06/offshoring_bad/index1.html "When Offshoring Goes Bad"], An article by Salon (a part of [[Associated Press|The Associated Press]]) about outsourcing, mentioning Altoros as an opposite to bad offshoring (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="open-source"&gt;[http://www.masshightech.com/stories/2007/07/16/story12-Young-software-exec-moves-to-open-source-model.html "Young software exec moves to open source model"] Mass High Tech, a business journal in New England, interviews the CEO of Altoros about the history of Apatar and Altoros.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4qlf3tgI8Dk "TechZulu interviews Renat Khasanshyn of Altoros Systems"](2008)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="global"&gt;[http://www.ecommercetimes.com/story/32929.html High-Tech R&amp;D: Too Vital To Outsource?], Renat Khasanshyn, Altoros's CEO, speaks about the business model of his company in an E-commerce Times article, a resource of ECT News Network&lt;/ref&gt;

The company actively supports and brings up technology communities in Northern and Eastern Europe by organizing related non-commercial events (such as [[CloudCamp]], [[user group]] meetings, [[hackathon|hackathons]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://article.techlabs.by/50_31285.html "$1000 за 24 часа: в Минске проходит хакатон hacby’11 web&amp;mobile"] A report from the first [[hackathon]] in Belarus, which was organized by Altoros {{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; etc.), participating in IT conferences as a speaker or expert,&lt;ref&gt;«Открытые технологии. Материалы 7-й международной конференции Linux Vacation / Eastern Europe 2011», Брест «Альтернатива» 2011, ISBN 978-985-521-251-6: This science publication features Altoros's presentation of Cells.js and interview with its author, who compares the work at Altoros and in Silicon Valley (pp. 6-8, pp.127-130). {{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="adobe-conf"&gt;[http://netnews.by/2009/05/09/adobe-3-dnya-i-6-dokladov-skoro Adobe: "3 дня и 6 докладов."], Local IT news resource writes about a 3-day conference held by Adobe and arranged by Altoros. {{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; and running free educational courses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.techlabs.by/14_68899.html "В Минске обсудили перспективы Ruby on Rails"] A piece of news about a free seminar on Ruby on Rails organized by Altoros{{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ruby_courses"&gt;[http://it.tut.by/233563 "Altoros предлагает веб-разработчикам бесплатные курсы по Ruby on Rails"] TUT.by, the largest news portal in Belarus, writes about the training course for Ruby on Rails developers arranged by Altoros {{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

Altoros was founded in 2001. 

In February 2007, Altoros launched [[Apatar]], a Java-based open source [[data integration]] product used by 21,000+ companies worldwide and driven by a global community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/082307-open-source-to-watch.html “Open Source Companies to Watch”], NetworkWorld, one of global [[IDG]]’s magazines, describes the intersection between [[Apatar]] and Altoros.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://connectedsocialmedia.com/2914/meeting-the-geek-behind-apatar/ "Meeting the geek behind Apatar"] [[Robert Scoble]] interviews CEO of Altoros about the community behind [[Apatar]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/whitepaper/Software/Integration/informationweek-associate-editor-elena-malykhina-interviews-renet-khasanshyn-ceo-of-apatar-a-maker-of-data-integration-software-wp1213673450988 "InformationWeek associate editor Elena Malykhina interviews Renat Khasanshyn"] InformationWeek interviews CEO of Altoros on the launch of [[Apatar]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, Altoros also founded Belarus Java User Group, which unites Java developers in Belarus and lists more than 500 Java specialists.

In July, 2008, Altoros became a resident of [[Belarus High Technologies Park]], a business environment for IT companies in Eastern Europe that forces cooperation in IT on the inter-governmental level.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radiobelarus.tvr.by/eng/news.asp?type=cont&amp;id=10003&amp;date=02.12.2008 "NHN, Korea's largest Internet company, is interested in establishing cooperation with Belarus' High-Tech Park"] National TV and Radio of Belarus about the meeting of [[NHN Corporation]] with Altoros and other HTP residents of High-Tech Park&lt;/ref&gt;

In August, 2011, the company launched free educational Ruby on Rails training course for developers&lt;ref name="ruby_courses" /&gt; in Eastern Europe.

On October 11, 2011, Altoros organized the first [[CloudCamp]] in Denmark. The first CloudCamp in Eastern Europe was held on April 7, 2012, in Minsk, Belarus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://it.tut.by/280362 В Минске прошел первый в Беларуси CloudCamp], TUT.by, the largest news portal in Belarus, reports about the first CloudCamp in Eastern Europe, which was organized by Altoros. {{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2008, Altoros has been arranging a variety of conferences and other events for IT specialists in Belarus, featuring Microsoft,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nestor.minsk.by/kg/news/2009/03/1118.html “Официальная презентация Microsoft Silverlight 3.0 в Беларуси”], One of the largest printed IT media in Belarus announces two educational seminars from Microsoft organized by Altoros {{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adobe,&lt;ref name="adobe-conf"&gt;[http://netnews.by/2009/05/09/adobe-3-dnya-i-6-dokladov-skoro Adobe: "3 дня и 6 докладов."], Local IT news resource informs about a conference featuring Adobe arranged by Altoros. {{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; SUN Microsystems,&lt;ref&gt;[http://kv.minsk.by/index2009252102.htm “Круглый стол по Java в Минске”], One of the largest printed IT newspaper in Belarus writes about a free seminar on Java organized by Altoros {{Language icon|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Engine Yard representatives as speakers. Altoros's in-house experts also speak at local IT events across both Europe and US very frequently, sharing their experience in big data, cloud computing, cross-platform app development, etc.

== Supporting Technology Community ==

Altoros is a founder of Belarus [[Java User Group]], which unites Java developers in Belarus and lists more than 500 Java specialists. In 2010, Altoros developers co-founded Belarus Ruby on Rails User Group. Altoros is also a partner of Belarus .NET User Group, Belarus Adobe Flash Platform User Group, Belarus Microsoft Certified Professional Club, and Belarus Open Source Lab.

Altoros is founder of [[Apatar]], open source data integration project used by 21,000+ companies worldwide, and is an active contributor to other open source initiatives such as [[Couchbase Server]].

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
# {{Official website|1=http://www.altoros.com|name=Altoros's Official Website}}
# [http://www.altoros.no Altoros Norge]
# [http://www.altoros.dk Altoros Danmark]
# [http://www.youtube.com/altorossystems Altoros’s YouTube Channel: events, presentations, etc.]
# [http://www.belarusjug.org Belarus Java User Group]
# [http://www.belarusdotnet.org Belarus .NET User Group]
# [http://www.belarusrubyonrails.org Belarus Ruby on Rails User Group] 
# [http://bafpug.com/ Belarus Adobe Flash Platform User Group] 
# [http://mcpclub.com/ Belarus Microsoft Certified Professional Club] 

[[Category:Software companies based in California]]
[[Category:Software companies of Belarus]]
[[Category:Companies established in 2001]]
[[Category:2001 establishments in Belarus]]
[[Category:Companies based in Sunnyvale, California]]
[[Category:Companies based in Silicon Valley]]</text>
      <sha1>gfumqs9k4ce91zbx6oimkee7v1k9ngy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>