<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Amazon S3</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5962343</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562557309</id>
      <parentid>562557179</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-02T15:24:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Raspalchima</username>
        <id>2807585</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>/* Amazon S3 file transfer and archiving */ updated text link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox website
| name                   = Amazon Simple Storage Service
| logo                   = [[File:AWS Simple Icons Storage Amazon S3 Bucket with Objects.svg]]
| logocaption            = An S3 Bucket with Objects
| type                   = [[Remote backup service|Online backup service]] 
| language               = [[English language|English]]
| current status         = Active
| url                    = {{url|http://aws.amazon.com/s3/}}
| ipv6                   = No
| commercial             = Yes 
| registration           = Required
| owner                  = [[Amazon.com]]
| launch date            = March 14, 2006
}}

'''Amazon S3''' ('''Simple Storage Service''') is an [[online file storage]] [[web service]] offered by [[Amazon Web Services]]. Amazon S3 provides storage through [[web service]]s interfaces ([[REST]], [[SOAP]], and [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]]).&lt;ref&gt;http://aws.amazon.com/s3/&lt;/ref&gt; Amazon launched S3, its first publicly available web service, in the United States in March 2006&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
| publisher = [[Amazon.com]]
| date = 2006-03-14
| title = Amazon Web Services Launches "Amazon S3"
| url = http://phx.corporate-ir.net/phoenix.zhtml?c=176060&amp;p=irol-newsArticle&amp;ID=830815
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in Europe in November 2007.&lt;ref name="s3-europe"&gt;{{cite news
| work = Dr. Dobb's Portal
| last = Dorsey
| first = John
| title = Amazon S3 Storage Now Available in Europe
| url = http://www.ddj.com/architect/202803151
| date = 2007-11-06
| accessdate = 2008-03-26
| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080415024818/http://www.ddj.com/architect/202803151| archivedate= 15 April 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At its inception, Amazon charged end users [[United States dollar|US$]]0.15 per gigabyte-month, with additional charges for bandwidth used in sending and receiving data, and a per-request (get or put) charge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher = [[Amazon.com]]|date=2009-02-05|title= Amazon Simple Storage Service pricing|url=http://aws.amazon.com/s3/#pricing}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of November 1, 2008, pricing moved to tiers where end users storing more than 50 [[terabyte]]s receive discounted pricing.&lt;ref name=busier&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = [[Amazon.com]]
| date = 2008-10-08
| title = Amazon S3 - Busier Than Ever
| url = http://aws.typepad.com/aws/2008/10/amazon-s3---now.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amazon claims that S3 uses the same scalable storage infrastructure that Amazon.com uses to run its own global e-commerce network.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/gp/browse.html?node=16427261 The same data storage infrastructure that Amazon uses to run its own global network of web sites]&lt;/ref&gt;

Amazon S3 is reported to store more than a trillion objects {{as of|2012|06|lc=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aws.typepad.com/aws/2012/06/amazon-s3-the-first-trillion-objects.html - Amazon S3 - The First Trillion Objects]&lt;/ref&gt; This is up from 102 billion objects {{as of|2010|3|lc=on}},&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.datacenterknowledge.com/archives/2010/03/09/amazon-s3-now-hosts-100-billion-objects/ Brian Lillie of Equinix said that Amazon now is hosting 102 billion objects in S3]&lt;/ref&gt; 64 billion objects in August 2009,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Cloud-Computing/Amazons-Head-Start-in-the-Cloud-Pays-Off-584083/ S3 (Amazon's Simple Storage Service) alone has over 64 billion objects in it.]&lt;/ref&gt; 52 billion in March 2009,&lt;ref&gt;[http://aws.typepad.com/aws/2009/03/celebrating-s3s-third-birthday-with-an-upload-promotion.html Just a year ago, there were 18 billion objects in S3. As of today there are 52 billion]&lt;/ref&gt; 29 billion in October 2008,&lt;ref name=busier /&gt; 14 billion in January 2008, and 10 billion in October 2007.&lt;ref name="amzn-cto-blog"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.allthingsdistributed.com/2008/03/happy_birthday_amazon_s3.html
|author=Vogels, Werner
|work=All Things Distributed
|date = 2008-03-19
|title=Happy Birthday, Amazon S3!}}&lt;/ref&gt; S3 uses include web hosting, image hosting, and storage for backup systems. S3 comes with a 99.9% monthly uptime guarantee&lt;ref&gt;[http://aws.amazon.com/s3-sla/ Amazon S3 SLA]&lt;/ref&gt; which equates to approximately 43 minutes of downtime per month.&lt;ref&gt;60 min/hour * 24 hours in a day * 30 days * 0.1% = 43.2&lt;/ref&gt;

== Design ==

Details of S3's design are not made public by Amazon. According to Amazon, S3's design aims to provide [[scalability]], [[high availability]], and [[low latency]] at [[commodity computing|commodity]] costs.

S3 is designed to provide 99.999999999% durability and 99.99% availability of objects over a given year,&lt;ref&gt;[http://aws.amazon.com/s3/#protecting Amazon S3 Protecting Your Data]&lt;/ref&gt; though there is no [[Service-level agreement|SLA]] for durability.

S3 stores arbitrary objects ([[computer file]]s) up to 5 [[terabyte]]s in size, each accompanied by up to 2 [[kilobytes]] of [[metadata]]. Objects are organized into ''buckets'' (each owned by an [[Amazon Web Services]]  account), and identified within each bucket by a unique, user-assigned key. [[Amazon Machine Image|Amazon Machine Images (AMIs)]] which are used in the [[Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud|Elastic Compute Cloud]] (EC2) can be exported to S3 as bundles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://techblog.aasisvinayak.com/starting-websphere-in-cloud-and-saving-the-data-in-s3/ Starting Websphere in Cloud and saving the data in S3]&lt;/ref&gt;

Buckets and objects can be created, listed, and retrieved using either a [[Representational State Transfer|REST]]-style [[Hypertext Transfer Protocol|HTTP]] interface or a [[SOAP (protocol)|SOAP]] interface. Additionally, objects can be downloaded using the HTTP GET interface and the [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]] protocol.

Requests are authorized using an [[access control list]] associated with each bucket and object.

Bucket names and keys are chosen so that objects are addressable using HTTP [[Uniform Resource Locator|URL]]s:

* &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http://&lt;/nowiki&gt;s3.amazonaws.com/''bucket''/''key''&lt;/code&gt;
* &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http://&lt;/nowiki&gt;''bucket''.s3.amazonaws.com/''key''&lt;/code&gt;
* &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http://&lt;/nowiki&gt;''bucket''/''key''&lt;/code&gt; (where ''bucket'' is a [[Domain name system|DNS]] CNAME record pointing to &lt;tt&gt;bucket.s3.amazonaws.com&lt;/tt&gt;)

Because objects are accessible by unmodified HTTP clients, S3 can be used to replace significant existing (static) [[web hosting service|web hosting]] infrastructure.&lt;ref name="S3 Web Hosting"&gt;[http://www.bucketexplorer.com/documentation/amazon-s3--how-to-use-Amazon-s3-for-web-hosting.html How to use Amazon S3 for Web Hosting]&lt;/ref&gt; The Amazon AWS Authentication mechanism allows the bucket owner to create an authenticated URL with time-bounded validity. That is, someone can construct a URL that can be handed off to a third-party for access for a period such as the next 30 minutes, or the next 24 hours.

Every item in a bucket can also be served up as a [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]] feed. The S3 store can act as a seed host for a torrent and any BitTorrent client can retrieve the file. This drastically reduces the bandwidth costs for the download of popular objects. While the use of BitTorrent does reduce bandwidth, AWS does not provide native bandwidth limiting and as such users have no access to automated cost control. This can lead to users on the 'free-tier' S3 or small hobby users amassing dramatic bills. AWS representatives have previously stated that such a feature was on the design table from 2006 to 2010&lt;ref&gt;https://forums.aws.amazon.com/thread.jspa?threadID=10532&amp;start=0&amp;tstart=0&lt;/ref&gt; but have recently stated the feature is no longer in development.&lt;ref&gt;https://forums.aws.amazon.com/thread.jspa?threadID=58127&amp;tstart=75&lt;/ref&gt;

A bucket can be configured to save HTTP log information to a sibling bucket; this can be used in later [[data mining]] operations. This feature is currently still in beta.

== Hosting entire websites ==

Amazon S3 provides options to host static websites with Index document support and error document support.&lt;ref&gt;http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/index.html?WebsiteHosting.html&lt;/ref&gt; This support was added as a result of user requests dating at least to 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://developer.amazonwebservices.com/connect/thread.jspa?messageID=153951&amp;#153951 |title=Re: default key or 'default document' - is it possible to specify in S3? |author=Garnaat, Mitch, | date=19 Nov 2009 | accessdate=21 Sep 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, suppose that Amazon S3 was configured with CNAME records to host &lt;nowiki&gt;http://subdomain.example.com/&lt;/nowiki&gt;. In the past, a visitor to this URL would find only an XML-formatted list of objects instead of a general landing page (e.g., index.html) to accommodate casual visitors. Now, however, websites hosted on S3 may designate a default page to display, and another page to display in the event of a partially invalid URL.

== Notable uses ==

&lt;!-- please have a very notable use here, not another disk backup service. --&gt;

Photo hosting service [[SmugMug]] has used S3 since April 2006. They experienced a number of initial outages and slowdowns, but after one year they described it as being "considerably more reliable than our own internal storage" and claimed to have saved almost $1 million in storage costs.&lt;ref name="smugmug-smtm"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.smugmug.com/don/2006/11/10/amazon-s3-show-me-the-money/|work=SmugMug Blog|publisher=SmugMug|date=November 10, 2006|title=Amazon S3: Show Me the Money}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are various [[Filesystem in Userspace|User Mode File System (FUSE)]]-based file systems for Unix-like operating systems (Linux, etc.) that can be used to mount an S3 bucket as a file system. Note that as the semantics of the S3 file system are not that of a [[Posix]] file system, the file system may not behave entirely as expected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://code.google.com/p/s3ql/wiki/other_s3_filesystems
 | title=Comparison of S3QL and other S3 file systems
 | accessdate=2012-06-29 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hadoop|Apache Hadoop]] file systems can be hosted on S3, as its requirements of a file system are met by S3. As a result, Hadoop can be used to run [[MapReduce]] algorithms on EC2 servers, reading data and writing results back to S3.

[[Dropbox (storage provider)|Dropbox]],&lt;ref name="dropbox-files"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.dropbox.com/help/7|date=November 28, 2010|title=Where are my files stored?}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bitcasa]],&lt;ref name="Bitcasa Legal"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bitcasa.com/legal|date=May 16, 2013|title=Bitcasa Legal}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[StoreGrid]], [[Jumpshare]], SyncBlaze,&lt;ref name="SyncBlaze Uses Amazon S3"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.vembu.com/launching-cloud-content-management-service-for-channel-partners-syncblaze/ |title=Where SyncBlaze Cloud stores my files?}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tahoe-LAFS]]-on-S3,&lt;ref name="Tahoe-LAFS-on-S3"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://leastauthority.com/products|date=August 21, 2012|title=What is Tahoe-LAFS-on-S3?}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Zmanda]] and [[Ubuntu One]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ubuntu One Technical Details|url=https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuOne/TechnicalDetails|publisher=Ubuntu.com|accessdate=16 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  are some of the many online backup and synchronization services that use S3 as their storage and transfer facility.

[[Minecraft]] hosts game updates and player skins on the S3 servers.&lt;ref name="minecraft-skins"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://notch.tumblr.com/post/2857128986/minecraft-beta-1-2-02|date=January 21, 2010|title=Minecraft Beta 1.2_02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Tumblr]], [[Formspring]], [[Pinterest]], and [[Posterous]] images are hosted on the S3 servers.

[[Alfresco (software)]] the OpenSource [[Enterprise Content Management]] provider are hosting data for the Alfresco in the cloud service on S3.

S3 was used in the past by some enterprises as a long term archiving solution, until [[Amazon Glacier]] was released.{{cn|date=June 2013}}

== Amazon S3 file transfer and archiving ==

Amazon S3 (Simple Storage Service) can be used for a wide variety of uses, ranging from Web applications to media files, to store and retrieve any amount of data, at any time, from anywhere on the Web, and gives users the same highly scalable, reliable, secure, fast, inexpensive infrastructure that Amazon uses to run its own global network of websites.

Although Amazon S3 storage is very reliable, the problem with using its Web interface for uploads/downloads is that it is very slow and can be unreliable. The Amazon S3 Transfer Engine &lt;ref&gt;Amazon S3 Transfer Engine[http://www.bbconsult.co.uk/Resources/AmazonS3TransferEngine.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt; is a free tool developed using .NET technology for Amazon S3 file transfer and archiving that works 24 hours a day, 7 days a week, in any Windows environment, and without the need for user intervention. The tool makes use of the multi-part upload feature implemented by the Amazon team. 

It is useful if there is an interruption during upload; such as an electrical outage, lost internet connection etc. From the Amazon side the timeout between upload attempts is not limited, so a user can return to complete a failed upload at any time.

== S3 API and competing services ==
The broad adoption of Amazon S3 and related tooling has given rise to competing services based on the S3 API.  These services utilize the standard programing interface; however, they are differentiated by their underlying technologies and supporting business models.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Watters|first=Audrey|title=Cloud Community Debates, Is Amazon S3's API the Standard? (And Should It Be?)|url=http://readwrite.com/2010/07/12/cloud-community-debates-is-ama|publisher=SAY Media, Inc.|accessdate=19 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;   A cloud storage standard (like electrical and networking standards) enable competing service providers to design their services and clients using different piece parts in different ways yet still communicate and provide the following benefits:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Committee on Standards Workshop Planning, Board on Telecommunications and Computer Applications, Commission on Engineering and Technical Systems, National Research Council|title=Crossroads of Information Technology Standards|year=1990|publisher=The National Academies Press, 1990.|location=Washington, DC:|pages=36–37|url=http://www.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=10440&amp;page=36}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

# Increase competition by providing a set of rules and a level playing field, encouraging market entry by smaller companies which might otherwise be precluded.
# Encourage innovation by Cloud Storage Vendors, Developers, and Client Tool Vendors, because they can focus on improving their own products and services instead of focusing on compatibility. 
# Allow economies of scale in implementation  (i.e., if a service provider encounters an outage or as clients outgrow their tools and need faster operating systems or tools, they can easily swap out solutions).
# Provide timely solutions for delivering functionality in response to demands of the marketplace (i.e.,  As business growth in new locations increases demand, clients can easily change or add service providers simply by subscribing to the new service).

Examples of competing S3 compliant storage implementations include:
 
*Cloud.com’s CloudStack&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Harris|first=Derrick|title=Cloud.com Expands Service Provider Footprint|url=http://gigaom.com/cloud/cloud-com-expands-service-provider-footprint/|accessdate=19 December 2012|newspaper=Gigaom|date=Mar 9, 2011&lt;!-- - 10:06AM PT--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*[[Cloudian]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cloudian.com/&lt;/ref&gt; an S3-compatible object storage software package.
*[[Connectria]] Cloud Storage&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Connectria Cloud Storage - Amazon S3®  Compatible Cloud Storage Service|url=https://www.mh.connectria.com/rp/order/cloud_storage_index|work=Connectria|publisher=Connectria|accessdate=19 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Connectria Hosting Launches Cloud Storage Solution|url=http://www.connectria.com/about_us/news/111611.php|publisher=Connectria Hosting|accessdate=19 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2011 became the first US cloud storage service provider based on the Scality RING organic storage technology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ross|first=Rose|title=Connectria selects Scality to launch a public cloud storage service|url=http://www.realwire.com/releases/Connectria-selects-Scality-to-launch-a-public-cloud-storage-service|accessdate=19 December 2012|newspaper=RealWire|date=February 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cloud Storage Providers|url=http://www.twinstrata.com/cloud-storage-providers|work=Twinstrata|publisher=Twinstrata|accessdate=19 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;   
*[[Eucalyptus (computing)|Eucalyptus]]
*[http://nimbula.com Nimbula]
*[[Riak]] CS,&lt;ref&gt;http://basho.com/products/riakcs/&lt;/ref&gt; which implements a subset of the S3 API including REST and [[Access control list|ACLs]] on objects and buckets.
*[[Ceph (file system)|Ceph]] with RADOS gateway.&lt;ref&gt;http://ceph.com/docs/master/radosgw/s3/&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== References ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web
| title = Amazon S3 Developer Guide
| url = http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/
| date = 2006-03-01
}}
* {{cite web
| title = Amazon S3 Introduces Storage Pricing Tiers
| url = http://developer.amazonwebservices.com/connect/ann.jspa?annID=351
| date = 2008-10-08
}}
* {{cite web
| title = RightScale Ruby library to access Amazon CloudFront, EC2, S3, SQS, and SDB
| url = http://developer.amazonwebservices.com/connect/entry.jspa?externalID=1014
| date = 2007-10-27
}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
&lt;!-- please have very notable links, not another disk backup service or some web site that uses S3. SUCH ADDITIONS WILL BE ROLLED BACK!
 Wikipedia is not a directory service, and editors will delete links following the WP:EL policy.
 --&gt;
*{{official website|http://aws.amazon.com/s3}}

{{Cloud computing}}
{{Amazon}}

[[Category:Amazon.com|S3]]
[[Category:Cloud storage]]
[[Category:Web services]]
[[Category:File hosting]]
[[Category:Network file systems]]

[[de:Amazon Web Services#Amazon Simple Storage Service (S3)]]</text>
      <sha1>l71rbhtysmsg4w9vkbmw94eaef3e3fs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>