<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Barry Libert</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20670603</id>
    <revision>
      <id>544767370</id>
      <parentid>544766945</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-16T22:35:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>166.147.123.34</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">

{{Infobox person
|name          = Barry Libert
|image         =
|caption       = 
|birth_name    =
|birth_date    = {{Birth date and age|1954|01|03}}
|birth_place   = 
|death_date    =
|death_place   =
|death_cause   =
|resting_place =
|resting_place_coordinates =
|citizenship   = [[United States]]
|residence     = [[Dover, Massachusetts]]
|known_for     = Co-founder of [[Mzinga]], Founder of [[OpenMatters]]
|education     = B.A. from [[Tufts]] and M.B.A. from [[Columbia University]]
|employer      =
|occupation    = Entrepreneur
|home_town     =
|title         = Founder and [[Chair (official)|Chairman]] of [[OpenMatters]]
|salary        = 
|networth      = 
|height        =
|weight        =
|term          =
|predecessor   =
|successor     =
|party         =
|boards        =
|spouse        = 
|partner       =
|children      = 
|parents       =
|relatives     =
|signature     = 
|signature_alt = 
|website       =
|footnotes     =
}}

'''Barry Libert''' (born in 1954) is a corporate director, technology investor, and strategic advisor to boards and their leaders.  He is based in [[Boston, Massachusetts]].  Mr. Libert specializes in social, mobile and big data company investing and advising  larger organizations on the impact of these technologies on their business.

==Career==
Libert is the chairman and founder of OpenMatters,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.openmatters.com www.openmatters.com&lt;/ref&gt; a technology (growth) investor and strategic advisory firm. He has spent the last ten years investing in and founding social, mobile, and big data technology companies. In 2001, he founded [[Mzinga]], a social software and analytics company.&lt;ref&gt;http://boston.dbusinessnews.com/shownews.php?newsid=157010&amp;type_news=latest&lt;/ref&gt; He currently serves on the boards of [[Innocentive]], a social innovation software company; [[Activate Networks]] (ANI),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.activatenetworks.net www.activatenetworks.net&lt;/ref&gt; a big data analytics company; The Pulse Network,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thepulsenetwork.com www.thepulsenetwork.com&lt;/ref&gt; an enterprise social video company, Sonicbids, a social music marketing company, The SEI Center for Advanced Studies in Management and Networked Organizations at the [[Wharton Business School]] of the [[University of Pennsylvania]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS133968+29-Sep-2008+BW20080929 |title=Mzinga Chairman Barry Libert Named to The Wharton School's SEI Center Board of Directors |publisher=Reuters |date= 2008-09-29|accessdate=2012-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Us Against Alzheimer's Network, an advocacy network seeking to end Alzheimer's by 2020 using today's technologies.  He is also a strategic advisor to a number of large enterprises seeking to use social, mobile and cloud technologies to improve their business models and reduce risks from their usage globally.

==Publications==
Libert has co-authored five books on the value of social networks, crowdsourcing and big data in business, healthcare and government. His fifth book, ''Social Nation'', was published in the fall of 2010 by John Wiley &amp; Sons.  

In 2007, Libert co-authored ''[[We Are Smarter Than Me]]'' with Jon Spector (CEO of the Conference Board), which focused on the power of crowdsourcing.  Using a wiki and the contributions of more than 4,500 people, ''We are Smarter than Me'' illustrated through practical applications (e.g. the first business book to be written by a crowd using a wiki) how businesses can profit from the wisdom of crowds using today's technologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bulkeley |first=William M. |url=http://online.wsj.com/public/article/SB116365019587024790-rUBDTb7KgX8kUBQ8TvNE2TjcvCc_20061215.html?mod=tff_main_tff_top |title=U.K.'s Pearson Tests The Group Dynamic For a 'Wiki' Book - WSJ.com |publisher=Online.wsj.com |date=2006-11-16 |accessdate=2012-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Prior to publishing ''We Are Smarter Than Me'', Libert also published ''Value Rx: How to Make the Most of Your Organization's Assets and Relationships'' in 2001 and ''Cracking the Value Code: How Successful Businesses Are Creating Wealth in the New Economy'' in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hunt-scanlon.com/newsarchives/orsarchives/2001/oct.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Both of these books focused on his research into the value of social interactions between constituents of an organization. He also published the book ''Barack, Inc'', which showed how [[Barack Obama]] used [[social media]] to win his presidential campaign and the lessons that could be used by business leaders seeking to win the loyalty and support of their customers and employees. 

Libert also authored more than a dozen e-books on the value of social media, mobile and cloud technologies. His newest e-book, ''Social Power'', focuses on what leaders need to know and do in today's connected world.

=== Bibliography ===

# ''Social Nation''
# ''Barack, Inc.''
# ''We Are Smarter than Me''
# ''Value Rx''
# ''Cracking the Value Code''

=== Articles ===

Barry Libert has authored 1,100 articles on the importance of social technologies and digital corporate directorship in enterprises. These articles have covered strategy, people, processes, technologies, governance, and financial results. Further, Libert has researched the impact on risks from these technologies, as well the returns from social enterprise business models. His articles have appeared in publications such as the ''Wall Street Journal'', ''New York Times'', ''Baron's'', ''Institutional Investor'', ''CIO Magazine'' and ''Mckinsey Quarterly''. 

=== Broadcast and Radio ===

Libert has appeared on CNBC, CNN and Bloomberg TV, as well as 100 other local and national outlets. He has discussed how social, mobile and open technologies impact business, government and finical markets. He has also appeared on more than 300 radio stations, including two appearances on National Public Radio (NPR).

=== Key Note Speaking Events ===

Libert has addressed more than 30,000 people at more than 400 events globally.

==Personal==

Libert holds a [[B.A.]] from [[Tufts University]] and an [[M.B.A.]] from [[Columbia University]]. He currently resides in Boston with his wife and two sons and serves on the boards of a number of charitable, academic and for-profit organizations.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Authority control|VIAF=60880453}}
{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Libert, Barry
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Businessperson
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1954
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = New York City, New York
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Libert, Barry}}
[[Category:American computer businesspeople]]
[[Category:American business writers]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1954 births]]</text>
      <sha1>k1ki1skb8a8ivvp433pumnyrcogt452</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>