<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Basho Technologies</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34458225</id>
    <revision>
      <id>560676152</id>
      <parentid>560675798</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-19T23:15:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>205.154.255.204</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Advert|date=May 2013}}

{{Infobox company
| name = Basho
| type = private company
| logo = [[File:Basho-logo-small.gif|Basho-Logo]]
| industry = Distributed Systems, [[NoSQL]], Cloud Storage Software
| key_people = Greg Collins &lt;br&gt; Justin Sheehy &lt;br&gt; Bobby Patrick &lt;br&gt; Andy Gross 
| foundation = 2008
| location_city = [[Cambridge, MA]]
| locations = 5
| num_employees = 120+
| products = [[Riak]], Riak Enterprise, Riak Cloud Storage
| homepage = [http://www.basho.com www.basho.com]
}}

'''Basho Technologies''' is a provider of distributed database software technology to fast-growing web businesses, cloud operators, large enterprises, and public-sector organizations worldwide. Basho was founded in 2008 by a group of engineers and executives from Akamai Technologies with the goal of creating a new database platform that offers extreme high-availability, low latency, linear scalability and a decentralized architecture that would be easy to use and manage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.451research.com/report-short?entityid=69112 "451: Basho Throws its Weight Behind Riak"]. ''451 Research.''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Products ==
Basho is the developer of [[Riak]], an open source NoSQL distributed database that is based on Amazon.com's Dynamo architecture. Basho offers Riak Enterprise, a commercial version of the database including advanced multi-data center replication and 24x7 enterprise support.&lt;ref&gt;[http://servicesangle.com/blog/2011/09/27/ria-hits-1-0/ "ServicesAngle: Open Source NoSQL Database Riak Hits 1.0"]. ''ServicesAngle.''&lt;/ref&gt; Basho also offers Riak CS, a multi-tenant, distributed cloud storage solution with metering, large file support, and an S3 compatible API.

Riak is a key value store system that can collect unstructured data and store it as objects in buckets that can then be queried. It's also highly scalable, able to distribute itself over a server cluster and add new servers as needed, while maintaining its own high availability.&lt;ref name="infoweek"&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/news/software/info_management/231602277 "Information Week"]. ''Information Week.''&lt;/ref&gt; Riak is written in Erlang, a language that gives a system built-in support for distribution across a server cluster, fault tolerance, and an ability to absorb new hardware being added to the cluster without disrupting operations.&lt;ref name="infoweek"/&gt;

On September 27, 2011, Basho announced the release of Riak 1.0, featuring secondary indices, Riak Pipe, Riak Search integration, Lager, and LevelDB Support.

On November 1, 2011, it was announced that the National Board of e-Health in Denmark deployed Riak to automate the Electronic Health Records of 5.5 million Danish citizens. The project was awarded the Digitization prize as one of the "best government IT projects in Denmark."

On January 5, 2012, Basho customer Voxer unveiled that it scaled 10 times to over one billion operations per day between November 2011 and January 2012. powered by [[Riak]], soaring to the top of Apple App Store rankings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://techcrunch.com/2012/01/10/popular-like-voxer/ "TechCrunch: Popular like Voxer"]. ''TechCrunch.''&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 21, 2012, Basho announced Riak v1.1. Riak 1.1 included Riaknostic, enhanced error logging and reporting, improved resiliency for large clusters, and a new graphical operations and monitoring interface called Riak Control.

On March 27, 2012, Basho launched Riak CS (Cloud Storage). Riak CS offers multi-tenancy, metering, large-object support and an S3-compatible API on top of Riak.

On July 16, 2012, Basho announced RICON, first industry conference dedicated to distributed systems technologies. Keynotes include Dr. Eric Brewer. Speakers include Comcast, Best Buy, Citrix, Twitter, Boundary, Engine Yard, Accenture, Clipboard, and many others. Sponsors include Github, Microsoft, Boundary, Yammer, and others.

On July 17, 2012, Yahoo! JAPAN and IDC Frontier make strategic financial investment in Basho and commit to deploying Riak and Riak CS.

On August 7, 2012, Basho unveiled Riak v1.2. Riak 1.2 improved performance scaling clusters fast, increased visibility into active handoffs, and added support for Riak on FreeBSD, among other features. Riak EnterpriseDS added SSL encryption and continued improvements in performance, visibility and control, across multiple data centers.

In January 2013, Basho customers enStratus and Alert Logic announced they have migrated off of Oracle mySQL to Riak. Alert Logic recorded performance results 5x higher than MySQL, achieving 35,000 operations per second per server.&lt;ref&gt;[http://basho.com/blog/technical/2013/01/24/Alert-Logic-Riak/ "Alert Logic Relies on Riak]. &lt;/ref&gt;

On February 7, 2013, Tokyo Electron Device announces that it has entered into a strategic partnership to distribute Riak throughout Japan. Tokyo Electron Device also committed an equity investment in Basho.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-02-07/tokyo-electron-device-buys-stake-in-basho-for-cloud-service.html "Tokyo Electron Device Buys Stake in Basho for Cloud"]. "Bloomberg."&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 20, 2013, Basho released portions of Riak CS code to open source. Basho also announced the commercial version designated Riak CS Enterprise, adding multi-datacenter replication, monitoring tools, and 24x7 support.&lt;ref&gt;[http://techcrunch.com/2013/03/20/basho-open-sources-riak-cs-its-big-data-storage-software-for-companies-that-want-their-own-amazon-s3-cloud/ "Basho Open-Sources Riak CS, Its Big Data Storage Software For Companies That Want Their Own Amazon S3 Cloud"]. "TechCrunch."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wired.com/wiredenterprise/2013/03/riakcs-open-source/ "Amazon Cloud Storage Clone Goes to Open Source"]. "Wired."&lt;/ref&gt;

==Location and Executives==

Basho is based in Cambridge, MA and maintains offices in London, San Francisco, Tokyo and Washington DC.

On June 29, 2011, Donald J. Rippert, long time CTO of [[Accenture]], joined Basho as president and CEO.&lt;ref&gt;[http://techcrunch.com/2011/06/29/big-data-storage-startup-basho-nabs-7-5m-and-accenture-cto-don-rippert/ "TechCrunch: Big Data Storage Startup Basho Nabs $7.5M"]. ''TechCrunch.''&lt;/ref&gt; On November 28, 2011, Bobby Patrick, former CMO of [[GXS]] and [[Digex]], joined Basho as CMO.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.storagenewsletter.com/news/people/bobby-patrick-basho "Storage News"]. ''Storage News.''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Customers and Partners ==

'''Basho Partners'''
* AWS
* Citrix
* EngineYard (http://www.engineyard.com)
* Erlang Solutions
* Joyent (http://www.joyent.com)
* IDC Frontier
* Microsoft
* SoftLayer
* Trifork (http://www.trifork.com)
* Tokyo Electron Device http://www.teldevice.co.jp/eng/)

'''Sample Customers Include:'''
* Adobe
* Alert Logic
* AT&amp;T
* Best Buy
* Bump Technologies
* Citi
* Clipboard
* CNN
* Comcast
* Danish Government
* [[Datapipe]]
* ideeli
* Mezeo
* Mad Mimi
* Mochi Media
* OpenX
* Rovio
* SEOmoz
* Sourcefire
* State Farm Insurance
* Voxer
* The Weather Channel
* Time Warner
* UK National Health Service
* Workday
* Xing
* Yahoo! JAPAN
* Yammer

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;
* [http://gigaom.com/cloud/basho-arms-would-be-amazon-killers-with-aws-compatible-storage/ GigaOM: Basho arms would-be Amazon killers with AWS-compatible storage]
* [http://techcrunch.com/2012/11/30/bashos-riak-storage-compatibility-with-amazon-s3-gets-potent-boost-with-added-replication-capability/ TechCrunch: Basho's Amazon S3 Compatibility Gets Potent Boost with Replication Capabilities for Riak Cloud Storage]

[[Category:NoSQL]]
[[Category:Cloud computing]]
[[Category:Software companies based in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Cloud infrastructure]]</text>
      <sha1>rdh6d3u2yao8fq8a31ka8jr2ve1dan2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>