<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Basis Technology Corp.</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10178154</id>
    <revision>
      <id>547305760</id>
      <parentid>547302501</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-27T18:10:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Clarify}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Company
| company_name = Basis Technology Corp.
| company_logo =
| company_type = [[Private company|Private]]
| foundation = 1995
| location = [[Cambridge]], [[Massachusetts]], [[USA]]
| key_people = Carl Hoffman (CEO &amp; Chair) &lt;br/&gt; Benson Margulies (Executive Vice President and Chief Technology Officer) &lt;br/&gt; Steven Cohen (Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer, Co-Founder) &lt;br/&gt; David Murgatroyd (Vice President, Engineering) &lt;br/&gt; Bill Ray (Vice President, Corporate Development and Federal Sales) &lt;br/&gt; Joel Ross (Vice President, Defense &amp; Intelligence Services) &lt;br/&gt; Daphne Kuo (Vice President, Chief Financial Officer) &lt;br/&gt; Amy Silverstein (Vice President, General Counsel) &lt;br/&gt; Brian Carrier (Vice President, Digital Forensics)
| area_served = [[Americas]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Europe]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Asia]] 
| industry = [[Information technology]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Information access]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Digital forensics]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Machine translation]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Transliteration]] 
| products = Rosette Linguistic Platform &lt;br/&gt; Sleuth Kit Forensics Support&lt;br/&gt; Highlight Language Analysis Suite
| revenue =
| operating_income =
| net_income =
| num_employees =
| parent =
| subsid =
| company_slogan = 
| homepage = http://www.basistech.com
| footnotes =
}}

'''Basis Technology Corp.''' is a software company specializing in applying artificial intelligence techniques to understanding documents written in different languages. It has headquarters in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]] and offices in San Francisco, Washington, D.C., London, and Tokyo.

The company was founded in 1995 by graduates of the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]] to use artificial intelligence techniques to help understand the many different languages that humans use. Its software focuses on finding structure inside text so algorithms can do a better job understanding the meaning of the words. The tools identify different forms of names and phrases. The name of someone, say Albert P. Jones for instance, can appear in many different ways. Some texts will call him "Al Jones", others "Mr. Jones" and others "Albert Paul Jones". Basis Technology's software can match all of these instances.

Their software enhances parsing tools by classifying the role of words and provides metadata on the role of words to other algorithms. Software from Basis Technology will, for instance, identify the language of an incoming stream of characters and then identify the parts of each sentence like the subject or the direct object. 

The company is best known for its Rosette Linguistics Platform which uses [[Natural Language Processing]] techniques to improve [[information retrieval]], [[text mining]], [[search engine]]s and other applications. The tool is used to create normalized forms of text by major search engines, and, translators.{{fact|date=February 2013}} Basis Technology software is also used by forensic analysts to search through files for words, tokens, phrases or numbers that may be important to investigators.{{fact|date=February 2013}}

== Rosette Linguistics Platform ==

The Rosette Linguistics Platform consists of a component library for multilingual text retrieval and analysis.  Rosette provides automatic language identification, linguistic analysis, entity extraction, and entity translation from unstructured text. It can be integrated into applications to help analyse volumes of unstructured text.

The Rosette Linguistics Platform is composed of these modules:

* '''Rosette Language Identifier''' looks at the structural and statistical signature of the file to identify the language. The pre-configured software can recognize 55 different languages with 45 different encodings.
* '''Rosette Base Linguistics''' identifies the lemma or [[word stem]] after finding the tokens. Search is often faster and more accurate when words are grouped by their stem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.technologyreview.com/featuredstory/402528/translation-in-the-age-of-terror/ |title=Translation in the Era of Terror |last=Erard |first=Michael |date=March 1, 2004 |work=Technology Review}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Rosette Entity Extractor''' analyzes raw text and identifies the probable role that words and phrases play in the document, a key step that makes it possible for algorithms to distinguish between the various meanings that many words can have. Splitting the raw text into groups of words according to their role and then classifying their contribution to meaning is often called [[entity analysis]]. The Basis hybrid approach mixes statistical modeling with rules, [[regular expression]]s, and gazetteers, lists of special words that can be tuned to the language and text to be analyzed. The tool is designed to work directly with varied alphabets and multiple languages, an advantage because foreign words are often transliterated in multiple ways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/3399087.stm |title=Language tools for fight on terror |last=Boyd |first=Clark |date=January 14, 2004 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed to be the first commercially available tool for analyzing Arabic text.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/79223/Language_analysis_software_aids_U.S._Web_search_for_terrorist_activity |title=Language analysis software aids U.S. Web search for terrorist activity |last=Weiss |first=Todd R. |date=March 10, 2003 |work=Computerworld}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Rosette Name Translator''' transliterates non-Latin alphabets like Arabic into a consistent Latin form.
* '''Rosette Name Indexer''' builds an index filled with a consistent collection of names in order to simplify searching when there are multiple forms of the same name.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bizjournals.com/profiles/company/us/ma/cambridge/basis_technology_corp/948205 Profile in Boston Business Journal]&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Rosette Core Library for Unicode''' smooths the use of Unicode text.{{clarify|date=March 2013}}
* '''Rosette Chat Translator for Arabic''' converts words from the [[Arabic chat alphabet]] to Arabic.

The Rosette Platform is used in both the United States government offices to support translation and by major Internet infrastructure firms like search engines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bizjournals.com/boston/stories/2003/03/24/newscolumn4.html |title=Basis Technology turns its focus to government security |last=Hollmer |first=Mark |date=March 21, 2003 |work=Boston Business Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.searchenginejournal.com/msn-search-engine-uses-basis-technology-for-natural-language-processing/1101/ |title=MSN Search Engine Uses Basis Technology for Natural Language Processing |last=Baker |first=Loren |date=November 30, 2004 |work=Search Engine Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Digital forensics ==

Basis Technology develops open-source [[digital forensics]] tools, ''The [[Sleuth Kit]]'' and ''[[Autopsy (software)|Autopsy]]'', to help identify and extract clues from data storage devices like hard disks or flash cards, as well as devices such as smart phones and iPods. The open-source licensing model allows them to be used as the foundation for larger projects like a Hadoop-based tool for massively parallel forensic analysis of very large data collections.

The digital forensics tool set is used to perform analysis of file systems, new media types, new file types and file system metadata. The tools can search for particular patterns in the files allowing it to target significant files or usage profiles. It can, for instance, look for common files using hash functions and also deconstruct the data structures of the important operating system log files.

The tools are designed to be customizable with an open plugin architecture. Basis Technology helps manage a large and diverse community of developers who use the tool in investigations.

== Highlight language analysis suite ==

Highlight language analysis suite (Highlight) is [[transliteration]] software designed to assist linguists and analysts standardize names and places, allowing them to concentrate upon "connecting the dots". Highlight is a plug-in to Microsoft Office. This collection of tools helps readers work with Arabic texts in various forms. Key tools include:

* Transliteration Assistant: [[Computer-assisted translation]] software which is a plug-in for Microsoft Office that correctly [[Translation|translates]] foreign names into English according to applicable government standards. Transliteration Assistant supports the [[Romanization of Arabic#Romanization standards and systems|Intelligence Community Standards]] and other standards for [[Arabic]], [[Dari]], [[Farsi]], and [[Pashto]].
* Knowledge Center: Integrated with Microsoft Office and Google Earth, Knowledge Center provides access to dictionaries, reference lists and name lists.
* Arabic Editor: Provides a method for entering and editing Arabic and Persian text from a standard keyboard or laptop computer.
* Geoscope: An interactive application that locates geographic features on a map in response to place name queries.

Highlight can:

* Resolve different spellings of foreign persons, places and organizations to standard forms.
* Translate name lists, telephone directories, and personnel databases from foreign languages into English.
* Comply with USG transliteration standards for Arabic, Dari, Farsi and Pashto.
* Connect place names appearing in reports with locations on maps.
* Access multilingual dictionaries and databases of key terms.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.basistech.com/ Official website]

[[Category:Software companies based in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Companies based in Cambridge, Massachusetts]]</text>
      <sha1>70h5sa7ebbo97zn79n123m2rqwhwdxg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>