<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>BioUML</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33693156</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532054902</id>
      <parentid>506293474</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-01-09T00:44:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BG19bot</username>
        <id>14508071</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fix for #61.  Punctuation goes before References. Do [[Wikipedia:GENFIXES|general fixes]] if a problem exists. - using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8853)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''BioUML''' is an [[open-source]] software platform for the analysis of data from [[omics]] sciences research and other advanced [[computational biology]] developed by scientists from the Institute of Systems Biology in [[Novosibirsk]], [[Russia]]. The platform is freely available online and used in research labs - mostly in academic institutions - for the discovery of disease origins and prevention. There is a commercial version available from the German [[bioinformatics]] company geneXplain,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.genexplain.com/ GeneXplain&lt;/ref&gt; which has some added features. BioUML is open source and, thus, is freely available online.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.BioUML.org BioUML&lt;/ref&gt;

==Available versions ==
The current release of BioUML is version 0.9.3 released in October 2010 and includes 3 versions;

'''BioUML Server''' - which offers access to data and analysis methods installed [[server-side]] for BioUML clients (workbench and web edition) over the [[Internet]].
 
'''BioUML Workbench''' - This is a [[Java (programming language)|Java]] application that can work standalone or as "[[thick client]]" for the BioUML server edition.
 
'''BioUML Web Edition''' - This is a web browser based "[[thin client]]" for the BioUML server edition and provides most of the functionality of the BioUML workbench. It utilizes [[AJAX]] and [[HTML5]] &lt;canvas&gt; technology for interactive data editing and [[visual modeling]].

The platform has been developed continuously since 2003 and offers [[data analysis]] and visualizations for scientists involved in complex [[molecular biology]] research. The system allows for the formalized description of biological systems structure and function including tools required to make discoveries related to [[genomics]], [[proteomics]], [[transcriptomics]] and [[metabolomics]]. The BioUML platform is built in a modular architecture which has allowed for the relatively simple addition of new tools. This has allowed the integration of many 3rd party tools into the platform over the 7 years it has been available.

== Application and usage ==
BioUML was used as the main workbench for Cyclonet's integrated database&lt;ref&gt;http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/content/35/suppl_1/D550.full-text-lowres.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; on [[cell cycle regulation]] and [[carcinogenesis]] in 2007&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mendeley.com/research/cyclonetan-integrated-database-on-cell-cycle-regulation-and-carcinogenesis/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17202170&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Next-generation sequencing]] (NGS) and other high throughput methods create huge data sets (called "[[big data]]") in the region of 100 [[terabytes]] upwards. BioUML can disseminate, analyse, and produce [[Information visualization|visualization]]s and [[simulations]], allows for parameter fitting and supports many other analysis techniques required to deal with large amounts of raw data. As research is typically shared between various institutions, the storage, delivery and sharing of 'big data' volumes has been a technical challenge. A typical [[genome]] data set might contain 500 terabytes of data which may need to be shared, often internationally using [[Internet2]] technology. Proprietary [[data compression]] mechanisms have been created (by [http://www.valexllc.com Valex LLC]) for the [[National Center for Biotechnology Information|NCBI]] [[Short Read Archive]] Project&lt;ref&gt;http://www.galter.northwestern.edu/news/index.cfm/2009/9/15/NCBI-Short-Read-Archive-SRA-of-NextGeneration-Sequencing-Data&lt;/ref&gt; that allow for the delivery of raw research data at speeds of up to 40Gbits/sec. To provide a full solution for such collaborative research, the makers of BioUML have developed a new hardware/software system in partnership with [http://www.valexllc.com/ Valex LLC]. This version of BioUML is called Biodatomics.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.biodatomics.com BioDatomics&lt;/ref&gt;

== Commercial versions ==
[http://www.biodatomics.com BioDatomics] is a new commercially available  version of BioUML which is a hardware and software solution for next generation and omics science researchers. BioDatomics is not open source but has the same modular architecture as BioUML and is offered as a full hardware/software [[platform as a service]] (PaaS) configuration as well as a standalone version of BioUML platform in a [[software as a service]] (SaaS) configuration.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Computational biology]]</text>
      <sha1>0mtiyjlurrovhfv38vbaeffpz809fow</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>