<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Birst</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33467505</id>
    <revision>
      <id>533591160</id>
      <parentid>503254909</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-01-17T21:42:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.76.40.150</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
|company_name=Birst Inc.
|industry=Software
|company_type=Private
|foundation= 2004
|location=San Francisco, California
|num_employees=120+
|homepage=[http://www.birst.com/ birst.com]}}

'''Birst Inc.''' is a [[software]] provider of [[business intelligence]] (BI) solutions headquartered in [[Analytics|San Francisco]], California. Birst originally delivered its solution exclusively via a Software-as-a-Service (SaaS) model but with Birst 5, the company additionally delivered its suite via a software virtual appliance.

== Executives ==
Brad Peters - CEO &lt;br&gt;
Paul Staelin - Vice President of Customer Success &lt;br&gt;
Ryan Ried - Vice President of Worldwide Sales &lt;br&gt;
Rick Spickelmier - CTO/VP Engineering &lt;br&gt;
Wynn White - Vice President of Worldwide Marketing &lt;br&gt;
Andrew Marks - Vice President of Professional Services

== Products ==
Birst delivers business analytics in the Cloud or on premise via an appliance which can be installed behind a corporate firewall. Birst offers a single solution Birst 5 which includes business intelligence and analytics components such as [[Datawarehouse|data warehousing]], [[Extract, transform, load|ETL]] tools, pixel-perfect and ad hoc reports, dashboards and [[analytics]]. In January 2012, Birst introduced an in-memory database option in addition to its relational and columnar databases.  Birst provides support for unstructured data, in addition to structured sources, with its Big Data Services which captures unstructured data in a hosted Hadoop instance allowing to combine it with structured sources for analysis.  Birst also supports managed data mash-ups, sometimes referred to as Distributed Business Analytics,to let business users augment corporate data residing in their data warehouse with their local data. 

== Recognition ==
2012 Wisdom of the Crowds, Cloud BI - Dresner Associates, Highest Ranked Vendor &lt;br&gt;
2012 Frost and Sullivan, New Product Innovation &lt;br&gt;
2012 JMP Securities, Hot 100 Software Companies &lt;br&gt;
2012 InformationManagment, Top 40 Vendors We are Watching &lt;br&gt;
2012 Nucleus Research Technology Value Matrix - Analytics, Leader &lt;br&gt;
Red Herring Global &lt;br&gt;
TDWI Best Practices &lt;br&gt;
Software Standard of Excellence


== References ==
&lt;!--- See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}
{{Refbegin}}
1.	Wall Street Journal, All Things Digital – http://allthingsd.com/20110927/birst-when-the-cloud-isnt-always-in-the-cloud/ &lt;br&gt;
2.	http://gigaom.com/cloud/birst-tries-to-prove-saas-doesnt-need-the-cloud/ &lt;br&gt;
3.	Cloud Computing Journal –http://cloudcomputing.sys-con.com/node/1997217 &lt;br&gt;
4. RightNow - http://www.rightnow.com/partners-birst.php &lt;br&gt;
5. http://montclairadvisors.com/blog/2010/06/saas-business-profile-birst/
{{Refend}}

&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;





[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Business intelligence companies]]
[[Category:Software companies based in California]]
[[Category:Companies based in San Francisco, California]]</text>
      <sha1>r50xdth3iqbdmwyi39d5v2zc4fu374f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>