<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Buell Motorcycle Company</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>788403</id>
    <revision>
      <id>561677823</id>
      <parentid>561670951</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-26T14:42:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dennis Bratland</username>
        <id>152627</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 3 edits by [[Special:Contributions/198.164.157.50|198.164.157.50]] ([[User talk:198.164.157.50|talk]]): Personal webiste. see [[WP:ELNO]]. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|reason= This article contains repetitive and potentially conflicting text that does not add to the factual content, and it often presents information in a confusing or ambiguous way.|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox Company |
| company_name = Buell Motorcycles
| company_logo = [[Image:Buelllogo.png|220px|Buell Logo]]
| company_type =  [[Subsidiary]]
| foundation = 1983
| defunct = October 30, 2009
| founder = [[Erik Buell]]
| location_city = [[East Troy, Wisconsin|East Troy]], [[Wisconsin]]
| location_country =USA
| key_people = 
| industry = Motorcycles
| products = [[Motorcycles]]
| parent = [[Harley Davidson]]
| subsid = 
| revenue =  
| num_employees = 
| homepage = {{URL|http://www.buell.com/}}
}} 
The '''Buell Motorcycle Company''' was an American [[motorcycle]] manufacturer based in [[East Troy, Wisconsin]], and was founded in 1983 by ex-[[Harley-Davidson]] engineer [[Erik Buell]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0KJI/is_8_118/ai_n16702057|title=Buell Motorcycle engineering, innovation, &amp; dedication|publisher=Automotive Design &amp; Production|date=August, 2006|author=Kevin M. Kelly|accessdate=2008-02-29|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Harley-Davidson acquired 49% of Buell in 1993, and Buell became a wholly owned subsidiary of Harley-Davidson by 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Buell Motorcycle Co. - Two Wheel Innovation | publisher = US Industry Today | url = http://www.usitoday.com/article_view.asp?ArticleID=1485 | accessdate = 2007-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
On November 17, 2006, Buell announced that it had produced and shipped its 100,000th motorcycle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.buell.com/en_us/company/news/detail.asp?news_id=1098/ | title= Buell Website Press Release Regarding 100,000th Unit | publisher= Buell}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 15, 2009, Harley-Davidson announced the discontinuation of the Buell product line as part of its strategy to focus on the Harley-Davidson brand.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
|title=Harley drops two lines, income plummets |first=Rick |last=Barrett |newspaper=[[Milwaukee Journal Sentinel]] |issn=1082-8850 |location=Milwaukee, Wisconsin |date=15 October 2009 |url=http://www.jsonline.com/business/64352232.html
|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Harley-Davidson.com July 11"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.harley-davidson.com/wcm/Content/Pages/HD_News/Company/newsarticle.jsp?locale=en_US&amp;articleLink=News/0292_press_release.hdnews&amp;newsYear=2008&amp;history=news | title=Harley-Davidson to acquire Mv Agusta Group expanding presence in Europe | publisher=Harley-Davidson.com| accessdate=2008-07-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The last Buell motorcycle was produced on October 30, bringing the number manufactured to 136,923.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.motorcyclenews.com/MCN/News/newsresults/General-news/2009/November/nov1309-last-buell-rolls-off-production-line/ | publisher= [[Motorcycle News]] | date= 13 November 2009 | accessdate= 17 November 2009 | title= Last Buell rolls off production line}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2009, Buell and Harley-Davidson announced the launch of [[Erik Buell Racing]], an independent company run by Erik Buell which at first produced race-only versions of the [[Buell 1125R|1125R]] model, but which is currently offering an updated 1190RS model for the street or the track.&lt;ref name=ebr&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.buell.com/en_us/racing/racing-news/detail.asp?news_id=1507 | title=  erik buell establishes erik buell racing  | publisher= Buell Motorcycle Company | accessdate= 23 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The first Buell motorcycle, the [[Buell RW750|RW750]], was built in 1983 purely for competition in the [[American Motorcycle Association|AMA]] Formula 1 motorcycle road racing championship.  At that time, Erik Buell was a top contending privateer motorcycle racer. After completion of the first two RW750 racing machines, one of which was sold to another racing team, the Formula 1 series was canceled. Erik Buell then turned his focus towards racing-inspired, street-going machines using engines manufactured by Harley. 

In 1993, Harley-Davidson purchased 49% of Buell, investing $500,000 and taking Erik Buell's house as security.&lt;ref name="cw0510"&gt;{{cite news|title=The Demise of the Buell Motorcycle Company|last=Anderson|first=Steve|date=2010-05|work=[[Cycle World]]|accessdate=24 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.harley-davidson.com/wcm/Content/Pages/Buell/buell.jsp?locale=en_us The Buell Motorcycle Company at Harley-Davidson.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Erik Buell took the deal, against strong advice from his attorney.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; Harley-Davidson CEO Jeffrey Bleustein had bought it as a [[Skunkworks project|skunkworks]] development.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

In 1998, Harley-Davidson bought a majority stake and took control of Buell Motorcycle Company, and the company became a subsidiary. Since then, Buell has used modified Harley-Davidson engines, primarily from the [[Harley-Davidson Sportster|Sportster]], to power its motorcycles.

[[Image:buellshop.jpg|thumb|right|Buell Facility]]

Most Buell motorcycles use [[four-stroke]] air-cooled [[V-twin engine]]s, originally built from [[Harley-Davidson Sportster|XR1000 Sportster]] engines.  After these were depleted, a basic 1200 Sportster engine was used.  In 1995, the engines were upgraded with Buell engineered high-performance parts and further upgraded in 1998.

The [[Harley-Davidson VRSC|liquid-cooled Harley V-Rod]] motor, developed by Harley-Davidson then made street legal according to the EPA by Porsche, was originally an Erik Buell project, designed for a fully faired [[AMA Superbike]] Buell by 1998.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; Harley decided the engine should also be used in a sport-cruiser, then took over development, making it "too big, too heavy, too expensive and too late" for Buell.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

Harley-Davidson forced Buell to follow the rigid product planning and distribution process beginning in the 1990s, with the philosophy that Buell was the starter brand, and customers would eventually trade up to a Harley.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; By 2008, Harley's credit arm, [[Harley-Davidson Financial Services]] (HDFS), was struggling, and the lower resale value of Buell motorcycles meant that new bike sales were significantly affected.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; When Harley CEO Keith Wandell was hired, he immediately questioned why Harley even owned Buell.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; Wandell, who had never been on a Harley before being hired, was heard talking about "Erik's racing hobby", and questioned "why anyone would even want to ride a sportbike".&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; He organized a team to analyze "the adrenaline market", and concluded that [[sport bike|sportbikes]] would encounter high competition and low profits, while cruisers had high returns.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

On October 15, 2009, Harley Davidson Inc. announced the end of production of Buell Motorcycles to focus more on the Harley Davidson brand. Selling Buell was not legitimately considered, as Harley didn't want their Harley dealerships to sell an outside brand, and Harley didn't feel Buell had much value without the dealer network.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; Closing the Buell brand was estimated to cost Harley approximately the same as their total investment in Buell over the past 25 years.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; Erik Buell immediately began looking for outside buyers, finding [[Bombardier Recreational Products|BRP]] (who owns the Austrian [[Rotax]] engine manufacturer BRP-Powertrain) a good choice, especially since Harley would have to pay Rotax "an eight-figure sum" for the 1,125&amp;nbsp;cc engine contract.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; 

Erik Buell later founded [[Erik Buell Racing]] to provide support for 1125 and XB privateer race efforts.&lt;ref name=ebr/&gt;

==Technology==
[[File:Buell disk brake.jpg|thumb|Buell ZTL front brake]]
Buell XB models also incorporated the industry's first Zero Torsional Load (ZTL) perimeter floating front [[disc brake]] system, a [[patent]]ed "inside-out" wheel/brake design that puts the brake disc on the outer edge of the wheel,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;d=PALL&amp;p=1&amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsrchnum.htm&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;s1=6561298.PN.&amp;OS=PN/6561298&amp;RS=PN/6561298 | publisher= [[United States Patent and Trademark Office]] | title= United States Patent 6,561,298 | date= 13 May 2003 | accessdate= 18 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
rather than at the hub. This lets the suspension function better, improving control and traction, through reducing [[unsprung weight]] on the front wheel, because only a single disc and caliper&amp;mdash;with a corresponding reduction in bolts and brake fluid&amp;mdash;is needed compared with the conventional dual-disc brake setup on most modern [[sport bike]]s. In an exchange in the pages of ''[[Motorcyclist (magazine)|Motorcyclist]]'' magazine between Suzuki engineer James Parker, creator of the GSX-RADD [[hub-center steering]] system,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.motorcyclistonline.com/features/122_0801_gsx_radd_p3/radd_steering.html |title=GSX-Radd P3 - Raddical - The Future Of Motor Cycling  |magazine=[[Motorcyclist (magazine)|Motorcyclist]] | issn=0027-2205 | publisher=Source Interlink Media |page= |date= |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
and Buell's Director of Analysis, Test &amp; Engineering Process, Abraham Askenazi, Parker conceded the ZTL system's advantage in unsprung weight.  But he pointed out the remaining weight is located further out on the rim where it is most detrimental to acceleration and braking, and that there were potential heat transfer issues, and the need for one fork leg to be stronger than the other. Responding, Askenazi disputed all of Parker's criticisms, saying the ZTL system was 30% lighter than the brakes on the [[Suzuki GSX-R1000]], and that the inertia of having the weight further out on the rim, and the heat generation near the tire, were not negative factors, based on testing. Askenazi concluded that testing and race track experience had proven the ZTL to be "state of the art."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
|last=Parker |first=James |title=Answers: ask the pro.(MC GARAGE) (Q&amp;A) |magazine=[[Motorcyclist (magazine)|Motorcyclist]] | issn=0027-2205 | publisher=Source Interlink Media |page=82 |date=June 2007 |issue=1323 |pages=166–169 |quote=ZTL has less unsprung weight, and the reduction in wheel weight is mostly near the hub. Some heat will be transferred to the rim and tire through the fasteners, which might be a negative factor in racing applications. However, the rotating mass/inertia of the large-diameter ZTL disc and its fasteners are a negative factor. You'd have to do the math to get an exact rotational comparison with two discs, but that one big disc certainly isn't a large improvement. [...] A ZTL caliper of equivalent rigidity will be heavier than a conventional caliper, but lighter than two. [...] With the ZTL system, one fork leg takes all the braking force.
|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Askenazi |first=Abraham |title=The word from Buell.(MC Mail)(Letter to the editor). |magazine=[[Motorcyclist (magazine)|Motorcyclist]] | issn=0027-2205 | publisher=Source Interlink Media |page=32 |date=August 2007 |issue=1325 |pages=166–169 |quote=ZTL has less unsprung weight: This is critically important in a performance motorcycle because minimizing it results in better suspension control and enhanced traction. ZTL is 30 percent lighter than the system on a Suzuki GSX-R1000! |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other industry innovations introduced by Buell in the XB lineup were the "fuel in frame" technology, and the dual use of the swingarm as an oil tank.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sporttwin.com/News/print/sid=113.html 2007 Buell Model Changes Released]&lt;/ref&gt;  
Also, all Buell models feature a muffler mounted below the engine which helps keep mass centralized with some models featuring a computer-controlled valve to switch between two exhaust paths as necessary to maximize torque.

Buell designs focus on providing good handling, comfortable riding, easy maintenance, and street-friendly real-world performance. Buell motorcycles were engineered with an emphasis on what they called the "Trilogy of Tech": mass centralization, low unsprung weight, and frame rigidity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|url=http://www.gizmag.com/go/6471/|title=100 bhp Buell Lightning Super TT XB12STT debuts at [[EICMA]]|publisher=Gizmag|accessdate=2009-02-25|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Buell engines were designed to be street-friendly both in fuel efficiency (up to {{convert|70|mpgus|abbr=on|disp=or}} with the Blast), and in torque (the 1,203&amp;nbsp;cc version produces {{convert|110|Nm|abbr=on|disp=or}}). They are also simple and easy to maintain. Most Buell two-cylinder engines utilize computer controlled ducted forced air cooling (variable speed fan that only activates as required), two valves per cylinder, a single throttle body, zero maintenance hydraulic valve actuation, and zero maintenance gear-driven cams.

==Buell Models==
===Tube-frame bikes (1984–2002)===
{{refimprove|sectionion|date=March 2010}}

====RW 750 Road Warrior (1984)====
The RW 750 was a development of the Barton Formula One racing motorcycle.&lt;ref name="BikeExifRW750"&gt;[http://www.bikeexif.com/buell-rw750 BikeExif - Buell RW750]&lt;/ref&gt; Buell bought the parts and tooling from the failed Barton concern and developed the RW 750 for his own use and for sale to private entrants.&lt;ref name="BuellAMAHoF"&gt;[http://www.motorcyclemuseum.org/halloffame/detail.aspx?racerid=327 AMA Motorcycle Museum Hall of Fame - Erik Buell]&lt;/ref&gt; The engine was a liquid-cooled two-stroke square four.&lt;ref name="BikeExifRW750" /&gt;&lt;ref name="BuellAMAHoF" /&gt; Buell's development resulted in a more competitive racer, but production ceased when the AMA discontinued the Formula One class.&lt;ref name="BikeExifRW750" /&gt;&lt;ref name="BuellAMAHoF" /&gt;

[[File:Buell RR1000 Battletwin 02.jpg|thumb|right|RR1000 Battletwin]]

====RR 1000 Battletwin (1987–1988)====
The RR 1000 Battletwin was a street sportbike using a modified Road Warrior chassis and a Harley-Davidson XR1000 engine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.motorcycleclassics.com/motorcycle-reviews/buell-RR1000.aspx|title=Buell RR1000|publisher=Motorcycle Classics|accessdate=2010-05-21|date=March/April2010|author=Alan Cathcart}}&lt;/ref&gt; Buell invented the ''Isoplanar'' engine mounting system to allow the heavy, vibration-prone engine to be used as a structural member of the frame without transmitting the engine vibrations to the frame. Lack of space caused Buell to put the suspension components under the engine. The linkage caused the spring and the shock absorber to extend when the wheel went up.&lt;ref name="CycleBattleTwin"&gt;{{cite journal| last1        = Cameron| first1       = Kevin| authorlink1  = | editor-last  =Schilling| editor-first =Phil| editor-link  =| year         = 1986| month        = April| title        =  Battle Twin| journal      = Cycle| volume       = | issue        = | series       = | pages        = 25–31, 126–127| location     = Westlake Village, California| publisher    = CBS| id           =| isbn         =| issn         = | oclc         = | pmid         = | pmc          = | bibcode      = | doi          = | quote        = | ref          = | separator    =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Variations on the RR 1000 Battletwin include the RR 1200 Battletwin (1988–1990), the RS 1200 Westwind (1989), the RS 1200/5 Westwind (1990–1992) and the RSS 1200 Westwind (1991).{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

====S2 Thunderbolt (1994–1995)====
Two-seater with Road Warrior based chassis and Sportster engine.  The S2T Thunderbolt (1995–1996) was a touring version, with saddlebags. The S2 was  very expensive to develop (around $100,000), and 1,399 units were sold in the first year&amp;mdash;well over the 300 units Buell had projected.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

[[File:Buell S1 White Lightning.jpg|thumb|Buell S1 White Lightning]]

====S1 Lightning (1996–1998)====
The S1 Lightning was a more fundamental sportbike than the S3 Thunderbolt and M2 Cyclone that it was marketed alongside. Variants of this version of the Lightning were the S1 Lightning (1996/1997/1998) and the S1W White Lightning (1998). The S1W came with a larger tank and ''Thunderstorm'' cylinder heads which gave an extra {{convert|10|hp|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Court Cranfield and Dave Gees - 25 Years of Buell&lt;/ref&gt;

====X1 Lightning (1999–2002)====
The X1 Lightning was the successor to the S1 Lightning line. They all used the Thunderstorm heads, fuel injection (Dynamic Digital Fuel Injection) and incorporated larger fuel tanks as well as completely different body designs. The most recognizable frame piece was the brushed aluminum tail section that swept upward and back underneath the two-up seat. The 1999 X1 Lightning was awarded motorcycle of the year in Japan.{{cn|date=July 2011}}

====S3 Thunderbolt (1997–2002) and S3T Thunderbolt (1997–2000)====
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2010}}
[[Image:1999BuellS3.jpg|thumb|1999 Buell S3 Thunderbolt|right]]
The S3 Thunderbolt sport-touring model was produced from 1997 through 2002, along with a mechanically identical S3T "Touring" model that ran through model year 2000. The 1,203&amp;nbsp;cc air-cooled V-Twin engine was mounted as a stressed member in a tubular frame. The powerplant output {{convert|91|hp|abbr=on}} in 1997 and jumped to {{convert|101|hp|abbr=on}} in the following years due to revised cam profiles and the new Thunderstorm cylinder heads. While the bike's overall look was the same throughout the model run, there were significant changes made in 1999 that set it, and later models, apart from the 1997 and 1998 bikes. The early bikes used a rectangular section steel rear swingarm, [[WP Suspension]] front forks and rear shock, a Keihin 40&amp;nbsp;mm CV carburetor, and a Performance Machine six-piston front brake caliper. Beginning in 1999 a new cast aluminum rear swingarm was utilized along with [[Showa Corporation|Showa]] front suspension forks and rear shock. The front brake caliper, while still a six-piston unit, was now made by Nissin. The most technological change came in the new Dynamic Digital Fuel Injection (DDFI) system, replacing the old carburetor.

The S3 featured a half faring that surrounded the headlight and gave decent wind protection for the rider's torso. The S3T model then added lower fairing extensions that gave better wind protection to the rider's legs. The S3T also featured hard saddlebags that could be color-matched to the bike color and were available in either "wide" for maximum storage, or "narrow" for a lighter feel. In addition to the lower fairings and the saddlebags, the S3T also came with a taller handlebar for a more upright, relaxed riding position. Each of the parts that set the S3T apart were available as accessories for the standard S3 model.
[[File:Buell M2 Cyclone white 2000 front.jpg|thumb|2000 Buell M2 Cyclone]]

====M2 Cyclone (1997–2002)====
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2010}}
The M2 Cyclone was produced from 1997 to 2002. It was in the middle of the Buell line up between the puristic S1 Lightning and the more comfortable but heavier S3 Thunderbolt. The S1 Lightning being the fastest and lightest of the bunch but offered a very narrow seat due to its minimalist approach for weight saving in this sport bike. The S3 Thunderbolt was a touring bike that offered a bigger wider seat and more comfortable riding position but was also a heavier motorcycle. The M2 Cyclone filled the gap between the sport and touring models with a bigger seat than the S1 Lightning and lighter and faster than the S3 Thunderbolt. The M2 was only available with the 1,203&amp;nbsp;cc engine and five-speed transmission. The frame was of the tubular [[41xx_steel|CrMo]] steel type.

===Blast (2000–2009)===
[[File:BuellBlast.jpg|thumb|2000 Buell Blast]]
{{Main|Buell Blast}}

The [[Buell Blast|Blast]] was Buell's only model to use a [[single-cylinder engine]]. With {{convert|492|cc|cuin||abbr=on}} displacement and {{convert|360|lb|kg||abbr=on}} dry weight, it was their smallest model, often used in Harley-Davidson's "Rider's Edge" new rider instruction/riding schools.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; This filled Harley CEO [[Jeffrey Bleustein|Jeff Bleustein's]] idea of having a make-specific training bike, since many students end up buying a bike from the dealer where they trained.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

The Blast came from a quick proof-of-concept at the Buell factory.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; It originally used half of a Sportster 883 engine.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; The engine ended up 80 percent over budget and very expensive compared to the higher-technology [[Rotax]] engines available from outside the company.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; ''[[Cycle World]]'' wrote "Such an overrun would be unheard of from an outside supplier, but when your supplier also owns you, you grin and bear it."&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; The Blast was ultimately the most expensive development project Buell undertook.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;
Because the engine was overpriced, it ended up making money for Harley while losing money for Buell.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; It was regarded as a technical success.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

In July 2009, Buell ran an ad campaign stating that the Blast would no longer appear in their line-up. The ad featured a Buell Blast being destroyed in an automobile crusher.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buell.com/en_US/bikes/blast/ ]{{dead link|date=February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By&amp;nbsp; Jeremy Korzeniewski RSS feed |url=http://www.autoblog.com/2009/07/28/buell-blast-comes-to-a-crushing-end-new-entry-level-sportbike-i/ |title=Buell Blast comes to a crushing end, new entry-level sportbike in the offing? [w/VIDEO&amp;#93; |publisher=Autoblog.com |date=2009-07-28 |accessdate=2012-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sportrider.com/news/146_2010_buell_blast_redesign/index.html |title=2010 Buell Blast Revealed? |publisher=Sportrider.com |date= |accessdate=2012-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===XB-series (2002–2010)===
[[File:Buell Lightning XB9S Stealth.jpg|thumb|2003 Buell Lightning XB9S]]
[[File:Buell Lightning XB9SX CityX.jpg|thumb|2006 Buell Lightning CityX XB9SX]]
[[File:Buell Ulysses Racing.jpg|thumb|A club racing version of the Buell Ulysses XB12X]]
The XB powertrain still had its roots with the Harley Sportster powertrain, and was designed for both projects.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; Unfortunately, it was designed by Harley with minimum input from Buell.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; A [[turbocharger]] was to be sourced from Aerocharger to help pump the XB horsepower to {{convert|150|hp|abbr=on}}, but the Aerocharger supplier deal fell through when Harley Davidson decided to engineer one in house.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; That project was a failure, despite "millions of dollars" spent.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; 

The first XB9 engines had a {{convert|985|cc|cuin||abbr=on}} displacement, the later XB12 engines had {{convert|1203|cc|cuin||abbr=on}}. 

Before the first XB was sold, the cost was well over the target, leading to a sales price increase from the original price of $7,995 to $9,995.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; It was a popular bike, but never sold as Harley marketing departments expected volume, partly due to the significantly higher price.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

Buell introduced the XB frame in the 2002 Firebolt XB9R [[sportbike]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motorcyclistonline.com/roadtests/buell_xb9r_firebolt/index.html Motorcyclist.com Buell XB9R Firebolt road test]&lt;/ref&gt;  The Firebolt XB12R was introduced in 2004 and was initially sold alongside the smaller displacement Firebolt XB9R.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motorcyclistonline.com/firstrides/122_0310_2004_buell_xb12r_xb12s/index.html Motorcyclist.com 2004 Buell XB12R and XB12S Motorcycles First Ride]&lt;/ref&gt; The Lightning came in 2003 and was marketed by Buell as a [[streetfighter]] motorcycle.
Buell's Ulysses XB12X debuted in July 2005. It offers seating, ergonomics, and long-travel suspension that are well-suited for use on unpaved and rough (fire)roads. Buell advertised the Ulysses as "the world's first adventure sportbike." For 2008, among other changes, XBRR oil pump and ignition timing systems have been changed tapping into the XBRR race bike as well as the addition of heated grips and increased turning fork swing from 54° to 74°. The Ulysses XB12XT differs from the Ulysses XB12X in several areas. It has a different front fender, unlike the [[Enduro]]-[[Fender (vehicle)|front fender]] that comes on the XB12X and lower fork protection is not as pronounced as on the XB12X, due to the intended purpose of the XB12XT which is more street than dirt oriented. Other major differences include the suspension which is completely different between the two bikes, being about an inch lower on the XB12XT and tuned more for street riding, vs. the XB12X's slightly taller and softer suspension better tuned for dirt use. Along with factory Hepco &amp; Becker hard [[pannier]]s and top box, tall windshield and a {{convert|30.9|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} seat height, the XB12XT also has wheels that are approximately {{convert|1|lb|g|-1|abbr=on}} lighter than those found on the XB12X, which have added mass to make them stronger for off paved road use.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roadracingworld.com/news/article/?article=31113 Buell Introduces Shorter, Sportier Ulysses XB12XT]&lt;/ref&gt; The XB12XP is a police model that was available for the 2009 model year.

====XB1 type====
* Firebolt XB9R
* Firebolt XB12R
* Lightning XB9S
* Lightning CityX XB9SX (MY 2010: Lightning XB9SX)
* Lightning XB12S
* Lightning Low XB12Scg
* Lightning XB12SX (MY 2010, Europe only)

====XB2 type====
(different frame with more fuel capacitiy, longer swing arm &amp; wheelbase, 23.8°/23.5° steering axis angle, more trail)
*Lightning Long XB12Ss
*Lightning Super TT XB12STT
*Ulysses XB12X
*Ulysses XB12XP
*Ulysses XB12XT
{{clear}}

=== 1125-series (XB3, 2007–2010)===
====1125R====
[[File:Buell 1125R.JPG|thumb|right|Buell 1125R 25th Anniversary Signature Edition]]
{{Main|Buell 1125R}}
In July 2007, Buell announced the 1125R, a [[sport bike]] that departed from Buell's history of using [[Harley-Davidson Sportster]] based middle weight powertrains and tapping into the XBRR racing bike learnings. The [[Rotax]] Helicon powertrain uses four valves per cylinder, dual over-head cam, liquid-cooled 72&amp;nbsp;degree V-Twin displacing 1,125&amp;nbsp;cc and producing {{Convert|146|hp|abbr=on}}. It produces {{convert|83|ft.lbf|N.m|abbr=on}} of peak torque but varies less than {{convert|6|ft.lbf|N.m|abbr=on}} of torque from 3,000 to 10,500&amp;nbsp;rpm. There is a vacuum assist [[slipper clutch]] to give predictable drive performance in hard cornering and deceleration and a six-speed transmission.

The Helicon engine was developed and built by [[Rotax|BRP-Powertrain]] in Austria.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; The design had significant Buell input, and was funded through Buell's cashflow, likely for 15–20% of the V-Rod engine development cost.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

The 1125R did not have a full fairing, as that would have put it in the same class as Japanese sportbikes.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; Erik Buell agonized over this, saying "it's not about listening to the voice of the customer."&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; ''Cycle World'' magazine said the 1125R was "a bit of an oddity."&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; The bike was initially released with a crude spark map, leading to criticism of the bike at low speeds.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; The Rotax Helicon also ended up costing significantly more by production time due to fluctuation in [[exchange rates]].&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;

====1125CR====
For the 2009 model year, Buell introduced the 1125CR, a version of the 1125R in the [[cafe racer]] style.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cycleworld.com/article.asp?section_id=3&amp;article_id=837 Cycle World: First Look: 2009 Buell 1125CR]&lt;/ref&gt; This was done in response to customer feedback, which said the 1125R wasn't what was wanted, and causing Buell to shelve plans for a [[Streetfighter]], going for a cafe racer instead.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt; The 1125CR has a longer swingarm, a longer wheelbase and a shorter secondary drive ratio.

{{clear}}

==Racing==
{{refimprove|section|date=March 2010}}

===Buell XBRR===
[[File:Buell XBRR.jpg|thumb|Buell XBRR]]
Buell also produced a limited series of 50 XBRR ({{convert|1339|cc|cuin||abbr=on|disp=or}}, {{Convert|150|hp|abbr=on|disp=or}}) racing-only machines for factory-backed and [[Privateer (motorsport)|privateer]] racing teams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.motorcycle-usa.com/77/283/Motorcycle-Article/2007-Buell-XBRR-First-Ride.aspx | publisher= MotorcycleUSA.com | title= 2007 Buell XBRR First Ride | first= Ken | last= Hutchison | date= October 2, 2006 | accessdate= February 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The XBRR frame was a XB1/XB2 hybrid, the suspension came from Swedish manufacturer [[Öhlins]], and the wheels were made of magnesium. It was the first model using the ZTL2  eight-piston caliper by Nissin.

===Buell 1125RR===
In 2009, Buell announced production of the 1125RR, also a race-only motorcycle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buell.com/en_us/experience/news/detail.asp?news_id=1459 ]{{dead link|date=February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bike was internally called the B2, aimed for the supersport market.&lt;ref name="cw0510" /&gt;  Built from the 1125R, the 1125RR changes include a titanium exhaust, magnesium wheels, full [[Motorcycle fairing|fairings]] and a chain drive.

On September 9, 2009, Buell won its first AMA Pro racing championship. Rider Danny Eslick clinched the title at New Jersey Motorsports Park on Buell's 1125R model.

On November 15, 2009, Buell won its first NHRA Pro Stock Motorcycle world championship. Rider Hector Arana clinched the title at Southern California NHRA Finals on a Lucas Oil backed Buell.

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Buell motorcycles|Buell}}
* {{Official website|http://www.buell.com/}}
* {{dmoz|Recreation/Motorcycles/Makes_and_Models/Buell/|Buell}}
* {{youtube|t5i7JDNACtI|Erik Buell announces the end of Buell (official video)}}

{{Major USA motorcycle manufacturers}}

[[Category:Buell motorcycles]]
[[Category:Defunct companies based in Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1983]]
[[Category:Companies disestablished in 2009]]
[[Category:Harley-Davidson]]
[[Category:Motorcycle manufacturers of the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>sllr6o3a35gen09k5pyokcddac64kh1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>