<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Cardot</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31222491</id>
    <revision>
      <id>546121641</id>
      <parentid>510642471</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-21T23:43:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 1 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q2938116]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Cardot''' may refer to:
* [[Jean Cardot]] (born 1930), a French sculptor
* [[Jules Cardot]] (1860-1934), a French botanist and bryologist
* [[Stephen Cardot]] (born 1955), an American artist and information technology scientist
{{surname}}


Stephen Cardot (1955 - ) an American artist and information technology scientist, born in Canton, Illinois.

Mr. Cardot (Minneapolis, MN) is the senior inventor and patent author to "Systems and Methods for Insuring Data over the Internet" and underwrite (TCP/IP) data transmission. This fundamental invention creates a new type of cyber-insurance, known as incremental data transmission insurance -or- CloudCover.

CloudCover

Stephen is the founder of CloudCover, Ltd. (Minneapolis, MN) a cyber-risk insurance management group focused on delivering the underwriting system and method for electronic privacy and security of data in-transit. Today as founder, Stephen leads the team that has re-invented the underwriting of in-transit data@risk within cloud computing. Mr Cardot and his team are completing the development on that which is appropriately being readied to real-time underwrite, insure, mitigate risk and address the claims when transmitting global online data. 

CloudCover have developed in-transit data insurance and are entering the cyber-insurance market with a fundamental real-time risk mitigation and risk transfer process at the elemental packet level. As CloudCover defines the online risk-gap and security vulnerabilities within cloud-computing, the ultimate goal is to become the standard for insurance when transmitting mobile data throughout the Internet.

Together with strategic partners, CloudCover is building the infrastructure to apply incremental underwriting, pricing, billing, and claims adjudication for cloud insurance of cyber-risky data assets and a host of public or private cloud-computing perils. As a result, CloudCover shall acquire the "big data" knowledge associated with underwriting the online privacy and security vulnerabilities of transit data. Thus the ultimate goal is to become the standard for insuring when transmitting cloud data, also known as the CloudCover Protocol.

CloudCover Protocol

Today, the underwriting protocol for real-time (in-transit) data insurance is uniquely focused on the world’s first cyber risk-transfer system and method to comprehensively "underwrite to insure" real-time information, digital media, web-based payment processing systems, security modernization of health care records, the safety of financial securities transactions, and other online commerce that involve risks associated with valuable personal identifiable information (PII) assets. 

History

In 1996, Mr. Cardot began to develop one of the world’s first online bank projects and further engaged secure online banking technology over the Internet. Cardot produced and directed numerous web projects and online product introductions over the Internet 90’s. He worked on numerous Fortune 500 projects and incorporated online security web-technologies to solve the very early stages of Internet security and privacy. With 30 years of experience in marketing and design, with an emphasis on web systems and integration, Cardot focused on data insurance over the previous decade. With an extensive background working on some of the world’s most complex online information issues, Cardot was inspired to promote effective responsible behavior concerning privacy and security online.

With so much attention to protect and secure e-commerce with encryption, Cardot initiated U.S. process patents in 1998 to insure the transmission of data over the Internet. This intellectual area was uncharted within the cyber-risk insurance market. The first process patents were published and issued: 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009 and 2011 respectively. Mr. Cardot has authored numerous patents and continues to pioneer real-time data insurance and supporting technology for in-transit risk to digital assets.

Issued:

Systems and methods for insuring data over the Internet: US 6,922,720

Systems and methods for insuring data transmissions: US 7,020,692

Systems for underwriting coverage for data transmissions: US 7,246,157

System &amp; methods for reports based transmission claims: US 7,349,954

Methods-apparatus for providing coverage for transmission data: US 7,555,535

Methods-apparatus for providing coverage for receiver of transmission data: US 7,711,646


Pending:

IP Data Insurance Policy Management System: PCT 12/388,292

IP Data Transmission Insurance System: PCT 12/388,269</text>
      <sha1>0ggtqjl6t5tfylxtpw1xurzhvi8sv2k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>