<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Citation index</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>423362</id>
    <revision>
      <id>555929783</id>
      <parentid>540354304</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-20T11:14:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tanjabu</username>
        <id>19045066</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>link [[Histcite]] using [[User:Edward/Find link|Find link]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A '''citation index''' is a kind of [[bibliographic database]], an index of [[citation]]s between publications, allowing the user to easily establish which later documents cite which earlier documents. The first citation indices were legal [[citator]]s such as [[Shepard's Citations]] (1873). In 1960, [[Eugene Garfield]]'s [[Institute for Scientific Information]] (ISI) introduced the first citation index for papers published in [[academic journal]]s, first the ''[[Science Citation Index]]'' (SCI), and later the ''[[Social Sciences Citation Index]]'' (SSCI) and the ''[[Arts and Humanities Citation Index]]'' (AHCI). The first automated citation indexing was done by [[CiteSeer]] in 1997. Other sources for such data include [[Google Scholar]].

==Major citation indexing services==
General-purpose academic citation indexes include:

*ISI (now part of [[Thomson Scientific]]) publishes the ISI citation indexes in print and [[compact disc]]. They are now generally accessed through the Web under the name '' [[Web of Science]]'', which is in turn part of the group of databases in the ''[[Web of Knowledge]].''
*[[Elsevier]] publishes [[Scopus]], available online only, which similarly combines subject searching with citation browsing and tracking in the sciences and [[social sciences]].
*[[Indian Citation Index (ICI)|Indian Citation Index]] is an online citation data which covers [[peer review]]ed journals published from India. It covers major subject areas such as scientific, technical, medical, and [[social sciences]] and includes arts and humanities. The citation database is the first of its kind in India.
Each of these offer an index of citations between publications and a mechanism to establish which documents cite which other documents. They differ widely in cost: the ISI databases and Scopus are available by subscription (generally to libraries).

In addition, [[CiteSeer]] and [[Google Scholar]] are freely available online.

==Citation analysis==

While citation indexes were originally designed for [[information retrieval]], they are increasingly used for [[bibliometrics]] and other studies involving research evaluation. Citation data is also the basis of the popular [[journal impact factor]].

There is a large body of literature on [[citation analysis]], sometimes called [[scientometrics]], a term invented by [[Vasily Nalimov]], or more specifically [[bibliometrics]]. The field blossomed with the advent of the [[Science Citation Index]], which now covers source literature from 1900 on. The leading journals of the field are ''[[Scientometrics]],'' ''Informetrics,'' and the ''[[Journal of the American Society of Information Science and Technology]]''. [[American Society for Information Science and Technology|ASIST]] also hosts an [[electronic mailing list]] called SIGMETRICS at  ASIST.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The American Society for Information Science &amp; Technology | work=The Information Society for the Information Age | url=http://www.asis.org| accessdate=2006-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; This method is undergoing a resurgence based on the wide dissemination of the Web of Science and Scopus subscription databases in many universities, and the universally available free citation tools such as  [[CiteBase]],  [[CiteSeerX]], [[Google Scholar]], and the former [[Windows Live Academic]] (now available with extra features as [[Microsoft Academic Search]]).

[[Legal citation]] analysis is a citation analysis technique for analyzing [[legal documents]] to facilitate the understanding of the inter-related regulatory compliance documents by the exploration the citations that connect provisions to other provisions within the same document or between different documents. Legal citation analysis uses a [[citation graph]] extracted from a regulatory document, which could supplement [[E-discovery]] - a process that leverages on technological innovations in [[big data analytics]].&lt;ref&gt;http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/search/wrapper.jsp?arnumber=5070630&amp;tag=1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mohammad Hamdaqa and A. Hamou-Lhadj, "Citation Analysis: An Approach for Facilitating the Understanding and the Analysis of Regulatory Compliance Documents",  In Proc. of the 6th International Conference on Information Technology, Las Vegas, USA&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BD-HB-R-01&gt;{{cite web|title=E-Discovery Special Report: The Rising Tide of Nonlinear Review|url=http://hudsonlegalblog.com/e-discovery/e-discovery-special-report-rising-tide-nonlinear-review.html|publisher=[[Hudson Global]]|accessdate=1 July 2012}} by Cat Casey and Alejandra Perez&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BD-HB-R-02&gt;{{cite web|title=What Technology-Assisted Electronic Discovery Teaches Us About The Role Of Humans In Technology - Re-Humanizing Technology-Assisted Review|url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/benkerschberg/2012/01/09/what-technology-assisted-electronic-discovery-teaches-us-about-the-role-of-humans-in-technology/|publisher=[[Forbes]]|accessdate=1 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In a 1965 paper, [[Derek J. de Solla Price]] described the inherent linking characteristic of the SCI as "Networks of Scientific Papers".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Derek J. de Solla Price | title=Networks of Scientific Papers | journal=[[Science (journal)|SCIENCE]] | date=July 30, 1965 | volume=149 | issue=3683| pages=510&amp;ndash;515 | url=http://garfield.library.upenn.edu/papers/pricenetworks1965.pdf | pmid=14325149 | doi=10.1126/science.149.3683.510|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; The links between citing and cited papers became dynamic when the SCI began to be published online. The [[Social Sciences Citation Index]] became one of the first databases to be mounted on the [[Dialog]] system&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Dialog, A Thomson Business | work="Dialog invented online information services" | url=http://www.dialog.com| accessdate=2006-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 1972. With the advent of the [[CD-ROM]] edition, linking became even easier and enabled the use of [[bibliographic coupling]] for finding related records. In 1973, Henry Small published his classic work on [[Co-Citation analysis]] which became a [[Self-organization|self-organizing]] classification system that led to [[document clustering]] experiments and eventually an "Atlas of Science" later called "Research Reviews".

The inherent topological and graphical nature of the worldwide citation network which is an inherent property of the [[scientific literature]] was described by [[Ralph Garner]] ([[Drexel University]]) in 1965.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.garfield.library.upenn.edu/rgarner.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of citation counts to rank journals was a technique used in the early part of the nineteenth century but the systematic ongoing measurement of these counts for scientific journals was initiated by Eugene Garfield at the Institute for Scientific Information who also pioneered the use of these counts  to rank [[journal author|authors]] and [[academic paper|papers]].  In a landmark paper of 1965 he and [[Irving Sher]] showed the correlation between citation frequency and eminence in demonstrating that [[Nobel Prize]] winners published five times the average number of papers while their work was cited 30 to 50 times the average. In a long series of essays on the Nobel and other prizes Garfield reported this phenomenon.  The usual summary measure is known as [[impact factor]], the number of citations to a journal for the previous two years, divided by the number of articles published in those years. It is widely used, both for appropriate and inappropriate purposes—in particular, the use of this measure alone for  ranking [[journal author|authors]] and [[academic paper|papers]] is therefore [[Impact factor#|quite controversial.]]

In an early study in 1964 of the use of Citation Analysis in writing the history of [[DNA]], Garfield and Sher demonstrated the potential for generating [[historiograph]]s, [[topological map]]s of the most important steps in the history of scientific topics. This work was later automated by E. Garfield, [[A. I. Pudovkin]] of the [[Institute of Marine Biology]], [[Russian Academy of Sciences]] and [[V. S. Istomin]] of [[Center for Teaching, Learning, and Technology]], [[Washington State University]] and led to the creation of the [[Histcite|HistCite]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Eugene Garfield, A. I. Pudovkin,  V. S. Istomin | year=2002 | title=Algorithmic Citation-Linked Historiography—Mapping the Literature of Science | work=Presented the ASIS&amp;T 2002: Information, Connections and Community. 65th Annual Meeting of ASIST in Philadelphia, PA. November 18–21, 2002  | url=http://www.garfield.library.upenn.edu/papers/asis2002/asis2002presentation.html | accessdate=2006-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; software around 2002.

Autonomous citation indexing was introduced in 1998 by [[Lee Giles]], [[Steve Lawrence]] and [[Kurt Bollacker]] &lt;ref&gt;C.L. Giles, K. Bollacker, S. Lawrence, "CiteSeer: An Automatic Citation Indexing System," DL'98 Digital Libraries, 3rd ACM Conference on Digital Libraries, pp. 89-98, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; and enabled automatic algorithmic extraction and grouping of citations for any digital academic and scientific document. Where previous citation extraction was a manual process, citation measures could now scale up and be computed for any scholarly and scientific field and document venue, not just those selected by organizations such as ISI. This led to the creation of new systems for public and automated citation indexing, the first being [[CiteSeer]] (now [[CiteSeerX]], soon followed by Cora, which focused primarily on the field of [[computer science]] and [[information science]]. These were later followed by large scale academic domain citation systems such as the Google Scholar and Microsoft Academic. Such autonomous citation indexing is not yet perfect in citation extraction or citation clustering with an error rate estimated by some at 10% though a careful statistical sampling has yet to be done. This has resulted in such authors as [[Ann Arbor, Michigan|Ann Arbor]], [[Milton Keynes]], and [[Walton Hall, Milton Keynes|Walton Hall]] being credited with extensive academic output.&lt;ref name="pmid18354457"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Postellon DC |title=Hall and Keynes join Arbor in the citation indexes |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]] |volume=452 |issue=7185 |pages=282 |year=2008 |month=March |pmid=18354457 |doi=10.1038/452282b}}&lt;/ref&gt;  SCI claims to create automatic citation indexing through purely programmatic methods. Even the older records have a similar magnitude of error.

==See also==
* [[Impact factor]]
* [[Citation impact]]
* [[Eigenfactor]]
* [[Microsoft Academic Search]]
* [[Google Scholar]]
* [[Scopus]]
* [[H-index]] or [[Hirsch number]]
* [[Citation analysis]]
* [[Acknowledgment index]]
* [[CiteSeer]]
* [[CiteSeerX]]
* [[Scientific journal]]
* [[Science Citation Index]]
* [[Indian Citation Index]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links ==
* Official [http://admin-apps.isiknowledge.com/JCR/JCR Journal Citation Report] from the [http://www.isinet.com ISI website]
* [http://www.librijournal.org/2005-4toc.html Google Scholar: The New Generation of Citation Indexes]
* [http://www.atlasofscience.net/ Atlas of Science: Mapping Science by means of citation relations]
* [http://www.dlib.org/dlib/september05/bauer/09bauer.html An Examination of Citation Counts in a New Scholarly Communication Environment]
* [http://cids.fc.ul.pt/ CIDS] online tool that calculates the h-index and [[g-index]] based on [[Google Scholar]] data and discerning self-citations

{{DEFAULTSORT:Citation Index}}
[[Category:Academic publishing]]
[[Category:Bibliometrics]]
[[Category:Library science]]
[[Category:Reputation management]]
[[Category:Citation indices]]</text>
      <sha1>qfsvdzil9o9dhskc4bj24f297ehhlf4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>