<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Cloudant</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30498279</id>
    <revision>
      <id>553354380</id>
      <parentid>547293110</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-03T14:50:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>130.199.3.165</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| name             = Cloudant
| company_logo     = [[Image:Cloudant companyLogo.jpg|225 px]]
| type             = Private
| founded      = [[2008]]
| founder          = Alan Hoffman (Chief Product Officer) &lt;br&gt; Adam Kocoloski (CTO) &lt;br&gt;Mike Miller (Chief Scientist)
| location    = [[Boston]], USA&lt;br&gt;[[Seattle]], USA&lt;br&gt;[[Bristol]], UK
| industry         = Software
| homepage         = [https://cloudant.com/ cloudant.com]
}}

'''Cloudant''' is a [[Massachusetts]]-based enterprise software company which provides an [[open source]] non-relational, distributed database service of the same name that requires zero-configuration. Cloudant is based on the [[Apache Software Foundation|Apache]]-backed [[CouchDB]] project and the creator of the open source [[BigCouch]] project. 

Cloudant's service provides integrated data management, search, and analytics engine designed for [[web applications]]. Cloudant scales your database on the CouchDB framework and provides hosting, administrative tools, analytics and commercial support for CouchDB and BigCouch.&lt;ref name="techcrunch"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://techcrunch.com/2010/09/03/cloudant/ |title= YC-Funded Cloudant Launches Its NoSQL Cloud Database Platform |accessdate= 15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cloudant's distributed CouchDB service is used just like you would use standalone CouchDB, with the added advantage of your data being redundantly distributed over multiple machines.

Cloudant is often considered part of a new generation of '[[NoSQL (concept)|NoSQL]]' databases that don't require fixed table schemas and is challenging the dominance of traditional relational databases (including the popular [[MySQL]]).

== History ==
Cloudant was founded by Alan Hoffman, Adam Kocoloski, and Michael Miller. The three met in the physics department at [[MIT]] where they worked with multi-petabyte data sets from experiments such as the [[Large Hadron Collider]] and the [[Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider]]. In early 2008 their ideas for fixing the ‘[[big data]] problem’ caught the attention of Silicon Valley-based [[Y Combinator (company)|Y Combinator]], which resulted in $20k seed funding. The company also received an early seed round of $1 million dollars from Avalon Ventures in August 2010.

Cloudant was born out of the founders’ collective frustration with the tools available to serve ‘big data,’ and was designed explicitly to take advantage of the cloud, automatically distributing data across multiple servers in addition to scaling the database to accommodate the ever-changing needs of web applications. 

In August 2010, Cloudant released [[BigCouch]] for free under an [[Apache License]](2.0).  Cloudant supports many open source projects including HAProxy, Opscode [[Chef (software)|Chef]], Rebar and many more. Cloudant offers services including support, consulting services and training (both public and private).

Cloudant has been gaining good traction ever since they delivered their first version of Cloudant in Q3 of 2010.&lt;ref name="cloudave"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cloudave.com/9417/cloudant-gains-traction-with-hosted-couchdb-and-analytics-offering |title= Cloudant Gains Traction With Hosted CouchDB And Analytics Offering |accessdate= 13 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cloudant has over 2500 customers for its hosted service as of January 2011.

== Data Model ==
[[CouchDB]] and Cloudant have the same REST API so you can use them in the same way.  Cloudant-developed [[BigCouch]] is an open-source fork of CouchDB. Cloudant is actively working with the CouchDB community to provide BigCouch features back into the main branch of CouchDB.

Cloudant's hosted service makes clustering similar to Voldemort, Cassandra, or Riak, as it implements a version of Amazon's [[Dynamo_(storage_system)]].&lt;ref name="cloudant"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://cloudant.com/blog/dynamo-and-couchdb-clusters/|title= Dynamo and CouchDB Clusters|accessdate= 15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cloudant takes advantage of the reliability, simplicity, and power of CouchDB and adds distribution, scalability, and 'cloud readiness.’

== Differences with CouchDB ==

Cloudant's hosted database extends CouchDB in several ways:
* Chained MapReduce Views&lt;ref name="cloudantmapreduce"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.cloudant.com/kb/views/chained-mapreduce-views|title= Chained MapReduce View|accessdate = 19 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Java Language View Server&lt;ref name="infoq"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.infoq.com/news/2010/09/cloudant-couchdb-java-viewserver|title=Cloudant Releases Java Based View Server for CouchDB|accessdate = 19 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; allows usage of Java for CouchDB map reduce analytics.
* vhosts
* API keys for programmatic access to CouchDB database.

== Awards and Recognition ==
In November 2010, Cloudant was recognized as one of ‘10 Cool Open-Source Startups’ by CRN.&lt;ref name="cloudantrn"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crn.com/slide-shows/applications-os/228201058/10-cool-open-source-startups.htm;jsessionid=VoyLlCdudD0g2vX4UgUzJA**.ecappj02?pgno=4|title= '10 Cool Open-Source Startups’|accessdate= 15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cloudant is regularly recognized in the local Boston startup community, named as one of the ‘Top 5 Database Startups’&lt;ref name="cloudanthub5"&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.hightechinthehub.com/2010/09/top-5-database-startups-in-boston/ |title= ‘Top 5 Database Startups’ |accessdate= 15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ‘Top Ten Cloud Computing Startups’&lt;ref name="cloudanthubstart"&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.hightechinthehub.com/2010/09/cloud-computing-in-boston/ |title= ‘Top Ten Cloud Computing Startups’|accessdate= 15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Boston’s popular technology column by Joe Kinsella, ‘High Tech in the Hub.’.&lt;ref name="cloudanthub"&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.hightechinthehub.com |title= High Tech in the Hub |accessdate= 15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons category|Database}}
{{Commons category|Database models}}
* [[Apache Software Foundation]]
* [[BigCouch]]
* [[Big data]]
* [[CouchDB]]
* [[Cloud computing]]
* [[Cloud infrastructure]]
* [[Database-centric architecture]]
* [[Datastructure]]
* [[NoSQL (concept)|NoSQL]]
* [[Real time database]]

== References ==
&lt;!--- See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.cloudant.com/ Cloudant]
* [http://couchdb.apache.org/ CouchDB]
* [https://github.com/cloudant/bigcouch/ BigCouch]
* [http://blog.cloudant.com/full-text-search-for-cloudants-hosted-couchdb Developer Preview: Cloudant Search for CouchDB]

[[Category:Cloud computing]]
[[Category:Cloud infrastructure]]
[[Category:Distributed file systems]]
[[Category:Software companies based in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]</text>
      <sha1>rdsnr9fp54l1ksv6h9tgzn2rm0bqjr9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>