<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Cloudera</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27059655</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562205885</id>
      <parentid>561411014</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-30T05:30:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.108.25.112</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ remove section. most are technologies. this article is about the company. the relevant ones are already linked in the article</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| name              = Cloudera
| logo              = [[Image:Cloudera logo v2.png|200px]] 
| genre             = Software Development
| location          = [[Palo Alto, California]]
| area_served       = Worldwide
| num_employees     = 400&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dbms2.com/2013/06/23/hadoop-news-and-rumors-june-23-2013/&lt;/ref&gt;
| homepage      = {{URL|http://www.cloudera.com/}}
}}

'''Cloudera Inc.''' is a [[Palo Alto]]-based American enterprise software company that provides [[Apache Hadoop]]-based software, support and services, and training to data driven enterprises.

Cloudera's open-source Apache Hadoop distribution, CDH (Cloudera Distribution Including Apache Hadoop), targets enterprise-class deployments of that technology. Cloudera says that more than 50% of its engineering output is donated upstream to the various Apache-licensed open source projects (Apache Hive, Apache Avro, Apache HBase, and so on) that combine to form the Hadoop platform. Cloudera is also a sponsor of the [[Apache Software Foundation]].&lt;ref name="Apache Software Foundation Sponsorship"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apache.org/foundation/sponsorship.html|title=Apache Software Foundation Sponsorship|accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The preferred [[demonym]] for an employee of Cloudera is "Clouderan."&lt;ref name="Use of the term Clouderan to refer to an employee of Cloudera"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2012/12/how-to-contribute-to-apache-hadoop-projects-in-24-minutes/|title=Use of the term Clouderan to refer to an employee of Cloudera|accessdate=12 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History and investors ==

The launch of Cloudera was announced by ''[[The New York Times]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/03/16/bottling-the-magic-behind-google-and-facebook/|title=Bottling the Magic Behind Google and Facebook|last=Vance|first=Ashlee|date=16 March 2010|accessdate=22 April 2010 | work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; which called Cloudera "the quintessential Silicon Valley story". That article's author explained how three top engineers from [[Google]], [[Yahoo]] and [[Facebook Inc.|Facebook]] ([[Christophe Bisciglia]], Amr Awadallah and Jeff Hammerbacher, respectively) had joined with a former [[Oracle]] executive (Mike Olson) to "tackle the problems inherent in quickly analyzing big piles of data." 

In March 2009, Cloudera announced the availability of Cloudera Distribution Including [[Apache Software Foundation|Apache]] [[Hadoop]] in conjunction with a $5-million capital injection led by [[Accel Partners]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://techcrunch.com/2009/03/16/cloudera-raises-5-million-series-a-round-for-hadoop-commercialization/|title=Cloudera Raises $5 Million Series A Round For Hadoop Commercialization|last=Wauters |first=Robin|date=16 March 2010|publisher=TechCrunch|accessdate=22 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, the company raised a further $40 million from [[Ignition Partners]], [[Accel Partners]], [[Greylock Partners]], [[Meritech Capital Partners]], and [[In-Q-Tel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://venturebeat.com/2011/11/07/hadoop-cloudera-funding-ignition-accel-greylock/|title=Hadoop-based startup Cloudera raises $40M from Ignition Partners, Accel, Greylock|accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Products ==

Cloudera offers software, services and support in three different bundles:
* Cloudera Enterprise - includes CDH and an annual subscription license (per node) to Cloudera Manager and technical support
* Cloudera Enterprise Free - includes CDH and Cloudera Manager Free Edition (CM Free Edition somewhat limited functionality)
* CDH may also be downloaded from Cloudera's website at no charge, but with no technical support nor Cloudera Manager

CDH contains the main, core elements of Hadoop that provide reliable, scalable distributed data processing of large data sets (chiefly MapReduce and HDFS), as well as other enterprise-oriented components that provide security, high availability, and integration with hardware and other software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.informationweek.com/software/information-management/cloudera-releases-next-generation-hadoop/240001574/|title=Cloudera Releases Next-Generation Hadoop Platform|last=Henschen |first=Doug|date=6 June 2012|publisher=InformationWeek|accessdate=22 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Oct. 2012, Cloudera announced the Impala project, an open-source distributed query engine for Apache Hadoop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zdnet.com/clouderas-impala-brings-hadoop-to-sql-and-bi-7000006413/|title=Cloudera’s Impala brings Hadoop to SQL and BI|last=Brust |first=Andrew|date=6 October 25, 2012|publisher=ZDNet|accessdate=1 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Management ==

Cloudera's management team includes:
* CEO Tom Reilly was formerly vice president and general manager of enterprise security at HP. Previous to HP, Tom served as CEO of enterprise security company ArcSight, which HP acquired in 2010. Tom led ArcSight through a successful initial public offering and subsequent sale to HP. Before ArcSight, Tom was vice president of business information services for IBM, following the acquisition of Trigo Technologies Inc., a master data management (MDM) software company, where he had served as CEO.
* Chief strategy officer (CSO) Mike Olson. Co-founded Cloudera in 2008 and served as its CEO until 2013 when he took on his current role. Was formerly the CEO of [[Sleepycat Software]], the creator of the open-source embedded database engine [[Berkeley DB]] (acquired by Oracle in 2006). Prior to joining Sleepycat, Mike held technical and business positions at Britton Lee, Illustra Information Technologies, and Informix Software.
* COO Kirk Dunn was formerly CEO of PowerFile, Inc. (acquired by Hitachi LG Data Storage) and Bang Networks Inc. He also has held positions at Inktomi, Network Equipment Technologies, Inc., and IBM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://investing.businessweek.com/research/stocks/private/person.asp?personId=1032567&amp;privcapId=5648440&amp;previousCapId=5648440&amp;previousTitle=PowerFile,%20Inc.
|title=Bloomberg Business Week, Executive Profile Kirk Dunn 
|accessdate=30 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* CTO Dr. Amr Awadallah was formerly VP of Product Intelligence Engineering at [[Yahoo!|Yahoo]], where he ran one of the first business units using Hadoop for data analysis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.businessinsider.com/2012-01-31/news/31008410_1_yahoo-servers-and-storage-systems-oracle|title=This Former Yahoo-er's Startup Is So Hot, Even the CIA Invested In It|accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chief Scientist Jeff Hammerbacher conceived and led the "data team" at Facebook, which used Hadoop as a platform for building strategic analytic applications involving massive volumes of user data.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/11_17/b4225060960537.htm|title=This Tech Bubble Is Different|accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Architect [[Doug Cutting]], also currently chairman of the [[Apache Software Foundation]], authored the open-source [[Lucene]] and [[Nutch]] search technologies before he wrote the initial Hadoop codebase in 2004. He designed and managed a production Hadoop storage and analysis cluster at Yahoo! before joining Cloudera in 2009.

== Awards ==

* In April 2010, Chief Scientist Jeff Hammerbacher was named a "Best Young Tech Entrepreneur" by Bloomberg BusinessWeek.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/technology/special_reports/20100420best_young_tech_entrepreneurs.htm|title=Best Young Technology Entrepreneurs 2010|accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In June 2012, received [[Morgan Stanley]]'s "CTO Award for Innovation".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marketwatch.com/story/cloudera-honored-by-morgan-stanley-with-prestigious-cto-award-for-innovation-2012-06-28|title=Cloudera Honored by Morgan Stanley With Prestigious 'CTO Award for Innovation'|accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In August 2012, CRN named Cloudera among the "The 25 Coolest Emerging Vendors For 2012".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crn.com/slide-shows/storage/240005642/the-25-coolest-emerging-vendors-for-2012.htm|title=The 25 Coolest Emerging Vendors For 2012|accessdate=28 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cloudera.com Official web site]

[[Category:Cloud computing]]
[[Category:Cloud infrastructure]]
[[Category:Distributed file systems]]
[[Category:Hadoop]]</text>
      <sha1>tg4gpzl312eem2yhqpfxx93a0rm3lox</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>