<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Competitive programming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34493264</id>
    <revision>
      <id>560053687</id>
      <parentid>554004538</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-15T18:39:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.193.52.34</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Online contest and training resources */ prefer notable sites (e.g. ones with Wikipedia articles) to unverified ones</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Competitive programming''' is a [[mind sport]] usually held over the [[internet]] or a [[local network]], involving participants trying to [[Computer programming|program]] according to provided specifications. Competitive programming is recognized and supported by several multinational software and internet companies, such as [[Google]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://code.google.com/codejam Google Code Jam]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.topcoder.com/tco12/overview-sponsor/tco12-sponsor-google/ Google sponsor page for TCO 2012]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Facebook]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.facebook.com/hackercup Facebook HackerCup]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[IBM]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/university/students/contests/acm/index.html ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest World Finals Sponsored by IBM]&lt;/ref&gt; As of January 2012 there are several organizations who host programming competitions on a regular basis.

A programming competition generally involves the host presenting a set of [[logic]]al or [[Mathematics|mathematical]] problems to the contestants (who can vary in number from tens to several thousands), and contestants are required to write [[computer program]]s capable of solving each problem. Judging is based mostly upon number of problems solved and time spent for writing successful solutions, but may also include other factors (quality of output produced, execution time, program size etc.)

== History ==
Since programming itself is a very recently developed branch of science, competitive programming is a very young sport. One of the oldest contests known is [[ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest|ACM ICPC]] which originated in the 1970s, and has grown to include 88 countries in its 2011 edition. Interest in competitive programming has grown extensively{{quantify|date=October 2012}} since 2000, and is strongly connected to the growth of the [[internet]], which facilitates holding international contests online, eliminating geographical problems.

== Overview ==
The aim of Competitive Programming is to write [[source code]] of computer programs which are able to solve given problems. A vast majority of problems appearing in programming contests are mathematical or logical in nature. Typical such tasks belong to one of the following categories : [[combinatorics]], [[number theory]], [[graph theory]], [[geometry]], [[String (computer science)|string analysis]] and [[data structure]]s. Problems related to [[artificial intelligence]] are also popular in certain competitions.

Irrespective of the problem category, the process of solving a problem can be divided into two broad steps, constructing an efficient [[algorithm]], and implementing the algorithm in a suitable [[programming language]] (the set of programming languages allowed varies from contest to contest). These are the two most commonly tested skills in programming competitions.

In most contests, the judging is done automatically by host machines, commonly known as judges. Every solution submitted by a contestant is run on the judge against a set of (usually secret) test cases. Normally, contest problems have an all-or-none marking system, meaning that a solution is "Accepted" only if it produces satisfactory results on all test cases run by the judge, and rejected otherwise. However, some contest problems may allow for partial scoring, depending on the number of test cases passed, the quality of the results, or some other specified criteria. Some other contests only require that the contestant submit the output corresponding to given input data, in which case the judge only has to analyze the submitted output data.

== Notable Competitions ==
There are two types of competition formats: short-term and long-term. Each round of short-term competition lasts from 1 to 3 hours. Long-term competitions can last from a few days to a few months.

=== Short-term ===
* [[International Olympiad in Informatics|IOI]] - one of the oldest competitions, for secondary school students
* [[ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest|ACM ICPC]] - one of the oldest competitions, for students of universities in groups of 3 persons each;
* [[Google Code Jam]] - competition held from 2003, provided and sponsored by [[Google]];
* [[Facebook Hacker Cup]] - competition held from 2011, provided and sponsored by [[Facebook]];
* TopCoder Algorithm Open - competition held since 2004 by [[TopCoder]].

In most of the above competitions, since number of contestants are quite large, competitions are usually organized in several rounds. They usually require "online" participation in all rounds except the last, which require "onsite" participation. The top performers at IOI and ACM ICPC receive gold, silver and bronze medals while in the other contests, cash prizes are awarded to the top finishers. Also hitting the top places in the score tables of such competitions may attract interest of recruiters from software and Internet companies.

=== Long-term ===
* [[TopCoder]] Marathon matches
* [[Kaggle]];
* Google [[AI Challenge]];
* [http://www.azspcs.net/ Al Zimmermann's Programming Contests];
* [http://infinitesearchspace.dyndns.org Infinite Search Space Competitions];
* [http://www.v-sonline.com/index.pl Virtual Source Programming Contests].

== Online contest and training resources ==
The programming community around the world has created and maintained several internet-resources dedicated to competitive programming. They offer standalone contests with or without minor prizes. Also the past archives of problems are a popular resource for training in competitive programming. These include:
* [[TopCoder]] - US resource and company, which organizes contests and also provides industrial problems as a kind of free-lance job; it offers dozens of short contests and several long ("marathons") every year. Specific feature - participants have a chance to check correctness of other contestants' solutions after coding phase and before final automatic testing (so called "challenge phase").
* [[SPOJ]] - Polish [[online judge]] system which provides a lot of problems for training, and provides a platform for other organizers to host their programming contests.
* [[Codeforces]] - Russian resource, maintained by [[Saratov State University]], which mostly provides frequent (up to two per week) short contests. Special features: ability to check correctness of other contestants' solutions during "coding phase", virtual contests, trainings etc.
* [[Internet Problem Solving Contest]] - Annual contest for teams up to three people.
* [[UVa Online Judge]] Contains over 3,500 problems for practicing. Hosts regular online competitions.
* [[Project Euler]] - Large collection of computational math problems
* [[Light Online Judge]] or Lightoj contains categorised problems for practice. Also users can host their own contests by uploading dataset or selecting problems from Lightoj.
* [[Hust Virtual Judge]] a platform for arranging own virtual contests. Problems can be added from almost all popular online judges,no dataset needed.
* [[Codechef]] - Maintained by [[Directi]], it hosts a 10 day long contest and another short contest every month, and provides a contest platform.
* Timus Online Judge - Russian resource, maintained by [[Ural State University]], which mostly provides ~10 contests per year.
* InterviewStreet&lt;ref&gt;https://www.interviewstreet.com/challenges/&lt;/ref&gt; - Indian startup operates from Mountain View Startup, organizes codesprints and host online coding rounds for several companies
* HackerRank&lt;ref&gt;https://www.hackerRank.com/&lt;/ref&gt; - Indian startup operates from Mountain View Startup, hosts a diverse set of challenges from Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, Big data apart from Algorithmic challenges. Also, conducts frequent coding contests for programmers. Powers coding contests of many schools and companies.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
Open-source project for running contests:
*[https://github.com/cms-dev/cms Contest Management System] Open-source tool in Python to run and manage a programming contest on a server [IOI2012].

[[Category:Programming contests]]</text>
      <sha1>17cnevkul3rhelrjgvjlq41i9pgof1z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>