<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Content repository API for Java</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2878742</id>
    <revision>
      <id>544155051</id>
      <parentid>537031631</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-14T18:14:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 1 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q1128624]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Content Repository API for Java''' ('''JCR''') is a specification for a [[Java (software platform)|Java]] platform [[application programming interface]] (API) to access [[content repository|content repositories]] in a uniform manner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theserverside.com/tt/articles/article.tss?l=JCRPract JCR: A Practitioner's Perspective, by Alexandru Popescu and Joseph Ottinger]&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=December 2010}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=93 Java API for XML Registries] - Another Java API for Registries and Repositories&lt;/ref&gt;{{failed verification|date=December 2010}} The content repositories are used in content management systems to keep the content data and also the [[metadata]] used in [[content management system]]s (CMS) such as versioning metadata. The specification was developed under the [[Java Community Process]] as JSR-170 (Version 1).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=170 JSR-170]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.day.com/specs/jcr/1.0/ JSR-170 (HTML version of the specification)]&lt;/ref&gt; and as JSR-283 (version 2)&lt;ref&gt;[http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=283 JSR-283]&lt;/ref&gt; The main [[Java package]] is &lt;code&gt;javax.jcr&lt;/code&gt;.

== Overview ==

A JCR is a type of [[object database]] tailored to storing, searching, and retrieving hierarchical data.  The JCR API grew out of the needs of content management systems, which require storing documents and other binary objects with associated metadata; however, the API is applicable to many additional types of applications.  In addition to object storage, the JCR provides: APIs for versioning of data; [[database transaction|transactions]]; observation of changes in data; and import or export of data to [[XML]] in a standard way.

== Data structure ==

The data in a JCR consists of a tree of nodes with associated properties.  Data is stored in the properties, which may hold simple values such as numbers and strings or binary data of arbitrary length. Nodes may optionally have one or more types associated with them which dictate the kinds of properties, number and type of child nodes, and certain behavioral characteristics of the nodes.  Nodes may point to other nodes via a special reference type property.  In this way nodes in a JCR offer both [[referential integrity]] and object-oriented concept of [[inheritance (computer science)|inheritance]].  Additional node types include the referenceable node type which allows the user to reference said node through use of a universally unique identifier.  Another popular type is the versionable type.  This makes the repository track a document's history and store copies of each version of the document.

== Queries ==
A JCR can export portions of its tree to XML in two standard formats and can import hierarchies directly from XML.  JSR 283 compliant implementations must support a standardized form of [[SQL]] for queries and a query object model QOM. JSR 283 deprecates the [[XPath]] query language defined in JSR 170.
The [[Apache Jackrabbit]] reference implementation of JCR also supports the integration of the [[Apache Lucene]] search engine to give full text searches of data in the repository.

== Available implementations ==

Both JSRs are led by [[David Nüscheler]] of [[Day Software]].  Day has both a commercial JCR implementation called Content Repository Extreme (CRX) and is involved in the open source [[Apache Jackrabbit]] JCR,&lt;ref&gt;[http://jackrabbit.apache.org Apache Jackrabbit home page]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://wiki.apache.org/jackrabbit/JcrLinks JCR links] to articles and applications based on JCR.&lt;/ref&gt; which had its 2.0 release in January 2010.  [[Jahia]], [[Hippo CMS]] and [[Magnolia (CMS)|Magnolia]]  are Enterprise Content Management systems built on the JCR API, using Jackrabbit as its repository by default, but able to plug in any other JSR-170 certified repository implementation. JSR-170 is also supported by [[Oracle Beehive]], Oracle's enterprise collaboration software. The eXo JCR by ObjectWeb is an open source repository with paid commercial support and documentation. Many other commercial vendors are working on JCR compatibility and products. [[Alfresco (software)|Alfresco]] is an open source content management system which provides a JCR API onto their repository. GX released the new [[GX WebManager Community Edition|community version]] of its Web [[enterprise content management]] (ECM) platform based natively on [[Apache Jackrabbit]] and JSR.

[http://www.exoplatform.com eXo Platform] JCR implementation on the
[http://wiki.exoplatform.com/xwiki/bin/view/JCR/eXo+JCR+Implementation company wiki].&lt;ref&gt;[http://wiki.exoplatform.com/xwiki/bin/view/JCR/eXo+JCR+Implementation eXo JCR Implementation]&lt;/ref&gt; eXo Platform 2 article on TheServerSide.com.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theserverside.com/tt/articles/article.tss?l=eXoPlatform2 TheServerSide.com: eXo Platform v2, Portal, JCR, ECM, Groupware and Business Intelligence: Part 2]&lt;/ref&gt;

[http://www.jboss.org/modeshape ModeShape] is a new open source JCR implementation that lets applications access existing information in external systems through the JCR API. ModeShape repositories can also federate content from multiple sources into one, unified repository.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jboss.org/modeshape ModeShape open source project]&lt;/ref&gt;

[http://www.jcrdev.com JCRDev.com] provides a common platform for JCR Developers. It is an online community built especially for people working on Java Content Repository.

PHP adaptions have been started by [[TYPO3]], translating the Java API to PHP.&lt;ref&gt;[http://forge.typo3.org/projects/package-phpcr phpCR]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://github.com/phpcr/phpcr phpcr on github]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[PHPCR]] interfaces are also implemented by Jackalope,&lt;ref&gt;[http://jackalope.github.com/ Jackalope: JCR for PHP]&lt;/ref&gt; a PHP frontend talking to the Jackrabbit backend through the WebDAV interface, and [[Midgard (software)|Midgard]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Midgard2 PHPCR provider hits 1.0|first=Henri|last=Bergius|url=http://bergie.iki.fi/blog/midgard2_phpcr_provider_hits_1-0/|date=2011-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; a cross-language content repository.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== See also ==
* [[Content Management Interoperability Services]] (CMIS), another content repository API

[[Category:Java enterprise platform]]
[[Category:Java specification requests]]
[[Category:Content management systems]]
[[Category:Database management systems]]

[[ru:Content repository API for Java]]</text>
      <sha1>6uypsvsv1ugm7vy60omi5x1lvlllnpk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>