<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Continuuity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37988515</id>
    <revision>
      <id>557558197</id>
      <parentid>536894592</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-30T18:27:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>209.172.102.90</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
{{Infobox company
| name = Continuuity
| type = [[Privately held company]]
| logo =
| industry = [[Big Data]], [[Cloud Computing]]
| foundation = 2011
| founders = Todd Papaioannou, Jonathan Gray, Nitin Motgi
| location = [[Palo Alto, California]], [[United States|USA]]
| key_people = {{nowrap begin}}Todd Papaioannou &lt;small&gt;(Co-founder and CEO)&lt;/small&gt;{{wrap}}Jonathan Gray &lt;small&gt;(Co-founder and CTO)&lt;/small&gt;{{wrap}}Nitin Motgi &lt;small&gt;(Co-founder)&lt;/small&gt;{{wrap}}Derek Wood &lt;small&gt;(DevOps)&lt;/small&gt;{{wrap}}Don Mosites &lt;small&gt;(User Experience)&lt;/small&gt;{{wrap}}Andreas Neumann &lt;small&gt;(Software)&lt;/small&gt;{{wrap}}Vikram Bhan &lt;small&gt;(Product)&lt;/small&gt;{{wrap}} Mario Lichtsinn &lt;small&gt;(Software)&lt;/small&gt;{{wrap}}
| num_employees =
| revenue =
| net_income =
| products = Continuuity AppFabric&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt;
| homepage = [http://www.continuuity.com// www.continuuity.com]
| footnotes =
}}

'''Continuuity''' is a cloud-based [[Big Data]] application platform for developers. Rather than simply providing another cloud service for writing and running [[Hadoop]] jobs, Continuuity allows developers to more easily build, deploy and manage Big Data applications on top of the components within the Hadoop ecosystem.&lt;ref&gt;http://gigaom.com/data/ex-yahoo-facebook-big-data-vets-launch-paas-for-hadoop/&lt;/ref&gt;

Packaged in Single-node, Hosted Private cloud, On-premise Private cloud and Public Cloud Editions, Continuuity has built a cloud-based application runtime platform called the Continuuity AppFabric. The company also provides an SDK and suite of developer tools that promise "push-button deployment" from the developer's local single node AppFabric to the cloud.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.drdobbs.com/cloud/big-data-was-a-data-play-now-its-a-devel/240012595&lt;/ref&gt;

==Product==

The company calls its product the Continuuity AppFabric, and it’s essentially a runtime for scalable Big Data applications. There are four core capabilities that comprise the AppFabric:&lt;ref&gt;http://gigaom.com/data/ex-yahoo-facebook-big-data-vets-launch-paas-for-hadoop/&lt;/ref&gt;
*Streams – allow users to send and store their data into the platform
*App Containers – allow users to process their data in real-time 
*Datasets – data and tables that store and index the output of applications that run in the App Containers
*Queries – allow users to access their data directly or write and deploy their own server-side query processors

These components sit on the Distributed Data Fabric that enables reading and writing to the underlying Hadoop infrastructure.

Continuuity AppFabric and a Software Development Kit allow developers to build applications in their IDE, run, test and debug them on their local machines, and when ready, "push to cloud" with a single click.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.datanami.com/datanami/2012-10-27/hadoop_world_special:_this_week_s_big_data_top_ten.html?page=8&lt;/ref&gt;  

Continuuity has simplified the entire Big Data application development lifecycle.&lt;ref&gt;http://devopsangle.com/2012/10/24/continuuity-launches-industrys-first-big-data-application-fabric/&lt;/ref&gt;

The platform currently supports Java applications only — a natural first step given that Hadoop is written in Java — but Continuuity plans to support other languages going forward.&lt;ref&gt;http://gigaom.com/data/ex-yahoo-facebook-big-data-vets-launch-paas-for-hadoop/&lt;/ref&gt;

From an integration perspective, Continuity supports REST interfaces.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.enterpriseappstoday.com/business-intelligence/former-yahoo-cloud-chief-aims-to-ease-hadoop-development.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Leadership==

Continuuity was started in 2011 by a team with deep domain expertise when it comes to Big Data,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.forbes.com/sites/davefeinleib/2012/10/23/big-data-startup-continuuity-comes-out-of-stealth-mode/&lt;/ref&gt; including Todd Papaioannou, former chief cloud architect at [[Yahoo]] and entrepreneur-in-residence at [[Battery Ventures]], and Jonathan Gray, founder of personalized news streaming startup Streamy and more recently a top engineer at [[Facebook]], where he worked on the company’s Messages product.&lt;ref&gt;http://pandodaily.com/2012/10/23/continuuity-comes-out-of-stealth-promising-big-data-for-small-developers/&lt;/ref&gt;

Papaioannou, along with cofounders Nitin Motgi and Jonathan Gray, were reportedly early adopters of the Hbase big data technology while working at companies such as Facebook and Yahoo.&lt;ref&gt;http://adtmag.com/articles/2012/10/24/continuuity-targets-big-data-developers.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

==Funding==
The startup received $2.5 million in seed funding in January 2012 from Battery Ventures, Andreessen Horowitz, Ignition Partners, and a group of angel investors&lt;ref&gt;http://pandodaily.com/2012/10/23/continuuity-comes-out-of-stealth-promising-big-data-for-small-developers/&lt;/ref&gt; On November 14, 2012, Continuuity, raised $10 million in a Series A round. The investors include Battery Ventures, Ignition Partners, Andreessen Horowitz, Data Collective and Amplify Partners.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.forbes.com/sites/tomtaulli/2012/11/14/continuuity-nabs-10m-to-drive-an-app-economy-for-big-data/&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Platform as a Service]]
* [[Big Data]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.continuuity.com// Continuuity Corporate Site ]

[[Category:Big Data]]
[[Category:Information technology companies]]
[[Category:Privately held companies based in California]]
[[Category:Companies established in 2011]]</text>
      <sha1>dg0fw97dcjbgd8wplhecvad0i180t7p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>