<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Data literacy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39675445</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562134043</id>
      <parentid>562133870</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-29T17:10:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Michael Hardy</username>
        <id>4626</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Related terms */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Data literacy''' is the ability to read, create and communicate data as information and has been formally described in varying ways. Discussion of the skills inherent to data literacy and possible instructional methods have emerged as [[data collection]] becomes routinized and talk of [[data analysis]] and [[big data]] has become commonplace in the news, business,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hey, A. J., Tony Hey, Tansley, S. and Tolle, K., Eds.|title=The fourth paradigm: data-intensive scientific discovery.|year=2009|publisher=Microsoft}}&lt;/ref&gt; government&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Open Data Philly|url=http://opendataphilly.org/|accessdate=14 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and society in countries across the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Na, L., &amp; Yan, Z.|title=Promote Data-intensive Scientific Discovery, Enhance Scientific and Technological Innovation Capability: New Model, New Method, and New Challenges Comments on" The Fourth Paradigm: Data-intensive Scientific Discovery|journal=Bulletin of Chinese Academy of Sciences|year=2013|volume=1|issue=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related terms==

Data literacy focuses on the ability to build knowledge from data, and to communicate that meaning to others. It is related to other fields, including:
* [[Media literacy]]
* [[Information literacy]]
* [[New literacies]]
* [[Numeracy]]
* [[Transliteracy]]
* [[21st-century skills]]

== Definitions ==
* A traditional view emphasizes the numeric, statistical nature of data as information, including "... understanding what data mean, including how to read graphs and charts appropriately, draw correct conclusions from data, and recognize when data are being used in misleading or inappropriate ways".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Carlson, J. R., Fosmire, M., Miller, C., Sapp Nelson, M.|title=Determining Data Information Literacy Needs: A Study of Students and Research Faculty|journal=Libraries Faculty and Staff Scholarship and Research|year=2011|volume=23|url=http://docs.lib.purdue.edu/lib_fsdocs/23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A more progressive view describes data literacy as "... the ability to: formulate and answer questions using data as part of evidence-based thinking; use appropriate data, tools, and representations to support this thinking;interpret information from data; develop and evaluate data-based inferences and explanations;and use data to solve real problems and communicate their solutions."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Vahey, P., Yarnall, L., Patton, C., Zalles, D., &amp; Swan, K.|title=Mathematizing middle school: Results from a cross-disciplinary study of data literacy.|journal=American Educators Research Association Annual Conference|year=2006|month=April|volume=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A workforce-focused example includes varying technical and digital formats by describing data literacy as "... competence in finding, manipulating, managing, and interpreting data, including not just numbers but also text and images."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Harris|first=Jeanne|title=Data Is Useless Without the Skills to Analyze It|url=http://blogs.hbr.org/cs/2012/09/data_is_useless_without_the_skills.html|work=Harvard Business Review|accessdate=14 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Literacy}}
[[Category:Computing and society]]
[[Category:Technology in society]]
[[Category:Literacy]]
[[Category:Mathematics]]
[[Category:Big Data]]
{{Education-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>920932s1h28ws28pneeemmlh41c2zpm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>