<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Data architect</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2406415</id>
    <revision>
      <id>544087463</id>
      <parentid>539550398</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-14T13:02:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 1 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q2860253]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A '''data architect''' in [[Information Technology]] is a person responsible for ensuring that the data assets of an organization are supported by a [[data architecture]] that aids the organization in achieving its strategic goals. The data architecture should cover [[database]]s, [[data integration]] and the means to get to the data. Usually the data architect achieves his/her goals via setting enterprise data standards. A Data Architect can also be referred to as a Data Modeler, although the role involves much more than just creating [[data model]]s.The work profile is related to Data Modeler.

The definition of an IT architecture used in [[IEEE 1471|ANSI/IEEE Std 1471-2000]] is:
''The fundamental organization of a system, embodied in its components, their relationships to each other and the environment, and the principles governing its design and evolution''., where the data architect primarily focuses on the aspects related to data.

In TOGAF (the Open Group Architecture Framework) [http://www.togaf.org], architecture has two meanings depending upon its contextual usage:
* A formal description of a system, or a detailed plan of the system at component level to guide its implementation
* The structure of components, their inter-relationships, and the principles and guidelines governing their design and evolution over time.

According to DAMA ([[Data Management]] Association)[http://www.dama.org], Data Architect is often interchangeable with, but includes enterprise architecture considerations. A DAMA recognized Certified Data Management Professional would have a wide range of such skills. 

Translating this to [[Data architecture]] helps defining the role of the data architect as the one responsible for developing and maintaining a formal description of the data and data structures - this can include data definitions, data models, [[data flow diagram]]s, etc. (in short [[metadata]]). [[Data architecture]] includes topics such as metadata management, business semantics, data modeling and metadata workflow management. 

A data architect's job frequently includes the set up a [[metadata registry]] and allows domain-specific stakeholders to maintain their own data elements. This is often implemented in an [[Master Data Management]] solution which enables centralized
management of business critical data.

Some fundamental skills of a Data Architect are:
* [[logical data model|Logical Data modeling]]
* [[physical data model|Physical Data modeling]]
* Development of a data strategy and associated polices
* Selection of capabilities and systems to meet business information needs

A Data Strategy enumerates the Data Policies each of which commit the organization to codifying a best practice. A policy may specify any one area of data standards; [[data security]] or [[Information Assurance]]; [[data retention]] or [[data steward]]ship. 

Data architects usually have experience in one or more of the following technologies:

* [[Data Dictionary|Data dictionaries]]
* [[Data warehouse|Data warehousing]]
* [[Enterprise application integration]]
* [[Metadata registry]]
* [[Master Data Management]] (MDM)
* [[Relational database|Relational Databases]]
* [[NoSQL]]
* [[Semantics]]
* [[Data retention]]
* [[Structured Query Language]] (SQL)
* [[Sql#Procedural_extensions|Procedural SQL]]
* [[Unified Modeling Language]] (UML)
* [[XML]], including [[XML schema|schema definitions]] (XSD and [[RELAX NG]]) and [[XSLT|transformations]].

==See also==
* [[Data Architecture]]
* [[Information security]]
* [[Semantic spectrum]]
* [[Disparate system]]
* [[System Integration]]


[[Category:Data management]]
[[Category:Data modeling]]
[[Category:Data security]]</text>
      <sha1>cbdfj5yg5sow9z3e7aroodehmijux7s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>