<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Data science</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35458904</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562292365</id>
      <parentid>561871374</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-30T20:16:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TedDunning</username>
        <id>5594752</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added earlier reference for the origin of the term "data scientist"</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2012}}
[[File:DataScienceDisciplines.png|thumb|Data Science]]
'''Data science'''  incorporates varying elements and builds on techniques and theories from many fields, including [[Mathematics|math]], [[statistics]], [[data engineering]], [[pattern recognition and learning]], [[computer programming|advanced computing]], [[Data visualization|visualization]], [[uncertainty modeling]], [[data warehousing]], and [[high performance computing]] with the goal of extracting meaning from data and creating data products. Data science is a novel term that is often used interchangeably with [[competitive intelligence]] or [[business analytics]], although it is becoming more common. Data science seeks to use all available and relevant data to effectively tell a story that can be easily understood by non-practitioners.

A practitioner of data science is called a data scientist. It has been claimed that the term was coined by DJ Patil and Jeff Hammerbacher&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/pictures/lmm45emkh/2-jeff-hammerbacher-chief-scientist-cloudera-and-dj-patil-entrepreneur-in-residence-greylock-ventures/|accessdate=11 March 2013|newspaper=Forbes}}&lt;/ref&gt;  but the term had been in use several years before they described their use of the term publicly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=National Science Board|title=Long-Lived Digital Data Collections Enabling Research and Education in the 21st Century|url=http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2005/nsb0540/|publisher=National Science Foundation|accessdate=30 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Data scientists solve complex data problems through employing deep expertise in some scientific discipline. It is generally expected that data scientists are able to work with various elements of mathematics, statistics and computer science, although expertise in these subjects are not required. However, a data scientist is most likely to be an expert in only one or two of these disciplines and proficient in another two or three. There is probably no living person who is an expert in all of these disciplines - if so they would be extremely rare. This means that data science must be practiced as a team, where across the membership of the team there is expertise and proficiency across all the disciplines. 

Good data scientists are able to apply their skills to achieve a broad spectrum of end results.  Some of these include the ability to find and interpret rich data sources, manage large amounts of data despite hardware, software and bandwidth constraints, merge data sources together, ensure consistency of data-sets, create visualizations to aid in understanding data and building rich tools that enable others to work effectively. The skill-sets and competencies that data scientists employ vary widely. Data scientists are an integral part of competitive intelligence, a newly emerging field that encompasses a number of activities, such as data mining and analysis, that can help businesses gain a competitive edge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=LaPonsie|first=Maryalene|title=Data scientists: The Hottest Job You Haven't Heard Of|url=http://jobs.aol.com/articles/2011/08/10/data-scientist-the-hottest-job-you-havent-heard-of/|accessdate=7 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

A major goal of data science is to make it easier for others to find and coalesce data with greater ease. Data science technologies impact how we access data and conduct research across various domains, including the biological sciences, medical informatics, social sciences and the humanities.

==Origins==
Data science has existed for over a decade. An early claimant to the term data science is William S. Cleveland&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.stat.purdue.edu/~wsc/ William S. Cleveland. Shanti S. Gupta Professor of Statistics. Courtesy Professor of Computer Science. Department of Statistics]. Purdue University&lt;/ref&gt; who wrote "Data Science: An Action Plan for Expanding the Technical Areas of the Field of Statistics', which was published in Volume 69, No. 1, of the April 2001 edition of the International Statistical Review / Revue Internationale de Statistique.&lt;ref name="cleveland01"&gt;Cleveland, W. S. (2001). Data science: an action plan for expanding the technical areas of the field of statistics. International Statistical Review / Revue Internationale de Statistique, 21-26&lt;/ref&gt; About a year later, in April 2002, the International Council for Science: Committee on Data for Science and Technology&lt;ref name="ics12"&gt;International Council for Science : Committee on Data for Science and Technology. (2012, April). CODATA, The Committee on Data for Science and Technology. Retrieved from International Council for Science : Committee on Data for Science and Technology: http://www.codata.org/&lt;/ref&gt; started publishing the CODATA ''Data Science Journal''.&lt;ref name="dsj12"&gt;Data Science Journal. (2012, April). Available Volumes. Retrieved from Japan Science and Technology Information Aggregator, Electronic: http://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/browse/dsj/_vols&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="dsj02"&gt;Data Science Journal. (2002, April). Contents of Volume 1, Issue 1, April 2002. Retrieved from Japan Science and Technology Information Aggregator, Electronic: http://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/browse/dsj/1/0/_contents&lt;/ref&gt;  Shortly thereafter, in January of 2003, Columbia University began publishing ''The Journal of Data Science''.&lt;ref name="jds03"&gt;The Journal of Data Science. (2003, January). Contents of Volume 1, Issue 1, January 2003.  Retrieved from http://www.jds-online.com/v1-1&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The term "data science" (originally used interchangeably with "[[datalogy]]") has existed for over thirty years and emerged as a substitute for [[computer science]] by [[Peter Naur]] in 1960. In 1974, Naur published ''Concise Survey of Computer Methods'', which freely used the term data science in its survey of the contemporary data processing methods that are used in a wide range of applications. In 1996, members of the International Federation of Classification Societies (IFCS) met in Tokyo for their biennial conference. Here, for the first time, the term data science is included in the title of the conference ("Data Science, classification, and related methods").

In 2001, William S. Cleveland introduced the notion of data science as an independent discipline, extending the field of statistics to incorporate "advances in computing with data" in his article "Data Science: An Action Plan for Expanding the Technical Areas of the Field of Statistics," which was published in Volume 69, No. 1, of the April 2001 edition of the International Statistical Review / Revue Internationale de Statistique.&lt;ref name="cleveland01"/&gt; In his report, Cleveland establishes six technical areas which he believed to encompass the field of data science: multidisciplinary investigations, models and methods for data, computing with data, pedagogy, tool evaluation, and theory. 

In April 2002, the International Council for Science: Committee on Data for Science and Technology (CODATA)&lt;ref name="ics12"/&gt; started the ''Data Science Journal'',&lt;ref name="dsj12"/&gt; a publication focused on issues such as the description of data systems, their publication on the internet, applications and legal issues.&lt;ref name="dsj02"/&gt; Shortly thereafter, in January 2003, Columbia University began publishing ''The Journal of Data Science'',&lt;ref name="jds03"/&gt; which provided a platform for all data workers to present their views and exchange ideas. The journal was largely devoted to the application of statistical methods and quantitative research. In 2005, The National Science Board published "Long-lived Digital Data Collections: Enabling Research and Education in the 21st Century" defining data scientists as "the information and computer scientists, database and software and programmers, disciplinary experts, curators and expert annotators, librarians, archivists, and others, who are crucial to the successful management of a digital data collection."

==Domain Specific Interests==
Data science is the practice of deriving valuable insights from data. Data science is emerging to meet the challenges of processing very large data sets i.e. "Big Data" consisting of structured, unstructured or semi-structured data that large enterprises produce. A domain at center stage of data science is the explosion of new data generated from smart devices, web, mobile and social media. Data science requires a versatile skill-set. Many practicing data scientist commonly specialize in specific domains such as marketing, medical, security, fraud and finance fields. However, data scientists rely heavily upon elements of statistics, machine learning, text retrieval and natural language processing to analyze data and interpret results.

==Research Areas==
As an interdisciplinary subject, data science draws scientific inquiry from a broad range of academic subject areas, mostly related to the hard scientist. Some areas of research are:

* Cloud computing
* Databases and information integration
* Learning, natural language processing and information extraction
* Computer vision
* Information retrieval and web information access
* Knowledge discovery in social and information networks

=== Security Data Science ===
Data science has a long and rich history in security and fraud monitoring. Paul Braxton founder of securitydatascience.org coined the term "security data science" and defined it as the application of advanced analytics to activity and access data to uncover unknown risks. Security data science is focused on advancing information security through practical applications of exploratory data analysis, statistics, machine learning and data visualization. Although the tools and techniques are no different that those used in data science in any data domain, this group has a micro-focus on reducing risk, identifying fraud or malicious insiders using data science. The information security and fraud prevention industry have been evolving security data science in order to tackle the challenges of managing and gaining insights from huge streams of log data, discover insider threats and prevent fraud.  Security data science is "data driven" meaning that new insights and value comes directly from data.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.securitydatascience.org&lt;/ref&gt;

==Conferences==
*DataEDGE Conference (Data EDucation a new GEneration of data-savvy professionals), held by School of Information, UC Berkeley, Google, [http://dataedge.ischool.berkeley.edu/ dataedge.ischool.berkeley.edu/], 2012
*ICDSE (International Conference on Data Science and Engineering), held by Department of Computer Science, Cochin University of Science and Technology, [http://icdse.cusat.ac.in icdse.cusat.ac.in], 2012
*Annual International Workshop on Dataology and Data Science, held by Research Center on Dataology and DataScience, Fudan University, China, [http://iwdds.fudan.edu.cn/ iwdds.fudan.edu.cn/], 2010, 2011, 2012
*Data scientist Summit, held by EMC Corporation, [http://www.greenplum.com/datasciencesummit/ www.greenplum.com/datasciencesummit/], 2011, 2012
*O’REILLY Strata Conference, held by O’REILLY, EMC, Microsoft, HPCC Systems, IBM, VMWare, Oracle, Cloudera, etc., [http://strataconf.com strataconf.com]
*IEEE International Conference on Big Data, [http://www.ischool.drexel.edu/bigdata/bigdata2013/index.htm]
* Data science workshops -[http://www.datacurry.in], [http://www.datacurry.com], 2013

==Further Reading==
* {{cite web |url=http://jsresearch.net/groups/teachdatascience/ |title=Introduction to Data science |author=Jeffrey M. Stanton |date=20 May 2012 |work= |publisher=Syracuse University School of Information Studies |accessdate=8 August 2012 }}
* {{cite web |url=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Data_Science:_An_Introduction |title=Data science: An Introduction |author=Calvin Andrus |year=2012 |work= |publisher=Wikibooks.org |accessdate=8 August 2012 }}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Anderson|first=Janna|title=The Future of The Internet|url=http://www.greenplum.com/sites/default/files/PIP_Future_of_Internet_2012_Big_Data.pdf|publisher=Pew Research Center|accessdate=7 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=West|first=Darrell|title=Big Data For Education: Data Mining, Data Analytics, and Web Dashboards|url=http://www.brookings.edu/~/media/research/files/papers/2012/9/04%20education%20technology%20west/04%20education%20technology%20west.pdf|publisher=The Brookings Institution|accessdate=7 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Davenport|first=Thomas|title=The Human Side of Big Data and High-Performance Analytics|url=http://www.greenplum.com/sites/default/files/Research_Human_Side_of_Big_Data_and_High_Performance_Analytics.pdf|publisher=International Institute for Analytics|accessdate=7 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hellerstein|first=Joseph|title=The MADlib Analytics Library or MAD Skills, the SQL|url=http://www.greenplum.com/sites/default/files/Madlib_Whitepaper.pdf|publisher=University of California at Berkeley|accessdate=7 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Drew Conway, John Myles White. "Machine Learning for Hackers". O’Reilly Media, Inc. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Stodder|first=David|title=Customer Analytics In the Age of Social Media|url=http://www.greenplum.com/sites/default/files/TDWI_BPReport_Q312_CAASM_EMCGreenplum.pdf|publisher=TDWI Research|accessdate=7 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Yangyong|first=Zhu|coauthors=Yun Xiong|title=Dataology and Data science：Up to Now|year=2011|month=June|url=ZHU Yangyong,Xiong Yun.Dataology and Data science：Up to Now[OL]. [16 June 2011] http://www.paper.edu.cn/en_releasepaper/content/4432156}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Jun (Luke) Huan,{{cite web |url= http://people.eecs.ku.edu/~jhuan/EECS940_S12|title= Theoretic Foundation of Data Science, EECS 940 |date=20 May 2012|accessdate=1 January 2012 }}, University of Kansas

==References==
{{Commons category|Data science}}
{{wikibooks}}
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Information science]]</text>
      <sha1>8gl3zfhlowm9z3nnr0ccs97g0hpdyy8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>