<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Dine and dash</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3220692</id>
    <revision>
      <id>559248715</id>
      <parentid>559248367</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-10T16:11:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Milesandkilometrestogo</username>
        <id>17368768</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Legal aspects */ cleanup</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{original research|date=August 2012}}
{{refimprove|date=August 2012}}
{{Globalize|date=April 2010}}
}}

A '''dine and dash''' (also referred to as "'''dine and ditch'''", "'''eat and run'''" or "'''beating the check'''") is a form of [[theft]] by [[fraud]], in which a patron orders and consumes food from a [[restaurant]] or similar establishment with no intent to pay, then leaves without paying.

== Legal aspects ==
Simply failing to pay a bill when due is generally not a crime in most circumstances or jurisdictions.  It is a contract debt, and the act is [[Civil law (common law)|civil]] rather than [[criminal law|criminal]] in nature.  However, there are often laws that apply specifically to restaurants, hotels, and other circumstances, where the presumption is that the customer never intended to pay their bill and therefore obtained the valuable services under false pretenses, a form of criminal fraud.

It is often the case that the establishment makes their employees pay the cost of customer theft to give them an incentive to police their customers.  They may do so explicitly by deducting unpaid meals from [[wage]]s or [[gratuity|tip]]s, or implicitly through an end-of-shift reconciliation system whereby the server is expected to provide enough cash and credit card receipts to cover the cost of their customers' meals, and keeps any surplus as tips.  Though theoretically illegal in some cases,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The costs of getting stiffed shouldn't be the server's to pay|first=Connie|last=Schultz|date=December 15, 2009|url=http://www.cleveland.com/schultz/index.ssf/2009/12/the_costs_of_getting_stiffed_s.html|publisher=Cleveland Live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Ontario Ministry of Labor|title=Payment of Wages|url=http://www.labour.gov.on.ca/english/es/pubs/guide/paywage.php|date=November, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.labour.gov.bc.ca/esb/igm/esa-part-3/igm-esa-s-21.htm|author=British Columbia Ministry of Labour and Citizens' Services|year=2005|title=Interpretation Guidelines Manual: British Columbia Employment Standards Act and Regulations}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.dol.gov/whd/regs/compliance/whdfs16.pdf|author=U.S. Department of Labor|year=2009|title=
Fact Sheet #16: Deductions From Wages for Uniforms and Other Facilities 
Under the Fair Labor Standards Act (FLSA)}} 
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Government of Alberta|title=Deductions that are not allowed |url=http://employment.alberta.ca/documents/Deductions-from-Earnings.pdf|date=September, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; the server is often held responsible for tabs that are not paid. It may be illegal, for example, for an establishment to require an employee to pay for an unpaid tab, but it is often a serious offense to have someone walk out on their check. The server must decide whether to pay the tab and keep his or her job, or not pay and risk losing it.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dine And Dash}}
[[Category:Theft]]
[[Category:Restaurant terminology]]
[[Category:Food law]]

{{Crime-stub}}

[[fr:Délit de grivèlerie]]
[[nl:Flessentrekkerij]]</text>
      <sha1>sd92zh86j5aqfjs0e1v5xyezc0w9p9i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>