<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>DMExpress</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4068618</id>
    <revision>
      <id>555948127</id>
      <parentid>555948091</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-20T14:03:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Talkietoaster-nc</username>
        <id>17016392</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''DMExpress''' is an [[Extract, transform, load|ETL]] and data integration tool designed primarily for performance.  It is a software product of Syncsort, Inc.  It runs on [[Windows]], [[UNIX]] and [[Linux]] systems and can transform and integrate data from multiple sources, including
* Database engines, including [[Oracle database|Oracle]], [[Sybase]], [[IBM DB2|DB2]], [[Informix]], [[Microsoft SQL Server]] [[Teradata]], [[Vertica]] and [[ODBC]] sources
* [[XML]]
* Various types of files, including delimited and fixed-record-length
* [[Mainframe computer|Mainframe]] data sets, including [[VSAM]] and [[COBOL]]
* The [[Hadoop]] Distributed File System ([[HDFS]])
It can also run natively as [[map-reduce]] processes on [[Hadoop]] clusters.

DMExpress processes data using proprietary algorithms instead of “pushing” transformation work to a database engine.  This can significantly reduce the workload on the database while improving overall throughput. DMExpress also runs on “commodity” hardware running [[Linux]] or [[Windows]] which is less expensive than specialized “database appliance” hardware.  Therefore, DMExpress is often able to reduce total cost by eliminating or postponing the need to upgrade or expand the database system.

Release 7.0 added support for reading and writing files on the [[Hadoop]] Distributed File System ([[HDFS]]).  The latest version is DMX-h, which contains [[Hadoop]]-specific extensions which allow DMExpress jobs to run natively as [[map-reduce]] processes.  This differentiates DMExpress from other ETL tools running on [[Hadoop]] because others generate Java or HiveQL code.  This allows DMExpress to out-perform other solutions on [[Hadoop]].

In additional to [[Extract, transform, load|ETL]]-type processing, since DMExpress is a general-purpose data transformation engine, it is also very effective for other purposes such as
* Delta processing ([[change data capture]])
* Data cleansing and validation
* Pivots and [[Database normalization|normalization]]
* Aggregation and analytics
* Website clickstream processing
* Database replication / migration / extraction
* Replacement of legacy sort and other data utility replacement
* Migration of [[mainframe computer|mainframe]] data to [[Windows]] / [[UNIX]] / [[Linux]]

It is also possible to use DMExpress to implement [[map-reduce]] functionality within [[Hadoop]] clusters, as an alternative to [[Java]], [[Pig]] or [[Hive]] coding, or in combination with those languages.  [[Map-reduce]] processes developed using DMExpress typically execute several times faster than equivalent [[Java]], [[Pig]] or [[Hive]] processes, and consume less CPU and memory.

According to the company, “Syncsort has historically been known as the ‘gold standard’ for sorting data on the mainframe and open systems. DMExpress is built on Syncsort’s high-performance sort engine to deliver the fastest, most efficient, and reliable [[Extract, transform, load|ETL]] engine.”
==Syncsort==
[[Syncsort]] is a global software company that helps the world’s most successful organizations rethink the economics of data. Syncsort provides record-setting data performance and rapid time to value through easy to use data integration and data protection solutions. With over 15,000 deployments, Syncsort has transformed decision making and delivered more profitable results to thousands of customers worldwide. For more information visit: www.syncsort.com

==References==
{{reflist}}
[http://www.syncsort.com/Solutions/DataIntegrationAcceleration.aspx Using DMExpress for Data Integration Accelleration]&lt;br /&gt;
[http://www.syncsort.com/en/Data-Integration/Solutions/Hadoop-Solutions/Hadoop-ETL Using DMExpress to Accellerate Hadoop]

{{database-software-stub}}

[[Category:ETL tools]]
[[Category:Hadoop]]</text>
      <sha1>leoxznoiormfekj4k3t96vdfjmhx4go</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>