<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>EMC Isilon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9073527</id>
    <revision>
      <id>546019785</id>
      <parentid>533065172</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-21T16:50:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Beland</username>
        <id>57939</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>downcase section titles</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company 
| company_name   = EMC - Isilon
| company_logo   = [[Image:isilon logo.jpg]]
| company_type   = [[Subsidiary]] 
| company_slogan = Simple is Smart
| foundation     = {{Start date|2001 }}
| location       = [[Seattle]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]], [[United States|U.S.]] 
| key_people     = Sujal Patel, [[President]] and [[CEO]]
| industry       = [[Data storage device]]s / [[Computer Storage]]
| homepage       = {{URL|http://www.isilon.com}}
}}

'''Isilon Systems''', a division of EMC, is headquartered in [[Seattle]] and sells clustered storage systems and software for digital content and other unstructured data, which includes but is not limited to video, audio, digital images, computer models, PDF files, scanned information, and test and simulation data. Isilon was acquired by [[EMC Corporation]] in November 2010.

Isilon's products are used to store and manage data filesets across various industries including Media &amp; Entertainment, Government, IC Design, Oil &amp; Gas, Manufacturing, Life Sciences, Internet/Web 2.0, and Content Delivery/Telco providers.&lt;ref&gt;Isilon Systems, Inc. [http://www.isilon.com/industries Industry Overview].&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, Isilon received venture capital funding from [[Sequoia Capital]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sequoiacap.com/company/isilon-systems/|title=Sequoia Capital funds Isilon}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Isilon's customers include NBC Universal,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/hotStocksNews/idUSN1640308120070416 |title=Isilon serves up digital storage for NBC Universal |publisher=Reuters |date=2007-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cedars-Sinai, Kelman Technologies, and Kodak, among others.&lt;ref&gt;Isilon Systems, Inc. [http://www.isilon.com/float/?page=resources Customer Case Studies].&lt;/ref&gt; Isilon's current tagline is "Simple is Smart".&lt;ref&gt;Isilon Systems, Inc.  [http://www.isilon.com/ Simple is Smart]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Business overview ==

Isilon designed and developed its clustered storage systems specifically to address the needs of storing, managing and accessing digital content and other unstructured data.&lt;ref name="Isilon Systems, Inc. Form 10-K"&gt;[http://media.corporate-ir.net/media_files/irol/20/203064/2006_10K.pdf Isilon Systems, Inc. Form 10-K.] (2007-03-15)&lt;/ref&gt; An Isilon clustered storage system is composed of three or more nodes.  Each node is a self-contained, rack-mountable device that contains industry standard hardware, including disk drives, CPU, memory chips and network interfaces, and is integrated with proprietary operating system software called [[OneFS]] (based on [[FreeBSD]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freebsdfoundation.org/press/2007Dec-newsletter.shtml#Isilon FreeBSD Foundation Newsletter], December 17, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;), which unifies a cluster of nodes into a single shared resource.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Apicella |first=Mario |url=http://www.infoworld.com/article/06/10/12/42OPstorinside_1.html |title=Clustered storage winks at the enterprise |publisher=InfoWorld |date=2006-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Isilon sells its products indirectly through a channel partner program that includes over 100 resellers and distributors, and directly through a field sales force.&lt;ref name="Isilon Systems, Inc. Form 10-K"/&gt;

== Financial troubles and executive changes ==

Sujal Patel, who founded Isilon in 2001 and served as its chief technology officer, returned to the company as CEO in the Fall of 2007.  This followed the resignation of Chief Executive Steve Goldman and Chief Financial Officer Stu Fuhlendorf. In the spring of 2008 Isilon reported questionable revenue recognition events to the SEC under the previous regime.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Raffo |first=Dave |url=http://storage.blogs.techtarget.com/2008/04/03/isilon-%E2%80%98fesses-up/ |title=Isilon 'fesses up' |publisher=SearchStorage |date=2008-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of earning reports submitted to the SEC from 2006 and 2007 were revised. Isilon introduced a new revenue recognition policy in order to remedy the previous issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Raffo |first=Dave |url=http://searchstorage.techtarget.com/news/article/0,289142,sid5_gci1308342,00.html |title=Isilon reveals turnaround plan |publisher=SearchStorage |date=2008-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Technology and architecture ==

Isilon clustered storage system architecture consists of independent nodes that are all integrated with the OneFS operating system software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Big data meets big storage: an in-depth look at Isilon's scale-out storage solution|url=http://arstechnica.com/business/raising-your-tech-iq/2011/05/isilon-overview.ars|publisher=Ars Technica|accessdate=28 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The systems can be installed in standard data center environments and are accessible to users and applications running Windows, Unix/Linux and Mac operating systems using industry standard file sharing protocols over standard Gigabit Ethernet.&lt;ref name="Isilon Systems, Inc. Form 10-K"/&gt; 

Nodes within the clustered storage system communicate with each other over a dedicated back-end network which is either [[Infiniband]] or standard Gigabit Ethernet.&lt;ref name="Isilon Systems, Inc. Form 10-K"/&gt; The architecture is designed so that each node has full visibility and write/read access to or from a single expandable file system.

The core technology of the Isilon clustered storage consists of [[OneFS]], which provides a single unified operating system and delivers up to 10 GB/s of throughput.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Asaro |first=Tony |url=http://www.isilon.com/pdfs/analyst/ESG_Brief_Isilon_45_Oct_2006.pdf |title=Isilon Raising the Bar (again) |publisher=Enterprise Strategy Group |year=2006 |month=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[OneFS]] operating system software is designed with file-striping functionality across each node in a cluster, a fully distributed lock manager, caching, fully distributed meta-data, and a remote block manager to maintain global coherency and synchronization across the cluster.&lt;ref&gt;Isilon Systems, Inc.  [http://www.isilon.com/pdfs/white_papers/Clustered_Storage_Revolution.pdf “Clustered Storage Revolution”], White Paper. (2006-09)&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2007, Isilon announced the release of the IQ 9000 and EX 9000 clustered storage products, claiming scalability of up to 1.6 petabytes of capacity in a single file system and single volume.&lt;ref&gt;Isilon Systems, Inc. [http://www.isilon.com/news/?sub=press&amp;page=press&amp;release=139 “Isilon Releases New Clustered Storage Systems, Delivering Unprecedented Scale, Performance And Value”]. Press Release. (2007-7-23)&lt;/ref&gt; New products were launched in September 2008, raising stated capacity to 2.3 PB&lt;ref&gt;http://www.isilon.com/company/?sub=press&amp;page=press&amp;release=187&lt;/ref&gt; and in March 2009, raising stated capacity to 3.4 PB.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.isilon.com/company/?sub=press&amp;page=press&amp;release=202&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2011, they raised the stated capacity to 15 PB.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.isilon.com/press-release/emc-isilon-delivers-worlds-largest-single-file-system-big-data&lt;/ref&gt;

== Acquisition by EMC ==

On November 15, 2010, it was announced that [[EMC Corporation|EMC]] would acquire Isilon for $2.25 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2010/11/15/emc-to-buy-storage-firm-isilon-for-2-25-billion/ |title=EMC to Buy Isilon Systems for $2.25 Billion |publisher=New York Times |date=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; EMC said that with its acquisition of Isilon, it would be better able to provide storage infrastructure for private and public cloud environments, with a focus on so-called [[big data]], like [[gene sequencing]], [[online streaming]], and oil and natural gas seismic studies.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.isilon.com}}

{{EMC}}
{{Coord|47.597431|-122.334395|display=t}}

[[Category:Companies based in Seattle, Washington]]
[[Category:Computer storage companies]]
[[Category:Storage Area Network companies]]</text>
      <sha1>b0v5idkl8ncw9xuuk631st1a3sol0av</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>