<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Enron Corpus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31087679</id>
    <revision>
      <id>559245848</id>
      <parentid>556576893</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-10T15:50:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nosql.analyst</username>
        <id>18823614</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ Added link to tutorial using the Corpus</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The '''Enron Corpus''' is a large database of over 600,000 emails generated by 158 employees&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper | last1 = Klimt | first = Bryan  | author2 = Yiming Yang | id = {{citeseerx|10.1.1.61.1645}} | title = The Enron Corpus: A New Dataset for Email Classification Research }}&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[Enron Corporation]] and acquired by the [[Federal Energy Regulatory Commission]] during its investigation after the company's collapse.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://sgi.nu/enron/ The Enron Email Corpus]" Retrieved March 5, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  A copy of the database was subsequently purchased for $10,000 by [[Andrew McCallum]], a computer scientist at the [[University of Massachusetts Amherst]].&lt;ref name="nyt"&gt;Markoff, John. "[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/05/science/05legal.html?hp Armies of Expensive Lawyers, Replaced by Cheaper Software]".  ''New York Times'' March 5, 2011. p A1.&lt;/ref&gt;  He released this copy to researchers, providing a trove of data that has been used for studies on social networking and computer analysis of language.  The corpus is "unique" in that it is one of the only publicly available mass collections of "real" emails easily available for study, as such collections are typically bound by numerous privacy and legal restrictions which render them prohibitively difficult to access.&lt;ref name="nyt"/&gt;
In 2010, [[EDRM]] published a revised version 2 of the corpus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Socha|first=George|title=EDRM Enron Email Data Set v2 Now Available|url=http://www.edrm.net/archives/6462|publisher=www.edrm.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This expanded corpus, containing over 1.7 million messages, is now available on [[Amazon S3]] for easy access to the research community.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://sgi.nu/enron/ Enron Corpus website]
*[http://info.nuix.com/Enron.html Nuix provides the data set cleansed of PII] (requires registration)
*[http://foundationdb.com/documentation/beta2/enron.html Tutorial on data modeling with the Enron Corpus]

[[Category:Enron]]
[[Category:Corpora]]</text>
      <sha1>k0gsnhyil3p00dzohjm2b0r9djntips</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>