<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Faceted search</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10715937</id>
    <revision>
      <id>549097972</id>
      <parentid>541474793</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-07T03:50:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>68.71.155.72</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Changed the wikilink from "taxonomy" which specifically is about biological taxonomy, and instead linked "general" taxonomy, which better fits the subject.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Faceted search''', also called '''faceted navigation''' or '''faceted browsing''', is a technique for accessing information organized according to a [[faceted classification]] system, allowing users to explore a collection of information by applying multiple filters. A faceted classification system classifies each information element along multiple explicit dimensions, enabling the classifications to be accessed and ordered in multiple ways rather than in a single, pre-determined, [[taxonomy_(general)|taxonomic]] order.&lt;ref name="Faceted Search"&gt;[http://www.morganclaypool.com/doi/abs/10.2200/S00190ED1V01Y200904ICR005 Faceted Search], Morgan &amp; Claypool, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Facets correspond to properties of the information elements.&lt;ref name="Basics of Faceted Search"&gt;[http://www.lucidimagination.com/Community/Hear-from-the-Experts/Articles/Faceted-Search-Solr Basics of Faceted Search]&lt;/ref&gt; They are often derived by analysis of the text of an item using [[entity extraction]] techniques or from pre-existing fields in a database such as author, descriptor, language, and format. Thus, existing web-pages, product descriptions or online collections of articles can be augmented with navigational facets.

==Development==

The [[Association for Computing Machinery]]'s [[Special Interest Group on Information Retrieval]] provided the following description of the role of faceted search for a 2006 workshop:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The web search world, since its very beginning, has offered two paradigms:
*Navigational search uses a hierarchy structure (taxonomy) to enable users to browse the information space by iteratively narrowing the scope of their quest in a predetermined order, as exemplified by [[Yahoo! Directory]], [[Open Directory Project|DMOZ]], etc.
*Direct search allows users to simply write their queries as a bag of words in a text box. This approach has been made enormously popular by [[Web search engine]]s. 
Over the last few years, the direct search paradigm has gained dominance and the navigational approach became less and less popular. Recently, a new approach has emerged, combining both paradigms, namely the faceted search approach. Faceted search enables users to navigate a multi-dimensional information space by combining text search with a progressive narrowing of choices in each dimension. It has become the prevailing user interaction mechanism in e-commerce sites and is being extended to deal with [[semi-structured data]], continuous dimensions, and [[Folksonomy | folksonomies]].&lt;ref name="sigir06"&gt;[http://facetedsearch.googlepages.com SIGIR'2006 Workshop on Faceted Search - Call for Participation]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Projects==
Within the academic community, faceted search has attracted interest primarily among [[library and information science]] researchers, and to some extent among [[computer science]] researchers specializing in [[information retrieval]].

The most notable academic efforts in faceted search are the following:
* The [[CiteSeerX]] project&lt;ref&gt;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/&lt;/ref&gt; at the [[Pennsylvania State University]] allows faceted search for academic documents and continues to expand into other facets such as table search.
* [[Apache Solr]] Search engine platform based on [[Apache Lucene]].

==Mass market use==

Faceted search has become a popular technique in commercial search applications, particularly for online retailers and libraries. An increasing number of [[List of Enterprise Search Vendors|enterprise search vendors]] provide software for implementing faceted search applications.

==Online retail==

Online retail catalogs co-pioneered the earliest applications of faceted search, reflecting both the faceted nature of product data (most products have a type, brand, price, etc.) and the ready availability of the data in retailers' existing information-systems. In the early 2000s retailers started using faceted search, leading to its ubiquity {{as of | 2012 | lc = on}} in their online storefronts.&lt;ref name="Internet Retailer: Most new e-commerce platforms designed with ‘faceted’ search, Venda says (2007)"&gt;[http://www.internetretailer.com/2007/05/16/most-new-e-commerce-platforms-designed-with-faceted-search Internet Retailer: Most new e-commerce platforms designed with ‘faceted’ search, Venda says (2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Libraries==

Although the noted librarian [[S. R. Ranganathan|Ranganathan]] was a strong proponent of a [[faceted classification]] system for library materials, he did not succeed in replacing the pre-coordinated [[Dewey Decimal Classification]] system with his faceted [[colon classification]] scheme.&lt;ref name="Major classification systems : the Dewey Centennial"&gt;[http://archive.org/details/majorclassificat00alle Major classification systems : the Dewey Centennial]&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, online library catalogs, also known as [[OPAC]]s, have increasingly adopted faceted search interfaces. Noted examples include the [[North Carolina State University]] library catalog (part of the Triangle Research Libraries Network) and the [[Online Computer Library Center|OCLC]] Open [[WorldCat]] system.

==See also==
* [[Exploratory search]]
* [[Faceted classification]]
* [[Human–computer information retrieval]]
* [[NoSQL]]
* [[Information Extraction]]
* [[Enterprise Search]]

==References==
&lt;References/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Faceted Search}}
[[Category:Information retrieval]]</text>
      <sha1>cdyis70lwudcosm5bbwil38k2ymop7e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>