<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Future Technology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31161038</id>
    <revision>
      <id>563102642</id>
      <parentid>563100162</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-06T12:33:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Fact}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{Underlinked|date=June 2013}}
{{Orphan|date=June 2013}}
}}

'''Future technology''' is beyond the reality of science and technology. Future technology is completely and essentially different with high-tech, the latest [[technology]] and cutting-edge technology. The latter represents just an advanced human invention created and been able to master and use recently. Future technology emphasizes human expectations or unforeseen things, which have not yet been invented or used. Only in a certain period, human beings maybe master and use future technology.Where is the development of future technology? How will the future technology exist? We look at several aspects to think about the future development of technology. Of course, this is inseparable from our current life.

==Screen world==
The ubiquitous screen will profoundly change the people, culture and business{{fact|date=July 2013}}. The impact of screen media and interactive window has not been released. We can imagine that the touch screen will play a much more important role in our life. The touch screen can bring us perfect communications with the real world. With the development of the science and technology, it will make a great convenience in our daily life. We can use a multifunctional screen device to deal with our daily schedule. It can tell us the weather and give us an advice about the dress when we get up a new day. We can use the device to control our washing machine, to prepare a healthy breakfast. After breakfast, we sit in our cars and tell the vehicle systems our destination, then the car will take us there itself. During our work we will have a TV meeting with classmates in some other places. What surround us are many high-tech devices with a touch screen. It makes a great improve in our work efficiency. After the work, we can choose to play a virtual game. The touch screen will give us a real experience and we can control the game role with our whole body. As the touch screen can take a great communication with our idea, we will surround by many more screen. The huge influence will bring us a much more convenient life.

==Further natural interaction==
Touch, voice, somatosensory is still the preliminary stage of human-computer interaction. There will be many surprising applications waiting for us, such as when you look at the screen the screen is in fact can see you, know your status, and constantly optimize learning, providing more in line with your service. Technology evolved as a living entity is in duty bound to weaken the ability of human rejection. We know the computer will be more and more intelligent, and the intelligence will be reflected in the human-computer interaction. Beyond our reality, future interaction will be much more actual and useful. The machine can give us 3-D virtual scene simulating the real surroundings, and then we can take what we need.For example, we will not need to spend much time in choosing the clothes. An interactive machine can give us a 3-D virtual scene, where we can choose various clothes. Future interaction will have much more emotion and intelligence.

==Big data stream==
In the future, people will leave in a communicative society. We can get what we want from the social net. We like to share with the whole world, and then endless data between people, things and things will "float" around us. Their integration and convergence will change our living conditions. The share tide and future interaction will bring us a large date to process. The information society will process more and more data, and we need efficient instruments to deal with the big data. What will the big data bring us? Big data represents our past. It records what we have experienced. If we deal with the big date effectively, we will solve many potential problems. Through integrating and analyzing the big date, we can make new value.

==Access rather than ownership==
The concept of possession has changed. We will not need to buy any book, any music and any general device. Digitization prefers access right to the concept of ownership. In the future, the service will be concentrate. Many people will not have to possess almost everything. We use a portable device to get music, videos, books and many others from the Internet. As for the users, it cost much less money and take us little time to get what we want. So it is very convenient.

==Value shift==
We will not get the harvest value by mass copy and selling copies. Value will not exist in copies themselves, but rather the satisfaction of customer value. Such as cellphones do not need money, but date flow gets money. The value is not to create value in kind, but rather to create a "communication" user value. We will not have to pay for the electric charge, net cost, and device outlay apart. We use everything, and we pay for the service once. We will not need so many facilitators, and the service become simple. The value exists in our satisfaction.

==References==

http://www.vrp3d.com/article/overseasnews/867.html

http://itechfuture.com/

http://itechfuture.com/category/technology/

http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20130102-tomorrows-world

http://itechfuture.com/category/technology-devices/

http://www.askci.com/news/201302/04/0415171359431.shtml



[[Category:Technology]]
[[Category:Futurology]]</text>
      <sha1>iinhrcun4cs25ngvprtv3elq71uc8od</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>