<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>GEICO advertising campaigns</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21396796</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562781257</id>
      <parentid>562493750</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-04T03:33:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.72.27.231</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{copy edit|date=October 2012}}
{| style="width: 80%; margin: 0 0 0 10%; border-collapse: collapse; background: #FBFBFB; border: 1px solid #aaa; border-left: 10px solid #f28500;"
|-
| style="padding: 0.25em 0.5em;" | '''This article or section reads like an [[Wikipedia:What Wikipedia is not#Wikipedia is not a soapbox|advertisement]].'''&lt;br/&gt;To meet Wikipedia's [[:Category:Wikipedia style guidelines|quality standards]] and comply with Wikipedia's [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view|neutral point of view]] policy, it may require [[Wikipedia:Cleanup|cleanup]]. ''(May 2013)''
|}

'''[[GEICO]] advertising campaigns''' are known for using humour and satire, often featuring distinctive characters such as the company's mascot, the GEICO gecko.&lt;ref&gt;[http://adage.com/article/cmo-interviews/big-data-spawned-geico-gecko/240398/ How Big Data Spawned the Geico Gecko] Retrieved 6 Apr 2013&lt;/ref&gt; The advertising strategy incorporates a [[Market saturation|saturation]]-level amount of print (primarily mail circulars) and [[Television advertisement|television]] [[parody advertisement]]s, as well as radio advertisements. A common tagline used by GEICO is "15 minutes could save you 15% or more on [[Vehicle insurance|car insurance]]."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.the-dma.org/moty/mostrecenthonorees.html&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Warren Buffett]], owner of GEICO parent [[Berkshire Hathaway]], has stated that he would spend $2&amp;nbsp;billion on GEICO ads if he could,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted by Ben |url=http://inoculatedinvestor.blogspot.com/2009/05/2009-berkshire-hathway-annual-meeting.html |title=The Inoculated Investor: 2009 Berkshire Hathaway Annual Meeting Notes |publisher=Inoculatedinvestor.blogspot.com |date=2009-05-05 |accessdate=2010-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; far exceeding the $994 million spent in 2011. Approximately 6.5% of the company's premiums are spent on advertising.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.insurancejournal.com/news/national/2012/06/26/252905.htm |title=Geico Spends 6.5% of Premiums on Advertising |publisher=Insurancejournal.com |date=2012-06-26 |accessdate=2013-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the most prominent TV ad campaigns, such as the GEICO Gecko, the GEICO Cavemen, and the Rhetorical Questions campaign featuring [[Mike McGlone]] were developed by [[The Martin Agency]].

==Animated advertisements==
Animated advertisements were part of the early GEICO Direct ads as well as the "Dumb Things" campaign. The 15-second long commercials, animated by [[Bill Plympton]], featured a curious little man walking up to an object and eventually getting hurt due to his curiosity of the object.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KWD6EhA1pmY&lt;/ref&gt; One of the commercials, for example, involved him finding a cannon and pressing a button, causing a resulting cannonball to fire out and stick to his face. The original saying in the commercial was "You could still save money on [[Vehicle insurance|car insurance]]. Even if you made a few mistakes."; later modified to "We all do dumb things. Paying too much for car insurance doesn't have to be one of them."&lt;ref&gt;GEICO commercial (1994) http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Uq7y3ecRxn4 Retrieved 6 Apr 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

==Individual advertisements==
GEICO has presented a number of memorable one shot ads. Amongst these are:

* A white duck says, "Am I on? (clears throat) GEICO Direct could save you hundreds of money on car insurance. Result..." (The duck then removes his beak, revealing a smaller one. He continues, in a high-pitched voice) "...Smaller bill."
* A man, whose insurance company didn't offer a loaner vehicle, left his house while covered in [[magnet]]s and "bummed a ride" by attaching himself to a passing car.
* A man's dog wears a [[fire proximity suit]] as he delivers a competing insurance company's bill because it is "too hot to handle".
* As an example of other companies' poor customer service, a man in a [[diner]] tells a waitress he didn't order [[mayonnaise|mayo]] on his sandwich, at which point she scrapes it off onto the side of the table.
* To showcase GEICO's 24-hour customer service, GEICO employees are shown wearing beer helmets with cups of [[coffee]] attached to them instead of [[beer]], followed by a comparison shot of a regular insurance company's small coffee mug and GEICO's big coffee mug.
* A police unit tracks the source of an apparent earthquake, only to find an obese man joyously jumping up and down over the money that GEICO saved him.
* A man employs a team of bloodhounds to find his Acme Insurance agent after hours but finds only a terrified janitor in the building.
* A man looks at his most recent auto insurance bill with his dog at his side; the dog, finding out his owner spent far too much money rolls on the floor laughing.
* A man places a long-distance collect phone call through an operator, claiming to be named Bob Wehadababyitsaboy to get his message across without having the call's recipient billed. This commercial ran for a few weeks with the name joke and the pitch for GEICO, followed by a parting shot of the man on the telephone further exploiting his name trick, saying "Last name is Wehadababyitsaboyandweighs8pounds3ouncesandisdoingfine". The commercial was later re-edited to remove the ending joke and add "Don't cheat the telephone company, save money the legal way with GEICO" in its place.
* A squirrel causes a car to swerve and crash off-screen.  Having survived, the squirrel performs a celebratory series of [[fist bump]]s and [[high five]]s with another squirrel.
* The camera tilts up to a night sky to show a constellation of a car, the windshield of which is hit by a comet.
* On his way to participate in spokesperson auditions, the gecko runs into the [[Taco Bell chihuahua]] which says "Oh great, a talking gecko."
* While an ACME worker is at her desk, a man is seen going back and forth before falling through a trapdoor.

== The GEICO Gecko ==
{{anchor|The GEICO gecko}}
The company's ads sometimes focus on its reptilian [[mascot]], The Gecko, an [[Anthropomorphism|anthropomorphic]] [[Phelsuma|Day Gecko]] created by [[The Martin Agency]], later modified to a [[Computer-generated image|CGI]] creature by [[Framestore CFC]]. The gecko first appeared in 1999 during the [[Screen Actors Guild]] [[Strike action|strike]] that prevented the use of live actors.&lt;ref name=geico_x&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/money/advertising/adtrack/2006-07-16-geico_x.htm Gecko wasn't first choice for GEICO.] USA Today, July 16, 2006. Retrieved February 16, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The original commercial features the Gecko, voiced by actor [[Kelsey Grammer]], pleading for people to stop calling him in error as he is a ''gecko'' not to be confused with ''GEICO.'' Later "wrong number" ads used [[Dave Kelly (broadcaster)|Dave Kelly]] as the voice of the gecko. In the subsequent commercials with [[Jake Wood]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tvacres.com/adanimals_geicogecko.htm|title=Advertising &gt; Animal Mascots &gt; Geico Gecko (GEICO Insurance)|publisher=tvacres.com|accessdate=2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; (which portray him as a representative of the company), the gecko speaks with a British [[Cockney]] [[Accent (sociolinguistics)|accent]], because it would be unexpected, according to Martin Agency's Steve Bassett. In 2010s commercials the gecko's accent is more working-class, perhaps in an effort to further "humanize" him.&lt;ref&gt;Weir, William (2006-02-21). [http://articles.courant.com/2006-02-21/features/0602210815_1_geico-gecko-british-accent-new-accent "Little Lizard Says 'Ello To A New Inflection"], ''[[The Hartford Courant]]'', Retrieved 2012-02-11.&lt;/ref&gt; "As [[computer animation]] got better and as we got to know the character better, we did a few things," says Steve Bassett, creative director at The Martin Agency. "We wanted to make him a little more guy-next-door. And he looks a lot more real than he's looked before."&lt;ref name=geico_x/&gt;

==Maxwell the Pig==
Maxwell is an anthropomorphic talking pig and something of a recurring character in a few Geico advertisements.  Maxwell debuted in an installment of the Rhetorical Questions campaign as the "little piggy who cried 'wee wee' all the way home" (referencing the famous nursery rhyme "[[This Little Piggy]]") being driven home by a friend's mother, squealing along the way.  While Maxwell was originally intended as a one-time character, the popularity of his debut commercial resulted in his appearance in a few other advertisements, including a radio commercial. [[piggy bank|Coin banks]] manufactured in his likeness were even available at one point.  However, he has not acquired as much of an iconic status as the Geico gecko himself.

At the end of 2011, Maxwell the Pig returned to advertise the new GEICO app.

==GEICO Cavemen==
{{Main|GEICO Cavemen}}

A popular series of well-received advertisements uses cavemen as pitchmen. Also developed by the Martin Agency, the ads center on [[Neanderthal]]-like [[caveman|cavemen]], no different from modern-day individuals (outside of the somewhat pre-historic facial features), encountering either an ad or commercial with the tagline "GEICO: so easy a caveman could do it," followed by their disgust with the supposed stereotype of caveman stupidity. The ads posit a world where cavemen are still alive and active members of society in the present day, behaving and living nothing at all like the stereotypical caveman. The main characters presented in the ads are affluent, educated, and cultured, eating at fancy restaurants, going to exclusive parties, and seeing their therapists (portrayed in the commercials by two-time [[Academy Award|Oscar]]-nominated actress [[Talia Shire]]). The humor revolves around the relative normality of the cavemen's presence and their reactions to the stereotype represented in the ads, and their attempts at defending themselves from the stereotype.

The ads were so successful that the commercial actors are appearing in a successful series of interactive websites written and produced by GEICO's in-house creative team at Caveman's Crib and most recently, [http://www.iheartcavemen.com iHeartcavemen]. A spin off TV series, titled ''[[Cavemen (TV series)|Cavemen]]'' and starring new actors, debuted on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] in October 2007&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117960384.html?categoryid=1300&amp;cs=1 | work=Variety | title=ABC developing 'Cavemen' | first=Michael | last=Schneider | date=2007-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- For sources, see separate article: [[GEICO Cavemen]] --&gt; &lt;!-- Why not include at least some sources here? That seems reasonable. --&gt; to overwhelmingly negative critical reaction. It was canceled after only six episodes were aired.

==Parodies==
Another common theme is misdirection, in which the commercial appears to be about an unrelated product (or, in fact, may not even be a commercial), suddenly changing to become a plug for GEICO. The commercials use a variety of fictional characters such as [[Speed Racer]], [[Mrs. Butterworth]], [[Jed Clampett]], and Bill Dutchess as well as real people such as [[Verne Troyer]], [[Tony Little]], [[Little Richard]], [[Joan Rivers]], [[Peter Frampton]], [[Don LaFontaine]], [[The Pips]], and [[James Lipton]] spoofing themselves. Other commercials relate to a hair loss doctor who has saved by switching to GEICO, a nature show about a fish, and a soap opera of a couple who are breaking up. Another set of GEICO ads involved a fictional reality show called "Tiny House" in which contestants were forced to live in a half-scale house.

An additional commercial theme is the promotion of fictional products. In 2006 parody ads featured such products as long distance phone service, tomato soda, fast-food, a reality TV show, dolls, and even poking fun at the [[Old Navy]] commercials - in all cases, the parody portion of the ad ends with "but it won't save you any money on car insurance." After the GEICO slogan is heard, the commercials end with "Why haven't you called GEICO?"

The parody pitch crossed over to the Caveman campaign in 2007, in a 10-second spot that appears to be a talking heads news interview, but features the popular caveman.

In response to some of the parody ads, [[Seth Green]] and [[Matthew Senreich]] wrote a sketch using the character [[Jar Jar Binks]] in a parody of one of the celebrity ads for their second ''[[Robot Chicken]]'' ''[[Star Wars]]'' special.

''[[MADtv]]'' also made a sketch parodying these ads using characters of [[Elmo (Sesame Street)|Elmo]] (who was performed by [[Frank Caeti]]) and [[Carlos Mencia]] (who was played by [[Johnny A. Sanchez|Johnny Sanchez]]).

==="I've got good news"===
In another ad campaign, a character would be breaking bad news to another (such as a [[baseball]] manager replacing a struggling pitcher with a reliever), but then offers helpfully, "I've got good news: I just saved a bunch of money on my car insurance by switching to GEICO!" That news, of course, is of no immediate use at all to the other character(s). Some of the ads were parodies and/or featured celebrities including, for example, [[Esteban]]; one featured the popular [[anime]] character [[Speed Racer]]. The exchange became parodied for a time while the ads were popular. One of the most watched "I've got good news" spots was a [[soap opera]] parody featuring television actor Sebastian Siegel.

===Bland salesman===
In another series of ads, a GEICO pitchman is played by actor [[Jerry Lambert (actor)|Jerry Lambert]] in an extremely bland and understated way, parodying the stereotype of an insurance man, such as reading to a group of uninterested children from a book of fairy tales about insurance. In one segment, he reads a supposed e-mail from a viewer saying it would be "da bomb" (''i.e.'', something good), if the Gecko would do a dance called "[[Robot (dance)|The Robot]]". Cut to the Gecko doing that dance smoothly and gracefully (to the tune of a not-for-public-sale melody called "Sweet World" by a group called Omega Men,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.auto-insurance-helper.com/geico-gecko-doing-the-robot-2.html|title=Geico Gecko Doing the Robot|publisher=Auto Insurance helper|accessdate=2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was used in the arcade video game ''[[In the Groove 2]]'') and then back to the insurance salesman attempting to do the same dance, seemingly more stiffly than an actual robot would. The newest commercial featuring the GEICO gecko depicts the Gecko receiving a business suit from the salesman, in order to present a more professional appearance, but he declines.

==Blueprint commercials==

GEICO also has several only blue-and-white ads, coined as "blueprint commercials", that focus on getting the point across that GEICO is "saving people money on more than just car insurance" (such as motorcycle, RV, boat, etc.), accompanied by the song "Gimme What I Want" by DCP Productions.

==My Great Rides==
In 2007, GEICO also launched a social networking site, [http://www.mygreatrides.com My Great Rides], for motorcycle owners. My Great Rides is a place for cycle owners to share stories about trips they have taken on their bikes, as well as post pictures of their motorcycles, and comment on other members' stories and pictures.

==GEICO Racing==
The number 7 car of the [[NASCAR]] [[Nationwide Series]] is driven by [[Mike Wallace (NASCAR)|Mike Wallace]] and was sponsored by GEICO prior to 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autoevolution.com/sport/nationwide-series/drivers/mike-wallace.html|title=Mike Wallace - NASCAR - Nationwide Series drivers|publisher=autoevolution|accessdate=2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.scenedaily.com/news/articles/nationwideseries/GEICO_leaves_Mike_Wallace_scrambling_to_find_sponsor_for_2009_season.html|title=Mike Wallace scrambling to find sponsor for 2009 Nationwide season|last=Montgomery|first=Lee|work=scenedaily.com|date=2008-12-01|accessdate=2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Commercials involving the race team are of a memorably disdainful young boy, played by actor Eddie Heffernan claiming to be a relative of Mike Wallace and being a better driver.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://autoracingsport.com/lauren-wallace-im-a-hundred-miles-away-son-ready-to-strike/|title=Lauren Wallace: 'I’m a hundred miles away, son, ready to strike'|work=NASCAR News|date=2008-05-01|accessdate=2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The boy says, "When people see [[Mike Wallace (NASCAR)|Mike Wallace]] and the GEICO number 7 doing well, they'll think of saving a bunch of money on car insurance. But when they see me, they'll say, 'There goes Lauren Wallace; the greatest thing to ever climb into a race car.'"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carinsurance357.com/2008/02/geico-has-best-car-insurance-ads-in.html|title=Geico Has the Best Car Insurance Ads in the Industry Bar None|publisher=Car Insurance 357|date=2008-02-25|accessdate=2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The commercials are sometimes presented in an interview fashion, where an unseen narrator speaks to the ambitious [[go-kart]] driver.  "What do you think of Mike Wallace?" the child is asked, to which he responds, "Whatever, he's out there selling car insurance, I'm out there to win."  When questioned on his relation to the [[NASCAR]] driver, Lauren shakes his head and concludes, "I didn't say I wouldn't go [[fishing]] with the man, all I'm saying is if he comes near me, I'll put him in the wall." To which the narrator questions him, "You don't race in the [[Busch Series]]."  Lauren replies "Listen, [[go-kart]] track, [[grocery store]], those remote controlled boats; when it comes to [[Mike Wallace (NASCAR)|Mike Wallace]] the story ends with me putting him in the wall."

New ads in this lineup include Lauren referring to himself as being, "100 miles away and ready to strike," and "lightning in a bottle."

The success of those ads resulted in the launch of an interactive website written and produced by GEICO's in-house creative team at [http://www.geicogarage.com GEICO Garage]. The site includes cameo appearances by Lauren Wallace and drivers Mike Wallace, his daughter Chrissy Wallace, Speed TV's Tommy Kendall, Paul Tracy, Christian Fittipaldi and Max Papis.

==15 Minutes Online==
Reminiscent of the old "Stupid Things" commercials, these show videos of people doing stupid things, such as running in hallways with pillows, done [[YouTube]] style. YouTube celebrity [[Brandon Hardesty]] also appeared in one such commercial, which included a clip from one of his famous ''Strange Faces'' videos.

==TRS: The Real Scoop==
Introduced in September, 2007, this series of ads features an ''[[E! True Hollywood Story]]''-type show about famed fictional characters such as [[Fred Flintstone]], [[Jed Clampett]], and even a [[Cabbage Patch Kids|Cabbage Patch Kid]] named Ben Winkler claiming to have their cars (the Flintmobile, Jed's 1923 [[Oldsmobile]] truck, and a [[Plymouth Reliant]], respectively) insured by GEICO, featuring interviews with made-up investigators (however, the Ben Winkler spot does not have an interview). These commercials were voiced over by narrator David O'Brien.

==The money you could be saving==
In 2008, GEICO began airing a series of television ads featuring "the money you could be saving", in the form of two paper-banded stacks of U.S. banknotes with a pair of [[Googly eyes]] on top. In some commercials, someone discovers this character sitting nearby, and in others it simply stares at the camera while a voice-over talks about how it wants you to save money. These ads includes a remix&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.geico.com/about/commercials/music/ "The Remake of 'Somebody's Watching Me{{'"}}], geico.com&lt;/ref&gt; by Mysto &amp; Pizzi of the 1980s song "[[Somebody's Watching Me]]". During the Halloween 2009 season, GEICO tied in with [[HBO]]'s ''[[True Blood]]'' series on bus bench ads and dressed up Kash in fang dentures.

==Talking inanimate objects==
In 2009, GEICO began a series of commercials featuring talking inanimate objects doing damage to cars. So far, they have used a talking tree [[branch|limb]] falling on a windshield and breaking it. The tree limb makes fun of the car right before a smaller limb falls on the hood.

The next one is a talking [[pothole]] with a thick [[southern belle]] accent causing a flat tire. The pothole somewhat apologizes then says she'll get her cell phone out and call a wrecker before realizing that she doesn't have one because she's a pothole.

==Rhetorical Questions Campaign==
{{cleanup|section|date=June 2010}}
Toward the end of 2009, [[GEICO]] introduced another advertising campaign in which [[Mike McGlone]] walks into an empty room and queries the viewer, "Could switching to GEICO really save you 15% or more on [[Vehicle insurance|car insurance]]?" After this, he pauses and then asks a rhetorical and/or obvious question which is immediately followed by a scene cut to the subject at hand.

Such questions have included (in no particular order):

===Television ads===
* "Is [[Ed Jones (American football)|Ed "Too Tall" Jones]] too tall?" (Cuts to Jones in a doctor's office being measured for his height, even though he is too tall for the maximum length of the measure. The nurse then says, "I'm just gonna guesstimate.")&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/user/GEICO#p/search/5/vEw87yeExZQ |title=Too Tall |publisher=YouTube |date=2005-12-06 |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* "Does [[Charlie Daniels]] play a mean fiddle?" (Cuts to Daniels energetically playing a fiddle in a classy restaurant after taking it from a violinist. Once he finishes, he hands it back and states "That's how you do it, son".)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/user/GEICO#p/search/0/1aZLw_KBdqc |title=Charlie Daniels |publisher=YouTube |date=2005-12-06 |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* "Does [[Elmer Fudd]] have trouble with the letter R?" (Cuts to Elmer hunting and telling the audience to be "vewy quiet" while he's "hunting wabbits", the director correcting his [[rhotacism]] to the former's frustration, and eventually stalking off the screen while muttering about how "this diwector is starting to wub me the wong way".)
* "Did [[The Waltons]] take ''way'' too long to say good night?" (Cuts to the Walton family saying "good night" to each other numerous times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.brandweek.com/bw/content_display/news-and-features/direct/e3i5b1f69da4015d79c5ef9248f92c76983|title=Geico Poses 'Rhetorical Questions'|last=Malykhina|first=Elena|work=Brand Week|date=2009-12-28|accessdate=2010-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www2.timesdispatch.com/rtd/business/local/article/MART24_20091223-222005/313354/|title=Martin Agency rolling out new ads for GEICO|last=Llovio|first=Louis|work=[[Richmond Times-Dispatch]]|date=2009-12-24|accessdate=2010-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
* "Does a ten pound bag of flour make a really big biscuit?" (Cuts to a child buttering an enormous biscuit on the kitchen counter humming as his mom walks in with a dismayed look upon her face.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/user/GEICO#p/search/0/jrMfDaLlNkA |title=Biscuit |publisher=YouTube |date=2005-12-06 |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* "Did the caveman [[Control of fire by early humans|invent fire]]?" (Cuts to the GEICO caveman sitting in a living room on a couch with a female companion. He looks disdainfully at the camera, then activates the fireplace by remote control before scowling at the camera once more.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/user/GEICO#p/search/0/FjqkH-rekiQ |title=Fire |publisher=YouTube |date=2005-12-06 |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* "Was [[Abraham Lincoln|Abe Lincoln]] honest?" (Cuts to an old-style black and white film of [[Mary Todd Lincoln]] asking "Does this dress make my backside look big?" After a lengthy pause and deliberation, Lincoln sheepishly responds, saying "Perhaps a...", interrupted as she gets up and walks out perturbed.)
* "Is having a snowball fight with pitching great [[Randy Johnson]] a bad idea?" (Cuts to Johnson helping a man to his feet, the latter with a hole in the arm of his jacket, in a snowy street. After lamenting the heavily damaged [[garage door]] behind them, they agree to go sledding instead.)
* "Is a bird in the hand worth two in the bush?" (Cuts to an [[Antiques Roadshow#United States|Antiques Roadshow]] appraiser examining a small statue of a human hand holding a bird. He tells the statue's owner that it is indeed worth at least two in the bush.)
* "Can [[fútbol]] announcer [[Andrés Cantor]] make any sport exciting?" (Cuts to Cantor loudly and energetically calling a slow-paced [[chess]] match, yelling his trademark "¡GOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOL!".)
* "Does a former drill sergeant make a terrible therapist?" (Cuts to [[R. Lee Ermey]] talking to a man on a psychiatrist's couch, then abruptly yelling at him for crying and then throws a box of tissues at him, calling him a crybaby.)
* "Do [[How much wood would a woodchuck chuck|woodchucks chuck wood]]?"  (Cuts to a jovial pair of woodchucks throwing chopped logs into a pond and being admonished by the farmer who chopped them.)
* "Did the [[This Little Piggy|little piggy]] cry 'wee wee wee' all the way home?" (Cuts to a [[pig]] named Maxwell riding in the back seat of an SUV holding pinwheels, yelling "wee wee wee" out the window, before being dropped off at his house by his friend's exasperated mother.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/user/GEICO#p/u/5/8F_G2zp-opg |title=Piggy |publisher=YouTube |date=2005-12-06 |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See section [[GEICO advertising campaigns#Maxwell the Pig|Maxwell the Pig]]) 
* "Does [[Takes two to tango (idiom)|it take two to tango]]?" (Cuts to a man and woman dancing the tango while another man tries to dance with them.)
* "What, do you live under a rock?" (Cuts to a man living underground who moves a rock so he can raise his head above ground to see outside, and then gets excited when he sees a GEICO billboard and invites his friend Rick to move his own rock and take a peek.)
* "Does [[Buck passing|the buck stop here]]?" (The camera zooms out as a [[deer]] walks onto the soundstage and stops next to McGlone, who then shrugs his shoulders.)
* "Do dogs chase cats?" (Cuts to a dog and cat engaged in a [[Bullitt]]-style car chase.)
* "Is [[The pen is mightier than the sword|the pen mightier than the sword]]?" (Cuts to a [[ninja]] menacingly demonstrating his swordsmanship to his opponent, who countermaneuvers by using a pen to sign for the delivery of his new taser, with which he promptly defeats the ninja.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IcZd-ql7t1I |title=Is the Pen Mightier? |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* "Would [[Foghorn Leghorn]] make a really bad book narrator?"  (Cuts to a recording studio where Foghorn is reading "[[A Tale of Two Cities]]"—his ad-libbing and talking over the director cause an exasperated [[Henery Hawk]] to get up from the control panel and whack him with a club.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gV369kpV4h0 |title=Foghorn Leghorn |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* “Do people use [[smartphone]]s to do dumb things?” (Cuts to 3 office workers using very silly smartphone apps to help celebrate the end of the workweek.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oe-Y-zSd5gs |title=Smartphone, dumb things |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Radio ads===
* "Would helium make opera sound less stuffy" (Cuts to male opera singer singing in a deep voice, then inhaling helium, and continuing in a high-pitched voice.)
* "Do mimes make even less sense when you can't see them?" (Cuts to a narrator describing a [[mime]] pretending to be inside an invisible box.)
* "Is sneaking out of a really boring meeting while wearing tap shoes a bad idea?" (Cuts to a boring meeting with tap shoes in the background, until the boss catches on.)
* "Does [[A rolling stone gathers no moss|a rolling stone gather no moss]]?" (Cuts to the sound of a boulder rolling through various things until it crashes to a stop, with McGlone then saying, "No moss -- you're gonna have to trust me on this one.")
* "Do only dogs hear [[dog whistle]]s?" (Cuts to the sound of someone breathing in, then blowing in a dog whistle a few times, before being interrupted by several barking dogs.)
* "[[If a tree falls in the forest]] and no one is around, does it make a noise?"  (Cuts to the sound of a tree falling and crashing, with McGlone then saying, "Yep.")
* "Is texting getting way out of hand?"  (McGlone then begins to elaborate, but is interrupted and distracted by several incoming texts, ultimately responding to one message with "LOL, UR my BFF.")
* "Can you find anything on the internet? "

==Short Stories and Tall Tales==
Starting in 2010, there have been TV commercials in which a [[nursery rhyme]], being read to the audience from an illustrated book entitled ''Short Stories and Tall Tales'', turns into an ad for GEICO homeowner's insurance:
* In one, the [[Hey Diddle Diddle|cow who jumped over the moon]] crashes down through someone's roof; luckily, the owner was insured with GEICO.
* In another, the [[Itsy Bitsy Spider]]'s home is flooded as a result of a clogged downspout, and his mattress is ruined; thanks to GEICO, he now has a "[[Select Comfort|Sleep Number]]" bed. His sleep number is 25.
* A burglar breaks into [[Little Miss Muffet]]'s house and steals her tuffets, which were fortunately insured. The burglar was later caught, given away by a whey stain.

==Xtranormal==
Near the end of 2010, a new advertising campaign began made up of amateurish computer animated advertisements, supposedly made in 15 minutes, created with the computer software program [[Xtranormal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Video: Robo-Talking Superhero Ad Uses Text-to-Voice Trick|first=Hugh|last=Hart|date=October 26, 2010|journal=[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]]|url=http://www.wired.com/underwire/2010/10/geico-superhero/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Easier Way to Save==
Starting in the summer of 2011, a new series of advertising involved people discovering unusual ways to save money.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.NYTimes.com NYTimes.com]'' [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/08/business/media/geico-uses-many-campaigns-to-stand-out-in-a-crowd.html?_r=0 Geico uses many campaigns to stand out in a crowd]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Television commercials''':
* A couple teaching their 6 year old son how to dunk a basketball in order to help him get a scholarship, with him getting stuck on the basket.
* A dog and a cockatoo playing [[A-Ha]]'s "[[Take On Me]]" because their owner can't afford to keep downloading music.
* A sea captain living as a roommate, rehearsing "[[Major-General's Song]]."
* A woman turning her daughter's pet fish into her husband's meal.
* Robots hired in a daycare center because they "work for free".
* Three guinea pigs rowing their boat to produce electricity for their owner's computer.
* A couple adopting a black rescue [[Panthera|panther]] who can protect their house.
* A man singing a personal ad to the tune of [[Bonnie Tyler]]'s "[[Total Eclipse of the Heart]]" because dating websites cost too much money
* Three middle school girls criticize on what the man is eating, only to watch his weight.
* A family forming their own theme park.
* Boy Scouts using paintball guns to decorate a couple's living room.
* A man adopting a pet possum for his kids, as a cheaper alternative to a puppy.

'''Radio commercials''':
* A man who tries to cut his wife's hair, while she sleeps, instead of going to the hairstylist.
* A man who can only rely on toll-free numbers.
* A man consolidating his 5 daughters' weddings into one day.
* A woman carpooling with her daughter's school bus.
* An umpire who cannot pay for his contacts, using the lost pair of eyeglasses he found.
* A man turning his bathroom shower into an amusement attraction, instead of taking his family to an amusement park.
* A man using carrier pigeons to send letters because of the high cost of postage stamps.
* A man who can't spend money on the Internet for his home, thus using his neighbor's [[WEP Key|unprotected]] connection.
* A woman who is dreaming of being in [[Machu Picchu]] because she cannot buy Airline tickets.

==Get Happy, Get GEICO==
Starting in 2012, GEICO ran TV commercials in which [[bluegrass music|bluegrass]] pickers named Ronny (played by Director / Musician Alex Harvey) and Jimmy (played by Actor / Comedian Timothy Ryan Cole), respectively, talk about how happy saving money on insurance can make someone, and using examples intended to be humorous:

* '''Happer than Gallagher at a Farmer's Market''': [[Gallagher (comedian)|Gallagher]] runs amok at a [[farmer's market]], smashing watermelons with a huge mallet and laughing maniacally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uJs_dnj6g_M&amp;feature=relmfu Gallagher ad] at [[YouTube]]&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than a Bodybuilder Directing Traffic''': A smiling [[Bodybuilding|bodybuilder]] is standing in an intersection and directing traffic while striking poses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TBSt1CtJEOk |title=GEICO Bodybuilder Commercial - Happier Than a Body Builder Directing Traffic |publisher=YouTube |date=2012-08-03 |accessdate=2013-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than Christopher Columbus with Speedboats''': [[Christopher Columbus]] is shown on a speeding motoboat, accompanied by two other boats, while a crew member looks seasick.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=raPLzhzxAeU |title=GEICO Christopher Columbus Commercial - Happier Than Christopher Columbus with Speedboats |publisher=YouTube |date=2012-08-16 |accessdate=2013-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than Eddie Money running a travel agency''': A family is shown sitting in front of a desk in an office.  An excited [[Eddie Money]] is then shown behind the desk holding airline tickets, where he begins singing ([[a capella]]), "I've got [[Two Tickets to Paradise]]" while the family appears increasingly annoyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iG0t57PUTaM |title=GEICO Two Tickets to Paradise Commercial - Happier Than Eddie Money Running a Travel Agency |publisher=YouTube |date=2012-08-24 |accessdate=2013-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than a Witch at a Broom Factory''': A [[Witch (etymology)|witch]] is seen flying around on a [[broom]] inside of a broom factory. She lands and demands another broom from one of the employees and begins flying again, laughing and having fun.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?NR=1&amp;feature=endscreen&amp;v=3btVEGC00Ns |title=GEICO Witch Commercial - Happier Than a Witch in a Broom Factory |publisher=YouTube |date=2012-09-07 |accessdate=2013-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than a Slinky on an Escalator''': A [[Slinky]] is seen steeping backwards on an up [[escalator]]. While the Slinky goes backwards, others try to avoid it as they go to work and the slinky says "This is Awesome!" &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yOUbW2A-e2Q |title=GEICO Slinky Commercial - Happier Than A Slinky On An Escalator |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2013-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than an Antelope with Nightvision Goggles''': Two [[antelope]] are seen watching a [[lion]] through [[Night vision device|nightvision goggles]]. The two are secretly laughing at the lion and his poor stealth skills.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7m0VnzPFxew |title=GEICO Night Vision Commercial - Happier than an Antelope with Night Vision Goggles |publisher=YouTube |date=2012-11-01 |accessdate=2013-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than Dikembe Mutumbo Blocking a Shot''': [[Dikembe Mutumbo]] appears blocking various things that people throw, such as a crumpled piece of paper, a pile of laundry, and a box of cereal. The GEICO Logo then appears and Mutumbo knocks off the "G".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C_0fyUYB3cA |title=GEICO Dikembe Mutombo Commercial - Happier Than Dikembe Mutombo Blocking a Shot |publisher=YouTube |date=2013-02-01 |accessdate=2013-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than Paul Revere with a Cell Phone''': [[Paul Revere]] who is inside a home in Concord, Massachusetts, notices a bell ringing from a church. As he looks out the window, he calls on his cell phone and warns that the British are coming. Afterwards, he returns to his guests and plays charades. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=urdPARN999o&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than Dracula Participating at a Blood Drive''': At a blood drive, [[Dracula]] asks a man his blood type and what he ate today. The man replies either A or B positive and that he ate Lebanese food. Dracula says that he loves the Lebanese. He then excitedly decides to skip the formalities and "get started". He is then seen following the man out at the end. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7bYr_PoVpcY&lt;/ref&gt; 

* '''Happier than the Pillsbury Doughboy on his way to a Baking Convention''': At an airport, the [[Pillsbury Doughboy]] is going through airport security, but every time the security guard tries to pat him down, he is easily tickled. He promises to hold it together, but keeps failing. Once he gets on his way, the Doughboy sings along as they continue playing guitar.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EvFul32xKCs&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Happier than a Camel on Wednesday''': At an office, a camel asks workers what day it is. A woman tells him that it is Hump Day. The camel whoops with excitement.

==Did You Know==
Starting in 2013, a series of commercials was broadcast in which one person reads a GEICO "15 percent" ad and a second person says "Everybody knows that," to which the first person says, "Well, did you know..." followed by an amusing (and fictional) "fact" which is then illustrated in a cutaway scene.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j8N2SftkPmQ&amp;list=PLwTsyIROsachrLHs58qKW1Fz6jMmDFzvf "Did You Know" ads] on [[YouTube]]&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Did You Know Some Owls Aren't That Wise?''': An [[owl]] is talking to her owl husband about her friend Megan, and the husband owl keeps saying, "Who?"

* '''Did You Know Old MacDonald Was a Really Bad Speller?''': [[Old MacDonald Had a Farm|Old MacDonald]] is a contestant in a [[spelling bee]], and is asked to spell "cow"; "C-O-W, E-I-E-I-O."

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Advertising campaigns]]</text>
      <sha1>px39wgkx6cbro9dlkhq2gn8ll32mbf8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>