<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Genome browser</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4457052</id>
    <revision>
      <id>559901313</id>
      <parentid>559900854</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-14T17:09:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tnabtaf</username>
        <id>4489820</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* List of genome browsers */ Added paper to Trackster.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">In [[bioinformatics]], a '''genome browser''' is a graphical interface for display of information from a [[biological database]] for genomic data.  Genome browsers enable researchers to visualize and browse entire genomes (most have many complete genomes) with annotated data including gene prediction and structure, proteins, expression, regulation, variation, comparative analysis, etc. Annotated data is usually from multiple diverse sources.  They differ from ordinary biological databases in that they display data in a graphical format, with genome coordinates on one axis and the location of annotations indicated by a space-filling graphic to show the occurrence of genes, etc.

==List of genome browsers==
&lt;!-- PLEASE KEEP IN ALPHABETICAL ORDER --&gt;
* [http://www.interactive-biosoftware.com/software/alamut/features Alamut] A gene browser that handles [http://www.hgvs.org/ HGVS] nomenclature&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|21992071}}&lt;/ref&gt; and integrates [[missense]] and [[RNA splicing|splicing]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|22505045}}&lt;/ref&gt; prediction tools for [[mutation]] interpretation.
* [http://annmap.picr.man.ac.uk Annmap] A genome browser that shows [[Affymetrix]] [[Exon]] Microarray hit locations alongside the [[gene]], transcript and exon data on a [[Google Maps]] API
* [http://apollo.berkeleybop.org/current/index.html Apollo Genome Annotation Curation Tool] A cross-platform, Java-based standalone genome viewer with enterprise-level functionality and customizations.  The standard for many model organism databases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 12537571}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.broad.mit.edu/annotation/argo/ Argo Genome Browser] A free and open source standalone Java-based genome browser for visualizing and manually annotating whole genomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|16709588}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.sanger.ac.uk/resources/software/artemis/ Artemis Genome Browser] A free and open source standalone genome browser ([[Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute]]) for visualizing and manually annotating whole genomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|11120685}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can also be used to visualize next generation data.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|22199388}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.avadis-ngs.com/features/genome_browser  Avadis NGS] combines a genome browser and set of data analysis tools for [[ChIP-Seq]], [[RNA-Seq]], and genomic variation experiments, developed by [[Strand Life Sciences]]
*[http://doolittle.ibls.gla.ac.uk/leader/BugView/index.html BugView] Free cross-platform desktop browser for visualizing genomes, especially suited for comparing prokaryotic genomes.
* [http://sourceforge.net/projects/celeragb/files Celera Genome Browser], developed at Celera Genomics as part of Celera's sequencing and annotation of the human genome, and released as open source in 2006. 
* [http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/chipmonk/ Chipmonk] A Java-based tool to visualise and analyse ChIP-on-chip array data, developed at the Babraham Institute in Cambridge.
* [http://www.biodalliance.org Dalliance] Javascript-based genome browser
* [http://diprogb.fli-leibniz.de DiProGB: The Dinucleotide Properties Genome Browser]
* [https://dnanexus.com/genomes/hg18/public_browse DNAnexus] Flash-based interactive genome browser, as well as next-gen sequence analysis and visualization.
* [http://www.ensembl.org/ Ensembl] The [[Ensembl]] Genome Browser ([[Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute]] and [[European Bioinformatics Institute|EBI]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 22086963}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 11752248}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://gaggle.systemsbiology.net/docs/geese/genomebrowser/ Gaggle Genome Browser] A java-based genome browser developed at Institute for Systems Biology (ISB) for  high-throughput data integration.
* [http://gmod.org/wiki/GBrowse GBrowse] The [[Generic Model Organism Database|GMOD]] GBrowse Project&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 20971988}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|16844709}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/genome-wowser/id437044318?mt=8 Genome Wowser] An iPad-enabled view of the human genome. The app, developed by the Center for Biomedical Informatics (CBMi) at [[The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia]], provides a functional presentation of the popular [[UCSC Genome Browser]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.genengnews.com/best-science-apps/genome-wowser/105/ Genome Wowser. "Best Science Apps". Genetic Engineering &amp; Biotechnology News.  Feb 01, 2013 (Vol. 33, No. 3).]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Genomic HyperBrowser]] focuses on statistical analysis of elements along the genome;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|21182759}}&lt;/ref&gt; built on the [[Galaxy (computational biology)|Galaxy]] platform.
* [http://www.genostar.com/en/genostar-software/genomic-analysis-tools/genobrowser.html Genostar GenoBrowser]: a standalone application to display and explore genomic data from any kind of file (EMBL, GenBank, Fasta, GFF...)
* [http://genoverse.org Genoverse interactive genome browser]: web-based, scrollable genome browser, designed to be easily integrated into any website with a few strings of javascript. Loads data dynamically via AJAX and visualizes via HTML5 canvas element
* [http://genplay.einstein.yu.edu GenPlay] A genome viewer and analyzer developed in Java at Albert Einstein College of Medicine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 21596789}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.goldenhelix.com/GenomeBrowse Golden Helix GenomeBrowse] A free genome browser for exploring sequencing pile-up and coverage data with numerous annotation tracks hosted on the cloud.
* [[Integrated Genome Browser]] (IGB) Open source and free Java-based desktop genome viewer for visualizing next-gen sequence and microarray data. 
* [http://www.broadinstitute.org/igv/ Integrative Genomics Viewer] (IGV) A high-performance visualization tool for interactive exploration of large, integrated genomic datasets &lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 22517427}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://img.jgi.doe.gov/ Integrated Microbial Genomes] (IMG) system by the DOE-[[Joint Genome Institute]]
* [http://jbrowse.org/ JBrowse] a JavaScript genome browser by the open source [http://gmod.org/ Generic Model Organism Database] project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|19570905}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://mgv2.cmbi.ru.nl MGV] - Microbial Genome Viewer
* [http://mykaryoview.com myKaryoView] - A Direct-to-consumer oriented genomic browser &lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 22046276}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://johnsonlab.ucsf.edu/sj/mochiview-start MochiView Genome Browser]
* [https://www.nextbio.com/b/gb/genomeBrowser.nb NextBio Genome Browser] - an interactive application that lets visualization of physical relationship between private or public biosets and different types of genomic elements, including genes, miRNA targets, CNVs, CpG islands, SNPs, GWAS associations, and LD blocks]
* [http://bioinformatics.ai.sri.com/ptools/ Pathway Tools] Genome Browser&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 12169551}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.genomesavant.com Savant Genome Browser] for visual analytics of high-throughput sequencing data
* [http://seed-viewer.theseed.org SEED viewer] for visualizing and interrogating the SEED database of complete microbial genomes
* [http://tgac-browser.tgac.ac.uk TGAC Browser] visualisation solutions for big data in the genomic era. An open-source Genome Browser developed at [http://www.tgac.ac.uk/ The Genome Analysis Centre, UK] works with Ensembl Data set and many more. 
* [http://wiki.galaxyproject.org/Learn/Visualization Trackster] [[Galaxy (computational biology)|Galaxy's]] visualization and visual analysis environment &lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 23138293}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|23758618}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://genome.ucsc.edu UCSC Genome Bioinformatics] [[UCSC Genome Browser|Genome Browser]] and Tools ([[University of California, Santa Cruz|UCSC]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid| 12045153}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://troy.bioc.uvic.ca/tools/VGO Viral Genome Organizer (VGO)] A genome browser providing visualization and analysis tools for annotated whole genomes from the eleven virus families in the VBRC (Viral Bioinformatics Resource Center) databases
* [[VISTA genome browser]]  a comprehensive suite of programs and databases for comparative analysis of genomic sequences. There are two ways of using VISTA - you can submit your own sequences and alignments for analysis (VISTA servers) or examine pre-computed whole-genome alignments of different species.
* [http://epigenomegateway.wustl.edu/browser WashU EpiGenome Browser] web-based visual exploration of genomics and epigenomics data sets&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|22127213}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|23255151}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Genomics]]</text>
      <sha1>7q66pyjv5db49bzxtdgnu1t4usj3pg2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>