<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>GoPivotal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39467663</id>
    <revision>
      <id>563003180</id>
      <parentid>563003016</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-05T17:59:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Michaeldweir</username>
        <id>19294973</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>clarified product information.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
'''GoPivotal, Inc. (Pivotal)''' is an American enterprise software company based in [[San Mateo, California]].  The company is [[Platform as a service | Platform as a Service (PaaS)]] centric, combining selected technology, people, and programs from [[EMC Corporation | EMC]] and [[VMware]] into an independent venture.

== History ==

The launch of Pivotal was first speculated in July of 2012 when [[GigaOM]] broke the news of a possible spin out of VMware and EMC that would consolidate some of their [[Cloud computing | cloud]] assets into a new division.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gigaom.com/2012/07/16/vmware-plans-cloud-spin-out-to-keep-up-with-microsoft-amazon-and-google/ VMware plans cloud spin out to keep up with Microsoft, Amazon and Google], GigaOM, 16-July-2012&lt;/ref&gt;  The companies confirmed speculation in December of the same year, announcing that EMC's [[Chief Strategy Officer]], [[Paul Maritz]], would lead the Pivotal Initiative - the committing of key existing technology, people and programs from both companies focused on [[Big Data]] and Cloud Application Platforms under one virtual organization.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.vmware.com/vmware/2012/12/the-pivotal-initiative.html The Pivotal Initiative], VMware Blogs, 04-December-2013&lt;/ref&gt;  On April 1, 2013, [[The New York Times]] reported that Pivotal was "official" and positioned the company as "a well-financed competitor to [[Amazon Web Services]]."&lt;ref&gt;[http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/04/01/emcs-amazon-challenger-comes-out/ EMC’s Amazon Challenger Comes Out], The New York Times, 01-April-2013&lt;/ref&gt;

At Pivotal's official launch event held on April 24, 2013, the organization announced both a $105 million investment from [[General Electric]] and its premier PaaS offering, Pivotal One, a cloud-enabled application platform for private cloud initiatives and public cloud providers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gartner.com/newsroom/id/2448415 GE Joins EMC and VMware in a Joint Venture to Challenge Software Megavendors in the Cloud], Gartner, 24-April-2013&lt;/ref&gt;

== Products ==

=== Pivotal One ===

'''Pivotal One''' is the first Consumer-Grade Enterprise PaaS offering real-time, high-capacity analytics, the flexibility of cloud independence, modern programming frameworks, and support for legacy systems.  It aims to offer companies a level of cloud independence by knitting together data, application, and cloud fabrics into a single platform that runs on third-party [[Infrastructure_as_a_service#Infrastructure_as_a_service_.28IaaS.29 | Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS)]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoworld.com/t/paas/under-the-hood-of-pivotal-one-where-cloud-dev-meets-big-data-217237 Under the hood of Pivotal One, where cloud dev meets big data], InfoWorld, 24-April-2013&lt;/ref&gt; 

Components of the platform are programs that were once produced by EMC, VMware, and their subsidiaries.

==== Pivotal Data Fabric ====

*'''Pivotal HD''' - a commercial [[Apache Hadoop]] distribution enhanced to support enterprise Big Data analytics and is the industry’s first native [[massively parallel computing |massively parallel processing (MPP)]] SQL database that connects to Hadoop.
*'''Pivotal Greenplum Database''' - a [[shared nothing architecture | shared-nothing]], MPP architecture designed for [[business intelligence]] and analytical processing.
*'''Pivotal DCA''' - a physical appliance built to integrate structured data, unstructured data, and Pivotal partner applications.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/09/21/emc_greenplum_dca_appliance_update/ Greenplum appliances swing both ways], The Register, 21-September-2011&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Pivotal Chorus''' - a social network portal for data science teams to search, explore, visualize, share, import data from both within the organization and external sources.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/development/database/emc-marries-social-networking-and-big-da/232602911 EMC Marries Social Networking And Big Data], InformationWeek, 20-March-2012&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Pivotal Performance and Monitoring''' - ensures optimal quality of service for critical enterprise applications by delivering real-time control of database transaction performance, including information about overall [[CPU]] and [[input/output | I/O]] consumption to the query level.
*'''Pivotal Analytics''' - a consumer-grade, analytics platform for enterprises that comprehensively analyzes big data to provide predictive business intelligence and IT/operational insights.
*'''Pivotal GemFire''' - an in memory data grid that enables real-time data distribution, data replication, caching and data management using a non-relational key-value store, to allow storage of data for client applications.
*'''Pivotal SQLFire''' - memory-oriented data management software delivering application data at runtime with horizontal scale and lightning-fast performance while providing developers with the well-known [[SQL]] interface and tools.

==== Pivotal Cloud and Application Fabric ====

*'''Cloud Foundry''' - an open PaaS, providing a choice of clouds, developer frameworks and application services.
*'''Pivotal tc Server''' - an enterprise [[Apache Tomcat | Tomcat]] Application server.
*'''Pivotal Web Server''' -  [[HTTP]] server and load-balancing component that increases web tiers performance, scalability and security while reducing deployment times and complexity.
*'''Pivotal RabbitMQ''' - robust and reliable inter-system messaging for modern applications.
*'''Spring Framework''' - provides a range of capabilities for creating all [[Java (software platform) | Java]] application types, including [[Java Platform, Enterprise Edition | enterprise Java]], rich Web and enterprise integration.

==== Pivotal Expert Services ====

*'''[[Pivotal Labs]]''' - developer of the popular [[agile management | agile]] [[project management]] tool, Pivotal Tracker, Pivotal Labs builds consumer and enterprise web and mobile applications for global clients.
*'''Pivotal Data Science Labs''' -  a [[data science]] consultation service provided by Pivotal’s team of data scientists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gopivotal.com/pivotal-products/pivotal-expert-services/pivotal-data-science-labs Pivotal Data Science Labs], retrieved 22-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Pivotal Open Source Software ====

Pivotal employs committers, project leads and contributors to dozens of open source projects and community initiatives. Pivotal maintains to the world's most poplar Java framework, Spring, the open platform as a service, Cloud Foundry, RabbitMQ, Redis and many other critical open source developer and infrastructure technologies.

Key open source initiatives&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gopivotal.com/pivotal-products/open-source-software Pivotal Open Source Software], retrieved 22-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt; sponsored and lead by Pivotal are:
*'''[[Spring Framework |Spring]]''' - a framework that provides free development tools and technologies used by millions of Java application developers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.springsource.org/get-started Get Started with Spring], retrieved 20-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Cloud Foundry]]''' - an open source cloud computing PaaS software developed under the terms of the [[Apache License]] 2.0.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rpstechnologies.net/ron/blog/2013/04/easy-grails-hosting-cloud-foundry/ Easy Grails Hosting: Cloud Foundry], 2013-April-15&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Redis]]''' -  an open source, [[BSD licenses | BSD licensed]], advanced key-value store database.
*'''[[RabbitMQ]]'''™ - an open source enterprise messaging system [[message broker]] based on the standard [[AMQP | Advanced Messaging Queueing Protocol (AMQP)]]. The source code is released under the [[Mozilla Public License]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://virtualization-for-layman.blogspot.com/2011/06/what-is-rabbitmq.html What is RabbitMQ?]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Grails (framework) | Grails]]''' - a full stack web application framework for the [[Java virtual machine | Java Virtual Machine (JVM)]] based on the Groovy programming language.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intelligrape.com/blog/2011/01/16/why-use-grails/ Why use Grails?], IntelliGrape, retrieved 22-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Groovy (programming language) | Groovy]]''' - a [[dynamic programming language]] with similar features as [[Python (programming language) | Python]], [[Ruby (programming language) | Ruby]], and [[Smalltalk]] that resides on the JVM.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoworld.com/d/application-development/groovy-the-roadmap-the-popular-jvm-language-202990 Groovy: The road map for the popular JVM language], InfoWorld, 25-September-2012&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''OpenChorus'''™ - aims to develop a platform for collaborative data science with Pivotal customers, data science practitioners, open source developers, and partners, while facilitating an open dialogue about the future of [[predictive analytics]].
*'''MADlib''' -  an open-source library for scalable in-database analytics, providing data-parallel implementations of mathematical, statistical and [[machine learning | machine-learning]] methods for structured and unstructured data.

== Leadership ==

*'''Paul Maritz''', [[Chief Executive Officer]], became the President of the Cloud Infrastructure and Services Division at EMC in 2008 when Pi, a company he founded, was acquired by EMC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emc.com/about/news/press/2008/20080221-01.htm EMC To Acquire Pi Corporation, Developer of Personal Information Management Technology], retrieved 23-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt; Immediately prior to leading Pivotal, Maritz was CEO of VMware and Chief Strategist of EMC.
*'''Bill Cook''', [[chief operating officer | Chief Operations Officer]], spent 19 years at [[Sun Microsystems]] where he served as Senior Vice President of US Sales.  He became President of EMC’s [[Greenplum]] division and served as CEO starting in 2010 when EMC acquired the company.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emc.com/about/news/press/2010/20100706-01.htm EMC to Acquire Greenplum], retrieved 23-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Adrian Colyer''', Chief Architect, was previously [[Chief Technology Officer]] at VMware. [[MIT Technology Review]] named Colyer as one of the top 100 young innovators in the world in the publication's 2004 listing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.technologyreview.com/news/403122/tr-100-computing/ TR 100: Computing], MIT Technology Review, retrieved 22-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Richard Snee''', [[Chief Marketing Officer]], led marketing at [[IronPort]], which was acquired by [[Cisco Systems |Cisco]] in 2007 for $830 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ecommercetimes.com/story/54992.html Cisco Buys IronPort for $830 Million], E-Commerce Times, retrieved 21-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt;  Immediately prior to Pivotal, he was Vice President of Marketing of EMC's Greenplum division.
*'''Robert O'Donovan''', [[Chief Financial Officer]], was Vice President of Sales Productivity and Enablement for EMC Asia Pacific and Japan where he pioneered strategies that led to the growth of operational performance.  Before that, he served as EMC's CFO for the Asia Pacific and Japan region.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gopivotal.com/about-pivotal/team Pivotal Executive Team], retrieved 23-May-2013&lt;/ref&gt;

== Competitors ==

*[[Amazon Web Services]]
*[[Cloud computing]]
*[[Google]]
*[[HP Cloud Services]]
*[[IBM]]
*[[OpenShift]]
*[[OpenStack]]
*[[Oracle Corporation |Oracle]]
*[[Rackspace Cloud]]
*[[Windows Azure]]

== References ==

{{reflist}}

== External Links ==

*Pivotal Web site (http://www.gopivotal.com)
*Pivotal Labs Web site (http://www.pivotallabs.com)
*Pivotal Analytics Work Bench Web site (http://www.analyticsworkbench.com/)
*Spring Web site (http://www.springsource.org/)
*Cloud Foundry Web site (http://www.cloudfoundry.com/)

&lt;!-- Be sure to cite all of your sources in &lt;ref&gt;...&lt;/ref&gt; tags and they will automatically display when you hit save. The more reliable sources added the better! See [[Wikipedia:REFB]] for more information--&gt;

&lt;!-- This will add a notice to the bottom of the page and won't blank it! The new template which says that your draft is waiting for a review will appear at the bottom; simply ignore the old (grey) drafted templates and the old (red) decline templates. A bot will update your article submission. Until then, please don't change anything in this text box.  Just press "Save page". --&gt;

[[Category:Software companies based in California]]</text>
      <sha1>kpk0t4wpyw7s2szbu76cisd6n6iagpw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>