<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Hiram B. Clawson</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26044165</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515368456</id>
      <parentid>486332557</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-30T21:05:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GoodDay</username>
        <id>589223</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed intro</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=January 2012}}
{{Infobox Latter Day Saint biography
| name                       = Hiram B. Clawson
| image                      = Hiram B. Clawson.jpg
| image_size                 = 
| alt                        = Photo of Hiram B. Clawson
| caption                    = 
| birth_name                 = 
| birth_date                 = {{Birth date|1826|11|07|mf=yes}}
| birth_place                = [[Utica, New York|Utica]], [[New York]], United States
| home_town                  = 
| nationality                = 
| death_date                 = 1912&lt;!-- {{Dda|yyyy|mm|dd|yyyy|mm|dd|mf=yes}} --&gt;
| death_place                = 
| death_cause                = 
}}
'''Hiram B. Clawson''' (November 7, 1826 &amp;ndash; 1912) was a Latter-day Saint businessman and Church leader in the 19th and early 20th centuries.

Clawson was born in [[Utica, New York]].  He was educated at the [[Utica Academy]]. In 1838 he joined [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] along with his widowed mother. In 1841 they moved to [[Nauvoo, Illinois|Nauvoo]].  

Clawson went west with the Latter-day Saints, arriving in Salt Lake City in 1848. He supervised the building of the first adobe building in Salt Lake City and then was the head mason for the [[Council House (Salt Lake City)|Council House]] of which [[Truman Angell]] was the architect.  Also for a time while Angell was away on a mission Clawson served as acting architect of the [[Salt Lake Temple]].

Clawson was a close associate of [[Brigham Young]] and for many years served as his business manager. He also was involved in the building of the [[Salt Lake Theatre]] and was often a performer in its plays. Clawson was also for a time manager of the theatre.&lt;ref&gt;[[Andrew Jenson]]. ''Encyclopedia History of the Church'' (Salt Lake City: Deseret Book, 1941) p. 763&lt;/ref&gt;

Clawson served as an aide-de-camp to [[Daniel H. Wells]] in running the [[Nauvoo Legion]] in 1850. He later served as adjutant general of the Legion from 1863 until the legion was disbanded in 1870.

In 1865 Clawson bought out William H. Hooper to become partners with [[Horace S. Eldredge]].  Clawson and Eldredge dissolved their firm in 1868 and sold it to [[Zion's Cooperative Mercantile Institution]] (ZCMI). Clawson was then the general superintendent of ZCMI from 1868-1873.  After been replaced for a short time by Hooper Clawson took over the head of ZCMI again from 1874-1875. In 1875 Clawson bought the agriculture, hide and wool departments of ZCMI which he ran as an independent business until 1885.

From 1884 until 1902 Clawson served as the bishop of the Twelfth Ward in Salt Lake City.
==Family==
Clawson had four wives. His first wife was Ellen Curtis Spencer Clawson, a daughter of [[Orson Spencer]]. Among their children was [[Spencer Clawson]] who ran unsuccessfully for mayor of Salt Lake City.

Clawson's second wife was Margaret Gay Judd, who was born in Canada. One of their children was [[Rudger Clawson]] who was a member of the [[Quorum of the Twelve]]. Another of their children, Thomas A. Clawson, became a dentist and served in several callings in the LDS Church including succeeding [[Orson F. Whitney]] as bishop of the Eighteenth Ward in Salt Lake City.

Clawson's third wife was Alice Young, a daughter of Brigham Young and [[Mary Ann Angell]].

Clawson's fourth wife was Emily Young, a daughter of Brigham Young and [[Emily Patridge]].

Clawson had a total of forty-two children.

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*[[Andrew Jenson]]. ''LDS Biographical Encyclopedia'', Vol. 1, p.&amp;nbsp;629.
*[[Richard H. Cracroft]] and [[Neal E. Lambert]], ed., ''A Believing People'', (Provo: BYU Press, 1974) p.&amp;nbsp;119.
*[http://db3-sql.staff.library.utah.edu/lucene/Manuscripts/null/Ms0040.xml/complete University of Utah bio of Clawson] 

{{LDScouncil50}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Clawson, Hiram B.
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1826
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Utica, New York|Utica]], [[New York]], United States
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1912
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Clawson, Hiram B.}}
[[Category:1826 births]]
[[Category:Converts to Mormonism]]
[[Category:American Latter Day Saints]]
[[Category:Mormon pioneers]]
[[Category:People from Utica, New York]]
[[Category:People from Salt Lake City, Utah]]
[[Category:Bishops of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]
[[Category:1912 deaths]]
[[Category:Members of the Council of Fifty]]</text>
      <sha1>tvqnij0pa5e22xnsl9dwumvwu47kggb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>