<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Joseph Smith Memorial Building</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2470882</id>
    <revision>
      <id>555624747</id>
      <parentid>549006366</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-18T08:42:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>79.192.36.163</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ added portals</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox NRHP
  | name = Hotel Utah
  | nrhp_type = 
  | image = JSMemorial.JPG
  | caption = View from the South.
  | location= S. Temple and Main St., [[Salt Lake City, Utah]]
  | lat_degrees = 40
  | lat_minutes = 46
  | lat_seconds = 11
  | lat_direction = N
  | long_degrees = 111
  | long_minutes = 53
  | long_seconds = 26
  | long_direction = W
  | coord_display = inline,title
  | locmapin = Utah
  | built = 1909-1911
  | architect = Parkinson &amp; Bergstrom
  | architecture = Classical Revival, Modern Italian Renaissance
  | added = January 3, 1978
  | area = {{convert|1|acre}}
  | governing_body = Private
  | refnum = 78002673&lt;ref name="nris"&gt;{{NRISref|2009a}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
[[Image:LDS Chapel.jpg|thumb|left|220px|The chapel in the Joseph Smith Memorial Building.]]
[[Image:JSMB foyer.jpg|thumb|220px|left|A view of the foyer, from the upper level. The statue is of [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]] and is nine feet five inches tall, weighing 3,950 pounds.]]
Originally the Hotel Utah, the '''Joseph Smith Memorial Building''' was later named in honor of [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]], the founder of the [[Latter Day Saint movement]].  It is located on the corner of Main Street and South Temple in [[Salt Lake City]]. It is now a social center with three restaurants: [http://www.templesquarehospitality.com/restaurants/roof.php The Roof Restaurant], [http://www.templesquarehospitality.com/restaurants/garden.php The Garden Restaurant] and [http://www.templesquarehospitality.com/restaurants/cafe.php The Nauvoo Cafe]. It is also a venue for events complete with 13 banquet rooms, [http://www.templesquarehospitality.com/jsmb/ catering services], event coordinators and a full-service floral department - [http://www.templesquarehospitality.com/services/floral.php Flowers Squared]. Several levels of the building also serve as administrative offices for LDS Church departments such as Family Search. On January 3, 1978, it was added to the [[National Register of Historic Places]] as the Hotel Utah.&lt;ref name="nris"/&gt;

== History==
The corner of Main Street and South Temple has long been important in Utah history. Prior to construction of the Hotel Utah in 1909-11, the general [[tithe|tithing]] office of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church), a [[bishop's storehouse]], and the [[Deseret News]] printing plant all were located on the site. 

Work on the Second [[Renaissance Revival]] style [[hotel]], designed by the [[Los Angeles]] architectural firm of Parkinson and Bergstrom, began in June 1909. Two years later, on June 9, 1911, the Hotel Utah opened for business. While the LDS Church was the primary stockholder, many Mormon and non-Mormon community and business leaders also purchased stock in the effort to provide the city with a first-class hotel.&lt;ref&gt;http://db3-sql.staff.library.utah.edu/lucene/Manuscripts/null/Ms0469.xml/complete&lt;/ref&gt;

"The largest and finest bar in the West [was built] in the basement of the Hotel" to pay off a $2M construction loan.  The financing was secured by [[Presiding Bishop (LDS Church)|Presiding Bishop]] [[Charles W. Nibley]], from New York financier Charles Baruch. But the scheme obviously required the sales of [[hard liquor]].

The ten-story building has a concrete and steel structure and is covered with white [[Glazed architectural terra-cotta|glazed terra cotta]] and [[brick]]. Various additions and remodelings have occurred throughout the years, including a substantial expansion to the north and modifications to the roof-top dining facilities. 

It was featured in the 1973 film "Harry in Your Pocket" starring James Coburn.

The building ceased operations as a hotel in August 1987. A major remodeling and [[adaptive reuse]] project to accommodate both community and church functions was completed in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lds.org/placestovisit/location/0,10634,1872-1-1-1,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;  Church leader [[Gordon B. Hinckley]] chose the name when he observed that there were many monuments to pioneer leader and Utah founder [[Brigham Young]], but none to Joseph Smith.

2011 marked the celebration of 100 years since initial construction was completed on the Hotel Utah.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hotelutah100.com/&lt;/ref&gt;

== Current use ==
The LDS Church now uses this building as follows:
* A large, historical, ornately decorated multi-story lobby, featuring a large white statue of [[Joseph Smith, Jr]], and an enormous crystal chandelier. Live classical music is often performed here as background.
* The [[FamilySearch]] center, where the public can use the provided computers and materials to do [[family history]] research and [[genealogy]].&lt;ref name="famsearch"&gt;http://www.lds.org/placestovisit/location/0,10634,1870-1-1-1,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Legacy: A Mormon Journey|Legacy Theater]], where the public can enjoy inspirational regularly scheduled free showings of various [[LDS movies#Recent films|church-produced movies]], including ''[[Joseph Smith: Prophet of the Restoration]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lds.org/placestovisit/location/0,10634,6434-1-1-1,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* Two restaurants, ''The Roof'' and ''The Garden'', on the top floor, provide views of downtown Salt Lake City.&lt;ref name="famsearch"/&gt;
* Interior levels of the building are devoted to ongoing work on various church software projects, supporting the worldwide [[Family History Center (LDS Church)|family history centers]], and various other activities.
* Many rooms on the ground level, and on the ninth and tenth floors, can be rented out for wedding receptions or dinners.
* There is a chapel used for the Sunday services of various downtown [[ward (LDS Church)|wards]].
* A pair of [[peregrine falcons]] returns yearly to nest in a [[nest box]] at the top of the building, which has two [[webcams]] installed in it, viewable to the public.&lt;ref&gt;http://wildlife.utah.gov/peregrine&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Latter-day Saints|Book of Mormon}}
{{Commons category|Joseph Smith Memorial Building}}
* [http://lds.org/placestovisit/eng/historical-sites/joseph-smith-memorial-building Official Joseph Smith Memorial Building Web Page]
* [http://www.allaboutmormons.com/templesquare.php An on-line tour of Temple Square, including the Joseph Smith Memorial Building]
* [http://www.oldsads.org/postcards.htm?tid=69&amp;image=932 History of the Hotel Utah, Old Post Cards]
* [http://wildlife.utah.gov/peregrine/ Falcon Homepage], [[Utah Division of Wildlife Resources]]
* [http://templesquarehospitality.com/restaurants/roof.php The Roof] and [http://templesquarehospitality.com/restaurants/garden.php The Garden] Restaurants, located on the top floor of the Joseph Smith Memorial Building

{{s-start}}
{{succession box|
  before=[[Boston Building (Salt Lake City)|Boston Building]]|
  title=[[List of tallest buildings in Salt Lake City|Tallest Building in Salt Lake City]]|
  years=1911 - 1912&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;56m&lt;/small&gt;|
  after=[[Walker Center]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{LDSsites}}
{{National Register of Historic Places}}

[[Category:20th-century Latter Day Saint church buildings]]
[[Category:Classical Revival architecture]]
[[Category:Defunct hotels in the United States]]
[[Category:History of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]
[[Category:Hotel buildings on the National Register of Historic Places in Utah]]
[[Category:Joseph Smith]]
[[Category:Meetinghouses of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints in Utah]]
[[Category:Office buildings in Salt Lake City, Utah]]
[[Category:Properties of religious function on the National Register of Historic Places in Utah]]
[[Category:Properties of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]
[[Category:Hotel buildings completed in 1911]]
[[Category:Religious buildings completed in 1911]]
[[Category:Skyscrapers in Salt Lake City, Utah]]
[[Category:The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints in Utah]]</text>
      <sha1>gwf8595fzf066s7g76rzmqqfc1lty7y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>