<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Languages of Tunisia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31090652</id>
    <revision>
      <id>552292582</id>
      <parentid>546114826</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-26T16:10:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Happy-omar</username>
        <id>18910574</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>"Science classes up to the end of high school were Arabised". I changed high school to middle school. Because I live in Tunisia, I study in Tunisia, and there is a project to arabize Sciences in high school but it was never done.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Languages of
| country    = Tunisia
| official   = [[Literary Arabic]]
| vernacular = [[Tunisian Arabic]]
| minority   = [[Berber languages]]
| regional   =
| immigrant  =
| foreign    = [[French language|French]]
| keyboard   =
| keyboard image =
| sign       = 
}}[[File:Zarkoun Street.JPG|thumb|right|250px|Street view in [[Tunis]]]]&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Tunisian Arabic advert.JPG|thumb|right|250px|Advert from 2007 with slogan at top in Tunisian Arabic. Tunisian features are the long vowel و in خوذ, the [[complementiser]] باش, the joining of the [[indirect object]] to the verb in تقوللها (tqu:lilha) and the typical [[Maghrebi Arabic|Maghrebi]] first person singular 'n-' in نحبك ''I love you''. Lower text detailing offer is in Standard Arabic.{{Deletable image-caption|Friday, 30 September 2011|date=May 2012}}]] --&gt;[[File:Fmso front.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Sign in Arabic and French at the Sousse Faculty of Medicine.]]
[[Tunisia]] is, in terms of language, the most homogeneous of the [[Maghreb]] states.&lt;ref name="Laval"&gt;{{fr}} [http://www.tlfq.ulaval.ca/AXL/AFRIQUE/tunisie.htm Aménagement linguistique en Tunisie (Université de Laval)]&lt;/ref&gt; This is because almost the entire population speaks [[Tunisian Arabic]] (also called [[Darija]]) natively. Most are also literate in [[Modern Standard Arabic|Literary Arabic]], which is the country's official language, and [[French language|French]]. The Tunisian Darija is considered a [[Varieties of Arabic|variety of Arabic]] - or more accurately a set of dialects &lt;ref&gt;« Travaux de phonologie. Parlers de Djemmal, Gabès, Mahdia (Tunisie) et Tréviso (Italie) », ''Cahiers du CERES'', Tunis, 1969&lt;/ref&gt; - therefore, there is no official standardisation body for Tunisian Arabic&lt;ref&gt;{{fr}} [http://www.persee.fr/showPage.do?luceneQuery=%28tunisie%29+AND+%28indexable_type%3Aarticlepage%3F%29&amp;words=tunisie&amp;words=articlepage&amp;urn=lfr_0023-8368_1977_num_35_1_4828 Juliette Garmadi-Le Cloirec, « Remarques sur la syntaxe du français de Tunisie », ''Langue française'', vol. 35, 1977, p. 86]&lt;/ref&gt; and it is spoken mainly in the context of a daily dialogue within the family. According to linguistic studies, it is a close relative to [[Maltese language|Maltese]].&lt;ref&gt;Albert J. Borg et Marie Azzopardi-Alexander, ''Maltese'', éd. Routledge, New York, 1996, p. XIII {{ISBN|0415022436|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Berber languages]] are spoken by a minority, especially in the south.

During the [[French protectorate in Tunisia]], [[French language|French]] was imposed through public institutions, notably the education system, which became a strong vehicle for dissemination of the language. From independence, the country gradually became [[Arabisation|Arabised]] even though the public administration, justice and education remained bilingual&lt;ref name="ghorbal27"&gt;Samy Ghorbal, « Le français a-t-il encore un avenir ? », ''Jeune Afrique'', 27 avril 2008, pp. 77-78&lt;/ref&gt; meanwhile knowledge of French and other European languages (as [[English language|English]] and [[Italian language|Italian]]) is enhanced by Tunisia's proximity to Europe and notably by media and [[Tourism in Tunisia|tourism]].

The 1990s marked a turning point for the Arabisation process. Science classes up to the end of middle school were Arabised in order to facilitate access to higher education and promote the Arabic language in society.&lt;ref name="ghorbal27"/&gt; Since October 1999, private establishments are forced to give [[Arabic alphabet|Arabic characters]] twice the size compared to [[Latin alphabet|Latin characters]],&lt;ref name="ghorbal27"/&gt; this rule is not always followed however. At the same time, the public administration is required to communicate in Arabic only. Nevertheless, only the departments of Defense and Justice and the [[Parliament of Tunisia|Parliament]] are fully Arabised.&lt;ref name="Laval"/&gt; In this context, the use of French seems to decline despite the increased number of graduates of the educational system, which leads to the fact that a good knowledge much of French remains an important social marker.&lt;ref name="ghorbal27"/&gt; This is because French is widely practised in the business community, the spheres of natural sciences and medicine and intellectual domains, one can even consider that the language has become gentrified.&lt;ref name="ghorbal27"/&gt;

According to recent estimates provided by the Tunisian government to the [[Organisation Internationale de la Francophonie]], the number French speakers is estimated at 6.36 million people, or 63.6% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{fr}} {{PDF|[http://www.francophonie.org/IMG/pdf/La_francophonie_dans_le_monde_2006-2007.pdf Christian Valantin (sous la dir. de), ''La Francophonie dans le monde. 2006-2007'', éd. Nathan, Paris, 2007, p. 16]|5.58&amp;nbsp;MB}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is still uncertain what effects the [[Jasmine revolution]] may have on the country's future language policy.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}}

== See also ==
{{Portal|Tunisia|Languages}}
*[[Demographics of Tunisia]]
*[[Arab World]]
*[[Arabized Berber]]
*[[Maghreb French]]
*[[Languages of Algeria]]
*[[Languages of Morocco]]

==References==

&lt;references /&gt;

==Further reading==
* Gabsi, Zouhir. "Attrition and maintenance of the Berber language in Tunisia." ''[[International Journal of the Sociology of Language]]'', September 2011. Issue 211, p. 135. ISSN 0165-2516. Available on [[Academic OneFile]].

== External links ==
*[http://www.tlfq.ulaval.ca/AXL/AFRIQUE/tunisie.htm Linguistic situation in Tunisia]

{{Africa in topic|Languages of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Languages Of Tunisia}}
[[Category:Languages of Tunisia]]</text>
      <sha1>4ihoiffg9osxz31lnfo43gq7r875f87</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>