<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>OpenWGA</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31282572</id>
    <revision>
      <id>555364964</id>
      <parentid>496083954</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-16T13:37:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>87.234.21.178</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Updated for version 6.1</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{ Infobox Software
| name                   = OpenWGA
| title                  = OpenWGA
| logo                   = [[Image:OpenWGA_6_Logo.png]]
| screenshot             = [[Image:openwga screenshot.png|265px]]
| caption                = OpenWGA Content Manager
| collapsible            = yes
| author                 = 
| developer              = Innovation Gate GmbH
| latest release version = 6.1
| latest release date    = {{release date|2013|04|02}}
| latest preview version = 
| latest preview date    = 
| programming language   = [[Java (programming language)|Java language]]
| operating system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| platform               = [[Java platform]]
| size                   = 45MB
| language               = [[English language|English]] (default), [[German language|German]]
| status                 = Active
| genre                  = [[Content Management System]]
| license                = GNU [[GPL]] 3.0 or higher for Community Edition, Commercial License for Enterprise Edition 
| website                = http://www.openwga.com/
}}

'''OpenWGA''' is [[Web Content Management]] [[computer software]] running on the [[Java Enterprise Edition]] Platform. It is used to build, manage and publish websites and content-centric web applications. The system is developed and maintained by German company Innovation Gate GmbH.

== Components and Editions of the CMS platform ==

The central part of the platform is the '''OpenWGA Server''', a web server process responsible for publishing web applications. It itself is a web application of the [[Java Enterprise Edition]] Platform and is available in two editions:

* The '''Community Edition''' contains the content publishing engine, support for storing content data on [[MySQL]], [[PostgreSQL]], [[Microsoft SQL Server]] and [[HSQLDB]] databases and includes basic capabilities for user authentication. It is licensed as [[Open Source Software]] under GNU [[GPLv3]] or higher and usable without fee. A special exception to the GNU GPL allows distribution of custom-licensed OpenWGA plugins along with the OpenWGA server.

* The '''Enterprise Edition''' builds upon the Community Edition to add support for database platforms ([[Microsoft SQL Server]], [[IBM DB2]], [[Oracle Database]]), user authentication systems ([[LDAP]] directory servers, multiple shared authentication) and external data sources ([[Content Management Interoperability Services|CMIS]] repositories, [[Lotus Domino]] Databases) that are considered "enterprise grade" by the product creators. It consists of the GPL licensed community edition plus a custom-licensed "Enterprise Plugin" containing the additional features. Access to the Enterprise Edition is available via a paidd subscription model by Innovation Gate GmbH.

Another part of the platform is the '''OpenWGA developer studio''', an [[Integrated development environment]] for developing and testing OpenWGA web applications, based on the [[Eclipse (software)|Eclipse IDE framework]].

== History ==

OpenWGA was long time developed under the name of  '''WGA''' and was by this time a commercial Web Content Management System only available to the German market. With releasing it under Open Source License it was rebranded to '''OpenWGA'''. The acronym originally stood for "WebGate Anywhere", containing a reference to the predecessor software "Webgate", a CMS running on the [[IBM Lotus Domino]] Platform. The WGA/OpenWGA software has no connection with [[Windows Genuine Advantage]], also known as WGA.

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Release !! Version !! Notable Enhancements
|-
| 2001 || 1.0 || No complete CMS but merely a Java-based interface server for adding content data to CMS "WebGate" via third party authoring clients like [[Microsoft Word]] and other office products
|-
| 2002 || 2.0 || Complete CMS server on [[J2EE]] platform storing content (and design) data in [[Lotus Domino]] Databases
|-
| 2003 || 2.1 || New administrative tools: "WGA Admin Page" for monitoring and "WGA Manager" ([[Java Webstart]] Application) for configuring the server; Introduction of WebTML actions
|-
| February 2004 || 2.2 || First version of WebTML portlet framework; Switching data interface for Lotus Domino to DIIOP CORBA protocol instead of "native interface", fixing various resource exhaustion problems
|-
| July 2004 || 3.0 || Introduction of content storage for relational database systems; Reworked Browser Authoring Interface; WebTML forms
|-
| December 2004 || 3.1 || WGA Scheduler; Incremental Content Store Synchronisation
|-
| 2005 || 3.2 || Integrated Lucene fulltext index; TMLScript overhaul; ACL Roles
|-
| 2006 || 3.3 || External storage of designs in design directories; Design sharing; WebTML forms and labels
|-
| 2007 || 4.0 || Focus on Web application development; WGA Plugins architecture; Modernization of WebTML portlet framework incl. AJAX functionality; OpenWGA Content Manager replaces "Browser Authoring Interface"; WGA Design Assistant allows configuration of WGA design directories
|-
| 2008 || 4.1 || Optimized content file handling with resource-neutral fetching of large file data; Addressing content via human-readable title path URLs
|-
| April 2010 || 5.0 || Release as OpenWGA Community Edition under GPL; Refactored and simplified administrative model including new OpenWGA admin client; OpenWGA developer studio; Content relations; Exposure to international market &lt;ref&gt;http://www.linux-magazine.com/Online/News/OpenWGA-CMS-Is-Free-Software&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| August 2010 || 5.1 || Pluggable language behaviour; Beginning Drag&amp;Drop support in OpenWGA Content Manager; Externalize serving of large files to HTTP server
|-
| November 2010 || 5.2 || [[Content Management Interoperability Services|CMIS]] connectivity; Support for PostgreSQL databases; Image editing features inside OpenWGA Content Manager &lt;ref&gt;http://www.cmswire.com/cms/enterprise-cms/openwga-52-adds-support-for-cmis-social-media-009368.php&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| March 2011 || 5.3 || Content modules; Virtual Hosts; Search Engine Optimizations
|-
| July 2011 || 5.4 || Plugin Store; Inheritable read access restrictions for pages; Content Module Templates; Customizable application designs
|-
| December 2011 || 5.5 || Basic Website Kit; HDBModel application framework; Support for Microsoft SQLServer in Community Edition
|-
| May 2012 || 6.0 || New base stream with 3 years of support; Basic App Kit; Shared server connection pool
|-
| May 2013 || 6.1 || OpenWGA Server API
|}

== Content management characteristics ==

OpenWGA provides the following characteristic features known in content management and publishing:

* Hierarchically organized, versionable, multi language content in a freely definable structure
* Storage of binary content data along with content
* Automatic fulltext indexing of content
* Browser-based WYSIWYG content authoring
* Configurable read/write authorisations on multiple levels: Application, Hierarchy, Document
* Approval Workflow
* Web service access to content data via CMIS, SOAP and WebDAV
* Synchronisation of Content Data across servers
* User personalisation via individual user profiles

== Template / Application development ==

OpenWGA uses its own templating languages called '''WebTML''' and '''TMLScript'''. WebTML is a syntax of [[XML]]-formatted tags, prefixed with "tml:", that mark dynamic parts of page templates, providing mainly data output and flow control beside offering higher level features. TMLScript is an expression language used to specify expressions and define routines in WebTML that complies to the rules of [[JavaScript]] Version 1.6.

The following example demonstrates the usage of WebTML and TMLScript (inside the "condition" atttribute) in a HTML page template:

&lt;pre&gt;
  &lt;tml:meta name="title"/&gt;
  
  &lt;tml:case condition="!isEmpty('abstract')"&gt;
    &lt;div id="abstract"&gt;
      &lt;tml:item name="abstract" editor="rtf"/&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/tml:case&gt;
  
  &lt;div id="body"&gt;
    &lt;tml:item name="body" editor="rtf"/&gt; 
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

The design of an OpenWGA web application is either provided as '''OpenWGA design directory''' for direct editing or as an '''OpenWGA plugin''' for wider distribution.

== See also ==

* [[List of content management systems]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.openwga.com/ Official Homepage]
* [http://www.innovationgate.com/ Homepage of Innovation Gate GmbH]

[[Category:Free content management systems]]
[[Category:Java platform software]]</text>
      <sha1>loyqx4z7yy5rhegdtsbi7okrbm07l1t</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>