<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Oracle Exalogic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29594639</id>
    <revision>
      <id>560765979</id>
      <parentid>559839182</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-20T15:55:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.183.92.14</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>This entry made no sense and sounded like a poor attempt at an advertisement for the author</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Exalogic''' is a [[computer appliance]] made by [[Oracle Corporation]], commercially available since 2010.&lt;ref name="reg"&gt;{{cite web
 | url         = http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/09/20/hp_oracle_play_nice_avoid_hurd/
 | title       = HP and Oracle avoid blows over disgraced Hurd
 | first       = Gavin
 | last        = Clarke
 | date        = 2010-09-20
 | work        = 
 | publisher   = [[The Register]]
 | accessdate  = 2011-05-29
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a [[Cluster (computing)|cluster]] of [[x86-64]]-servers running [[Oracle Linux]] or [[Oracle Solaris]] preinstalled.

Its full trade mark is ''Oracle Exalogic Elastic Cloud X2-2'' (derived from the [[SI prefix]] ''[[exa-]]'' and ''-logic'', probably from [[Weblogic]]), positioned by the vendor as a preconfigured clustered application server to use in building blocks in [[Cloud computing|clouds]] with [[elastic computing]] abilities.&lt;ref name="ft"&gt;{{cite news
 | first       = Geoff
 | last        = Nairn 
 | title       = Big Data, Big Blue and Going Green
 | url         = http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/b7e4143e-c821-11df-ae3a-00144feab49a.html
 | work        = 
 | publisher   = [[Financial Times]]
 | location    = {{L.}}
 | id          = b7e4143e-c821-11df-ae3a-00144feab49a
 | pages       = 
 | page        = 
 | date        = 2010-09-27
 | accessdate  = 2011-05-29
 | issn        = 0307-1766
 | quote = More surprising was to hear the software giant announce a piece of hardware, the Oracle Exalogic Elastic Cloud. As its name suggests, it is Oracle’s attempt to steal the cloud computing spotlight. It comprises a mix of Oracle software and high-performance hardware and is aimed at enterprises that want to build their own “private cloud” using their own hardware. Sounds suspiciously like mainframe computer.
 | archiveurl = 
 | archivedate = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Oracle Corporation announced Exalogic at the [[Oracle OpenWorld]] conference in [[San Francisco]] in September 2010. The company presented it as a continuation of the Oracle-engineered systems product-line which had started in 2008 with [[Exadata]] (preconfigured database cluster).&lt;ref name="reg"/&gt;&lt;ref name="ft"/&gt;

== Form ==
Exalogic is a factory assembled [[19-inch rack]] of 42 [[Rack unit|units]], completed with [[Server (computing)|servers]] and [[network equipment]]. There are 4 configurations, at different prices, depending on what fills the rack (the following price list is for U.S. consumers):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url         = http://www.oracle.com/us/corporate/pricing/exadata-pricelist-070598.pdf
 | title       = Oracle Engineered Systems Price List
 | date        = 2012-01-10
 | format      = PDF
 | work        = Oracle price lists
 | publisher   = [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]]
 | accessdate  = 2012-01-14
 | description = Oracle Exadata, Exalogic, Exalytics, SPARC SuperCluster and Big Data appliance price list for U.S.
 | deadurl    = 
 | archiveurl  = 
 | archivedate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* eighth rack — $325,000;
* quarter rack — $475,000;
* half-rack — $675,000;
* full rack — $1,075,000.

The weight of the full rack is about 1 ton (more than 2000&amp;nbsp;lbs), a quarter rack weighs half as much.&lt;ref name="hw-spec"/&gt;

== Hardware ==
The hardware component of the appliance consists of: a group of 1-unit Intel Xeon servers, each of equipped with two six-core 2.93&amp;nbsp;GHz processors and two [[solid-state drive]]s for operating system and [[swap space]]; a common [[storage area network]]; and a set of [[InfiniBand]] and [[Ethernet]] switches.&lt;ref name="linuxj"&gt;{{cite web
 | url         = http://www.linuxjournal.com/content/oracle-exalogic-elastic-cloud
 | title       = The Oracle Exalogic Elastic Cloud
 | first       = Mitch
 | last        = Frazier
 | quote       = Each 1U "node" in an Exalogic rack consists of two Xeon chips. Each Xeon chip is a 6-core processor running at 2.93 GHz. Each node has redundant InfiniBand connections. Each node also contains two solid-state disks (SSD) for the operating system and for local swap space. An full rack would contain 360 CPU Cores, 2.8 TB (TeraBytes, 1 TB = 1024 GB ) of RAM, 6 TB of SSD, and 60 TB of SAS (Serial Attached SCSI) disk. 
 | date        = 2010-09-20
 | format      = 
 | work        = 
 | publisher   = [[Linux Journal]]
 | accessdate  = 2011-05-29
 | archiveurl  = 
 | archivedate = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A full rack contains 30 server nodes, a half rack, 16, a quarter rack, 8, and an eighth rack, 4. Each server node has installed 96 GB of RAM, 4 [[10 Gbit Ethernet]] cards, and a double Infiniband port. The storage area network for all configurations is similar, with 40 TB of raw space. The vendor's specifications and advertising content usually indicate the total parameters (360 processor kernels and 2.9 TB RAM for full rack).&lt;ref name="hw-spec"&gt;{{cite web
 | url         = http://www.oracle.com/us/products/middleware/oracle-exalogic-x2-2-ds-349921.pdf
 | title       = Oracle Exalogic Elastic Cloud X2-2
 | date        = [[PDF]]
 | format      = 2011-03-15
 | work        = Data Sheet
 | publisher   = [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]]
 | accessdate  = 2011-05-29
 | description = 
 | archiveurl  = 
 | archivedate = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Software ==
Customers have a choice of two 64-bit operating systems to run on the server nodes of the appliance: [[Oracle Enterprise Linux]] version 5.5 or [[Solaris (operating system)|Solaris]] release 11 express.&lt;ref name="linuxj"/&gt; All servers have an installed cluster configuration of [[Oracle WebLogic Server]] and distributed memory cache [[Oracle Coherence]]. To run Java applications on a machine there is a choice of [[HotSpot]] or [[JRockit]]. Management of the appliance is available in the [[Oracle Enterprise Manager]] toolset, which is also pre-installed in the appliance. A transaction monitor [[Tuxedo (software)|Tuxedo]]&lt;ref name="soft-spec"&gt;{{cite web
 | url         = http://www.oracle.com/us/products/middleware/oracle-exalogic-sw-ds-349920.pdf
 | title       = Oracle Exalogic Elastic Cloud Software Data Sheet
 | date        = 2011-03-25
 | format      = [[PDF]]
 | work        = Oracle Data Sheet 
 | publisher   = [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]]
 | accessdate  = 2011-05-29
 | description = 
 | deadurl    = 
 | archiveurl  = 
 | archivedate = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; is optionally supplied.

== Customers ==
Exalogic is deployed by the [[University of Melbourne]], [[Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA) in the United States, [[Amway]], the [[Hyundai Motor Group]], [[Banco de Chile|Bank of Chile]], [[Haier]], and [[Deutsche Post|Deutsche Post DHL]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/12/21/oracle_ellison_exa_cluster_apple_ibm/ Are Oracle's Exadata racks fluffing Apple's iCloud?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.oracle.com/fusionmiddleware/entry/recap_day_1_oracle_highlights OpenWorld Recap Day 1: Innovations in Oracle Fusion Middleware, Exalogic, Cloud Application Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
[[Mark Benioff]], founder of [[Salesforce.com]], presumes that any appliance principally lacks scalability for the end-user compared with the [[IaaS|infrastructure, supplied as service]], and notes that the Exalogic approach is actually a rollback to the obsolete [[Mainframe computer|mainframe]] concept.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url         = http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/12/07/benioff_fires_back_at_ellison/
 | title       = Salesforce's Benioff: 'Ellison flunks vision test'. Oracle dreams of a mainframe past
 | first       = Gavin
 | last        = Clarke
 | date        = 2010-12-07
 | work        = 
 | publisher   = [[The Register]]
 | accessdate  = 2011-05-31
 }}
&lt;cite&gt;"The cloud is not in a box — you don’t have to add more boxes to get scalability, " Benioff said&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Also, commentators have expressed concerns about the appropriateness of placing the word "elastic" in the name,&lt;ref name="rww"&gt;{{cite web
 | url         = http://www.readwriteweb.com/cloud/2010/09/why-the-oracle-exalogic-cloud.php
 | title       = Why the Oracle Exalogic Cloud is Not Elastic
 | first       = Alex
 | last        = Williams
 | date        = 2010-09-30
 | work        = 
 | publisher   = [[ReadWriteWeb]]
 | accessdate  = 2011-05-31
 }}&lt;cite&gt;«Placing the term "Elastic" in the name of this offering is stretching the accepted definition of the term as it relates to cloud computing … You can scale your applications up and down within this solution, but in the end, you are limited to the number of cores, amount or RAM, and size of the storage you purchased…» … «EMC and HP are both making solutions that fit this description … use case ends, those resources are then returned to the common pool to be redeployed, just as they would be in a larger cloud infrastructure»&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; because, despite the ability to load balance, there are obvious computing limits of the box, and those limits cannot be transcended like they should be in a true elastic environment; the same criticism applies to all solutions designed for private cloud computing, in particular, it applies to [[EMC Corporation|EMC]] and [[Hewlett-Packard]] products.&lt;ref name="rww"/&gt; However, any computing environment is a collection of servers, and since many Exalogic machines can be combined, it is not limited to the single box capacity, which may be considered as merely a building block.

== See also ==
* [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]]
* [[Oracle Exadata|Exadata]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{Official website|oracle.com/us/products/middleware/exalogic/|Exalogic Elastic Cloud appliance}}

{{Oracle}}

[[Category:Cloud computing]]</text>
      <sha1>g1he7i12iusvq433yb7kdh7927w28wd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>