<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>PANGAEA (data library)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24810701</id>
    <revision>
      <id>545753620</id>
      <parentid>541143175</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-20T19:16:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 1 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q947684]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{More footnotes|date=February 2013}}
[[File:Pangaea logo hg.png|thumb|The '''PANGAEA logo''' shows the supercontinent Pangaea at about 150 Million years ago in an artistic vision.]]
[[File:Singing iceberg.oga|thumb|An example of the data stored in PANGAEA - an audio recording of a "singing" iceberg, from [[doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.339110]]. Most datasets are much larger.]]

'''PANGAEA - Data Publisher for Earth &amp; Environmental Science''' is a digital [[data library]] and a data publisher for [[earth system science]]. Data can be [[georeference]]d in time (date/time or geological age) and space (latitude, longitude, depth/height).

Scientific data are archived with related metainformation in a relational database ([[Sybase]]) through an editorial system. Data are in [[Open access (publishing)|Open Access]] and are distributed through [[web service]]s in standard formats on the Internet through various search engines and portals. Data set descriptions (metadata) are conform to the [[ISO 19115]] standard and are served in various further formats (e.g. [[Directory Interchange Format]], [[Dublin Core]]). They include a bibliographic citation and are persistently identified using [[Digital Object Identifier]]s (DOI). Identifier provision and long-term availability of data sets via library catalogs is ensured through a cooperation with the [[German National Library of Science and Technology]] (TIB). Retrieval of data sets is provided through a [[full text search]] engine (based on [[Apache Lucene]] / [[panFMP]]). For efficient data compilations a [[data warehouse]] is operated. Data descriptions are available through various protocols ([[OAI-PMH]], [[Web Catalog Service]]).

PANGAEA is hosted by the [[Alfred Wegener Institute for Polar and Marine Research]] (AWI), Bremerhaven and the [[Center for Marine Environmental Sciences]] (MARUM), Bremen in Germany. The system is used by various international research projects from public funding as data repository and by the [[World Data Center for Marine Environmental Sciences]] (WDC-MARE) as long-term archive. The system was initially developed since 1987 and is operational on the Internet since 1995.

The [[MediaWiki]] software is used to operate a [[wiki]] as PANGAEA manual and reference.

== References ==

* Diepenbroek, M., Grobe, H., Reinke, M., Schindler, U., Schlitzer, R., Sieger, R., Wefer, G. (2002) ''PANGAEA - an information system for environmental sciences'', Computers &amp; Geosciences, ''28(10)'', 1201–1210, {{doi|10.1016/S0098-3004(02)00039-0}}.
* König-Langlo, G., Gernandt, H.(2009) ''Compilation of ozonesonde profiles from the Antarctic station Georg-Forster from 1985 to 1992'', Earth System Science Data, ''1'',1-5, {{doi|10.5194/essd-1-1-2009}} (Example of a data publication with PANGAEA, corresponding data set: {{doi|10.1594/PANGAEA.547983}}).

==External links==
* [http://www.pangaea.de/ PANGAEA home page]
* [http://wiki.pangaea.de/ Manual ''PangaWiki'']
* [http://www.wdc-mare.org/ WDC-MARE home page]
* [http://www.awi.de/en Alfred Wegener Institute for Polar and Marine Research] (AWI)
* [http://www.marum.de/en/ Center for Marine Environmental Sciences] (MARUM)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pangaea (Data Library)}}
[[Category:Digital libraries|Digital libraries]]
[[Category:Bibliographic databases]]</text>
      <sha1>h6hybv1ri043g7bcpvbmlmlrwj46l0o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>