<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>ParAccel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22036575</id>
    <revision>
      <id>563263637</id>
      <parentid>552241971</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-07T17:45:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sadads</username>
        <id>563447</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>link [[Adaptive compression]] using [[User:Edward/Find link|Find link]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| company_name   = ParAccel, Inc.
| company_logo   = [[Image:ParAccel-Logo-Oct2011.jpg]]
| company_type   = [[Private company|Private]]
| foundation     = 2005
| location       = [[Campbell, California|Campbell]] and [[San Diego]], [[California]] [[United States]]
| industry       = [[Data Warehousing]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Enterprise Software]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Database Management]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Business Analytics]]
| products       = The ParAccel Analytic Platform&lt;br /&gt;ParAccel Base / Advanced Analytic Packages&lt;br /&gt;Informatica Adaptor for ParAccel
| homepage       = [http://www.paraccel.com/ www.paraccel.com]
}}

'''ParAccel, Inc.''' is a vendor in the analytic platform / analytic database market.  Vendors in this market provide a purpose-built [[database management system]] used for analytics, [[business intelligence|business intelligence (BI)]] and advanced analytics. It has been announced that ParAccel will be acquired by [[Actian]].

==Corporate overview==
ParAccel is a venture-backed company focused on developing solutions to improve performance for data analysis. During its most recent funding round, existing investors were joined by Amazon.com. ParAccel was founded by Barry Zane, the current Chief Technology Officer (CTO).

ParAccel is based in California with offices in [[Campbell, California|Campbell]] and [[San Diego]].

==History==
{{prose|date=October 2012}}
{{refimprove|section|date=August 2012}}
Note: All available press releases can be found on ParAccel's press releases webpage.&lt;ref&gt;www.paraccel.com/news/press-releases.php&lt;/ref&gt;{{rs?|date=August 2012}}
* '''Mid 2005''': Company founded by Barry Zane
* '''Mar 2006''': First angel investors
* '''Aug 2006''': Venture Capital Series "A" investments by Mohr Davidow Ventures, Bay Partners, Tao Venture Partners
* '''Mar 2007''': Bruce Scott (employee #4 of Oracle corp) &amp; Rick Glick (CTO of Teradata) join ParAccel
* '''Oct 2007''': Public product launch of the ParAccel Analytic Database
* '''Dec 2007''': Series "B" VC funding of $20M led by Walden International
* '''Jun 2009''': Series "C" VC funding of $22M led by [[Menlo Ventures]]
* '''Jun 2009''': ParAccel announces version 2.0 of the ParAccel Analytic Database
* '''Feb 2010''': ParAccel announces version 2.5 of the ParAccel Analytic Database
* '''Mar 2010''': Wall Street Journal lists ParAccel as one of The Top 50 Venture Backed Companies&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://graphicsweb.wsj.com/documents/NEXT_BIG_THING/NEXT_BIG_THING.html | work=The Wall Street Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Apr 2010''': ParAccel releases a record-breaking TPC-H 1,000 GB benchmark&lt;ref&gt;http://tpc.org/tpch/results/tpch_result_detail.asp?id=110041101&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Sep 2010''': Charles W. Berger joins ParAccel as CEO
* '''Nov 2010''': ParAccel announces version 3.0 of the ParAccel Analytic Database
* '''Jan 2011''': Paul Zolfaghari (former EVP Worldwide Sales and Operations at MicroStrategy) joins ParAccel as COO
* '''Jan 2011''': ParAccel expands international operations
* '''May 2011''': Minder Cheng Joins Strategic Advisory Board at ParAccel
* '''June 2011''': ParAccel Announces Upgrade to Its Analytics Platform.
* '''June 2011''': ParAccel Selected as a Red Herring Top 100 North America Company.
* '''July 2011''': ParAccel Announces Amazon as Investor in Latest Funding Round.
* '''July 2011''': MicroStrategy and ParAccel to Deliver Analytical Platform for Social and Cloud-Based Applications.
* '''Sept 2011''': ParAccel Collaborates with MicroStrategy for High Performance Cloud and Social Media Analytics.
* '''Oct 2011''': Analytics Leader Paraccel Adds Industry Veterans To Accelerate Growth And Drive Product Innovation.
* '''Nov 2011''': ParAccel Announces Cloud Edition.

==Product offering==
ParAccel currently offers products as part of the ParAccel Analytic Platform - built on the ParAccel Analytic Database (PADB) as a foundation.

;ParAccel Analytic Database (PADB)
ParAccel's DBMS engine is built from the ground up for analytics though the initial optimizer was [[PostgreSQL]].  ParAccel began phasing in a new optimizer (Omne) in release 2.0 and has made significant changes to Omne with V3.0 and V3.1 (released in June 2011).

Other technology features of the ParAccel Analytic Database&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fulltablescan.com/index.php?/archives/155-ParAccel-Update.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* Fully columnar / MPP-based / [[shared nothing architecture]]
* Compiled queries
* [[Adaptive compression]] for columnar data blocks
* A proprietary interconnect protocol to reduce packet loss and improve the performance of inter-node communications
* Integration with SAN (Storage Area Network) technologies from a NetApp, EMC, etc.

;Extensibility Framework
Starting with V3.0, customers could leverage advanced mathematical, statistical and data mining functions within PADB to complement native SQL-based analytics. Customers have the option to build their own custom functions or buy functions "off-the-shelf".  

;Integrated (In-Database) Analytics
ParAccel offers a number of built-in advanced analytic functions (like standard deviation, variance, etc.) while also offering two off-the-shelf Analytic Packages (Base Package and Advanced Package). Additional functions specific to Financial Services are also available. 

;On Demand Integration (ODI) Modules
ParAccel offers ODI modules to leverage analytics and data that lie outside of the ParAccel Analytic Platform. These modules were built using the Extensibility Framework. Therefore customers, partners and 3rd-parties can quickly build their own custom modules. Currently ParAccel offers ODI modules for Teradata, Hadoop (MapReduce), NYSE Technologies and FIX messages.  

;Product / Platform History
In its past, ParAccel initially offered two different analytic database products named AMIGO and MAVERICK.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fulltablescan.com/index.php?/archives/71-Getting-to-Know-ParAccel,-Part-II.html&lt;/ref&gt;  The AMIGO product was designed to accelerate queries directed at an existing data warehouse while leaving the data warehouse as-is.  With the AMIGO product, the existing data warehouse remained as the database of record.  In contrast the MAVERICK product was designed as a stand-alone data store.  ParAccel discontinued the AMIGO product offering in favor of the MAVERICK stand-alone offering which they evolved into the ParAccel Analytic Database (PADB).

==Notable employees==

;Chuck Berger
:Chairman and CEO of ParAccel.
:Industry veteran with 30 years of leadership experience at Nuance, DVDPlay, {{Not a typo|Vicinty}}, AdForce, as well as Apple, and Sun.

;Rick Glick
:VP of Technology &amp; Architecture of ParAccel.
:Seventeen-year veteran of Teradata, and former CTO of Teradata's Database Engineering group.

;Barry Zane
:Founder and current CTO of ParAccel.
:Former VP of Architecture at Netezza Corp (part of founding team), and former CTO of Applix Inc.

;Paul Zolfaghari
:Chief Operating Officer of ParAccel.
:Prior to joining the Company, Mr. Zolfaghari worked for more than eleven years at MicroStrategy, Inc. (Nasdaq: MSTR) where he most recently served as executive vice-president, Worldwide Sales and Operations.

==Competitors==
* [[Greenplum|EMC]]
* [[Vertica|HP]]
* [[Netezza|IBM]]
* [[Oracle Corporation]]
* [[Teradata]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{official website|http://www.paraccel.com/}}

[[Category:Business intelligence]]
[[Category:Data warehousing products]]
[[Category:Software companies based in California]]</text>
      <sha1>7couli2u5bmd4h9aw34lyc4ty9u1u7r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>