<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Pentaho</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25598358</id>
    <revision>
      <id>561891980</id>
      <parentid>561891836</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-27T23:21:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>François Robere</username>
        <id>18144528</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>/* Community Driven, Open-Source Pentaho Server Plugins */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{tooshort|date=December 2012}}
{{external links|date=December 2012}}
{{advert|date=December 2012}}
}}

{{Infobox software
| name = Pentaho Business Intelligence
| logo = [[File:Pentaho Corporation 2012 Logo with motto.jpg|frameless]]
| screenshot =
| caption =
| author =
| developer = Pentaho Corporation
| released =
| latest release version = Business Analytics Suite 4.8.0/ November, 2012
| latest release date =
| latest preview version =
| latest preview date =
| operating system = [[Windows]], [[Linux]], [[Mac OS X]]
| platform = [[Java (software platform)]]
| genre = [[Business intelligence]]
| license = Pentaho Community Edition (CE): [[Apache 2 License|Apache]] version 2.0; Pentaho Enterprise Edition (EE): Commercial License
| website = [http://www.pentaho.com www.pentaho.com]
|
}}

'''Pentaho''' was founded in 2004 by five founders.
&lt;ref name="computerworlduk"/&gt;&lt;ref name="informationweek-grimes"/&gt; It offers a suite of [[open source]] [[Business Intelligence]] (BI) products called Pentaho Business Analytics providing [[data integration]], [[OLAP|OLAP services]], reporting, [[Dashboards (management information systems)|dashboarding]], [[data mining]] and [[Extract, transform, load|ETL]] capabilities.&lt;ref name = "ovum-sheina"/&gt; Pentaho is headquartered in Orlando, FL, USA. &lt;ref name = "sfbt"/&gt;

== Overview ==
The Pentaho suite consists of two offerings, an enterprise and community edition.  The enterprise edition contains extra features not found in the community edition. The enterprise edition is obtained through an annual subscription and includes extra support services.  Pentaho's core offering is frequently enhanced by add-on products, usually in the form of plugins, from the company itself and also the broader community of users and enthusiasts.  The table below summarizes the most popular products and plugins in the Pentaho ecosystem.

=== Server Applications ===
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Product !! Offering !! Type !! Recent version !!Description
|-
|'''Pentaho BI Platform''' || EE, CE || Server Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/pentaho/files/Business%20Intelligence%20Server/4.8.0-stable/ 4.8.0] || Commonly referred to as the BI Platform, and recently renamed Business Analytics Platform (BA Platform), makes up the core software piece that hosts content created both in the server itself through plugins or files published to the server from the desktop applications.  It includes features for managing security, running reports, displaying dashboards, report bursting, scripted business rules, OLAP analysis and scheduling out of the box.  &lt;br&gt;Commercial plugins from Pentaho expand out-of-the-box features.  A few open-source plugin projects also expand capabilities of the server.  The Pentaho BA Platform runs in the Apache [[Application_server#Java_application_servers|Java Application Server]].  It can be embedded into other Java Application Servers.

|-
| '''Pentaho Analysis Services (Mondrian)''' || EE, CE || Server Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/mondrian/files/ 3.5.0] ||Pentaho Analysis Services, codenamed [[Mondrian OLAP server|Mondrian]],  is an [[open source]] [[Online analytical processing|OLAP]] (online analytical processing) [[Server (computing)|server]], written in [[Java (programming language)|Java]].
It supports the [[MultiDimensional eXpressions|MDX]] (multidimensional expressions) query language and the [[XML for Analysis]] and [http://www.olap4j.org olap4j] interface specifications.  It reads from [[SQL]] and other data sources and aggregates data in a memory cache.  Mondrian can be run separately from the Pentaho BI Platform, but is always bundled with the platform itself in both EE and CE versions.

|-
| '''Pentaho Dashboard Designer (PDD)''' || EE || Server Plugin || 4.8-GA || A commercial plugin provided to enterprise edition (EE) subscribers.  It allows users to create [[Dashboards (management information systems)|dashboards]], which are collections of other content components displayed together with the goal of providing a centralized view of [[Key performance indicator| key performance indicators (KPI)s]] and other business data movements, letting users monitor them and make decisions.  Content components are usually individual [[Information graphics]], tables, OLAP views or reports.  The plugin simplifies dashboard creation through the use of layout templates, drag-and-drop interaction and a [[GUI]] for providing parameters and inputs to dashboard components.

|-
| '''Pentaho Analysis (Analyzer) (PAZ)''' || EE || Server Plugin || 4.8-GA || The Pentaho Analyzer plugin provides an advanced web based, drag-and-drop OLAP viewer. It allows a user to visually create MDX queries by dragging parts of a previously defined Mondrian OLAP schema onto a canvas, where other activities can take place like filtering, sorting, creating calculated members from other measures, exporting the result table to PDF or MS Excel, and optionally graphing the data.  It is also known to work on Apple iPads by using the Safari web browser.
|-
| '''Pentaho Interactive Reporting (PIR)''' || EE || Server Plugin || 4.8-GA || This plugin enables users to create [[Ad-hoc]] reports in a visual drag-and-drop fashion.
|-
| '''Pentaho Data Access Wizard''' ||EE,CE|| Server Plugin || 4.8-GA || This plugin is bundled with all servers and allows users to create new data sources for use throughout the system from other databases or CSV files uploaded to the server while using a setup wizard.  During the steps of creating a datasource users also are given a chance to create a data model describing how columns or fields relate to each other creating hierarchies of relationships like Time: Year, Quarters, Months, Weeks and Product Division, Category, Type etc.  The resultant model is used by Mondrian and any other plugin like Analyzer or Saiku to create new queries against the newly created data source.  This component is part of what Pentaho introduces as agile BI, which simply means having a way to start from basic data and quickly iterate through steps to discover the proper way to structure, study and present the data.&lt;ref name="pentahodataaccess"&gt;Michael Terallo, Pentaho [http://www.pentahoevalcenter.com/content-creation-delivery/data-access-wizard/ Data Access Wizard] Retrieved July 29, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''Pentaho Mobile''' ||EE|| Server Piece || 4.8-GA || A new addition since 4.5-GA suite that is a user interface adapted for use with the Apple iPad.  It exposes all of the major functionality of OLAP analysis and running of reports and dashboards that allow greater interaction on a small, touch screen. Mobile also adds features for bookmarking favorite content for easy access and the concept of opening several pieces of content in tabs.
|}

=== Desktop / Client Applications ===
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Product !! Offering !! Type !! Recent version !!Description
|-
| '''Pentaho Data Integration (PDI)'''|| EE, CE || Desktop Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/pentaho/files/Data%20Integration/4.4.0-stable/ 4.4.0-stable] || Pentaho Data Integration, codenamed Kettle, consists of a core data integration (ETL) engine, and [[GUI]] applications that allow the user to define data integration jobs and transformations. It supports deployment on single node computers as well as on a cloud, or cluster.

|-
| '''Pentaho for Big Data''' || EE, CE || PDI Plugin || N/A || Pentaho for Big Data is a data integration tool based on [[Pentaho Data Integration]].&lt;ref name="pbd1"&gt;Surya Mukherjee, Ovum.  "[http://ovum.com/2012/03/08/pentaho-expands-big-data-coverage/ Pentaho expands coverage for Big Data]."  March 8, 2012.  Retrieved April 11, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  It allows executing [[Extract, transform, load|ETL]] jobs in and out of big data environments such as Apache [[Hadoop]] or Hadoop distributions such as Amazon, Cloudera, EMC Greenplum, MapR, and Hortonworks.&lt;ref name="pbd2"&gt;James Kobielus, Forrester Research. "[http://www.forrester.com/The+Forrester+Wave+Enterprise+Hadoop+Solutions+Q1+2012/fulltext/-/E-RES60755 The Forrester Wave:  Enterprise Hadoop Solutions]." February 2, 2012.  Retrieved May 10, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  It also supports [[NoSQL]] data sources such as [[MongoDB]] and [[HBase]].&lt;ref name="pbd3"&gt;David Menninger, Ventana Research. "[http://www.ventanaresearch.com/blog/commentblog.aspx?id=1577 Pentaho 4 Unites Enterprise Business intelligence and Data Integration]." June 22, 2011.  Retrieved April 8, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

|-
| '''Pentaho Report Designer''' || EE, CE || Desktop Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/pentaho/files/Report%20Designer/3.9.1-stable/ 3.9.1-stable] || Pentaho Report Designer is a visual, banded report writer.  Features include using subreports, charts and graphs.  It can query and use data from many sources including [[SQL]], [[MultiDimensional eXpressions|MDX]], Community Data Access, scripting, static table definitions and more. It consists of a core reporting engine, capable of generating reports based on an [[XML]] definition file stored in a [[Zip (file format)]] with a .PRPT extension. Many tools have been developed surrounding the reporting engine, including [[GUI]] designers and ad-hoc wizards that guide the user through a step-by-step process of creating a report, using solely graphical tools without the need to write any code.

|-
| '''Pentaho Data Mining''' || EE, CE || Desktop Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/weka/files/3.6]  ||Pentaho Data Mining used the Waikato Environment for Knowledge Analysis ([[Weka (machine learning)|Weka]]) to search data for patterns.  [[Weka (machine learning)|Weka]] consists of machine learning algorithms for a broad set of data mining tasks.&lt;ref name="weka4"&gt;Nikos Mastorakis, Valeria Mladenov and Vassiliki Kontargyri. "[http://books.google.de/books?id=avPz1cUPlKgC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=Proceedings%20of%20the%20European%20Computing%20Conference%2C&amp;pg=PA789#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Proceedings of the European Computing Conference]." Heidelberg, Germany:  Springer Science and Business Media, 2009. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special%3ABookSources&amp;isbn=9780387848136 ISBN 978-0387848136]. p. 789. Retrieved July 11, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  It contains functions for data processing, regression analysis, classification methods, cluster analysis, and visualization.  Based on the discovered patterns, users can predict future trends.&lt;ref name="weka5"&gt;Ed Woord, FLOSS FOR SCIENCE. "[http://www.floss4science.com/machine-learning-with-weka-mark-hall/ Machine Learning with WEKA:  AN Interview with Mark Hall]." July 1, 2012.  Retrieved July 25, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''Pentaho Metadata Editor (PME)''' || EE, CE || Desktop Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/pentaho/files/Pentaho Metadata/ 4.8] || The metadata editor is used to create business models and act as an abstraction layer from the underlying data sources.  The resulting metadata models are used by Pentaho Interactive Reporting, Saiku Reporting, and Pentaho's legacy AD-HOC reporting plugin applications to create reports within the BA server without using any of the other external desktop applications.
|-
| '''Pentaho Aggregate Designer (PAD)''' || EE, CE || Desktop Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/mondrian/files/aggregation%20designer/ 1.5.0] || Aggregate Designer operates on Pentaho Analysis (Mondrian) XML schema files and the database with the underlying tables described by the schema to generate precalculated, aggregated answers to speed up analysis work and MDX queries executed against Mondrian.  This is accomplished by the software examining the hierarchies described in the schema and the measures also defined there and generating SQL which would result in the creation of tables storing those answers away for future use by Mondrian.  After using the software to generate these aggregate tables, the original Mondrian XML schema file describing the OLAP cube is modified to reference the precomputed results.

|-
| '''Pentaho Schema Workbench (PSW)''' || EE, CE || Desktop Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/mondrian/files/schema%20workbench/ 3.5.0] || Pentaho Schema Workbench provides a graphical interface for designing OLAP cubes for Pentaho Analysis (Mondrian).  The schema created is stored as a regular XML file on disk.  It is not necessary to use the Schema Workbench to create schema, but it is often helpful for beginners and even experts who need go inspect a cube visually and come up to speed with how to maintain or extend it.

|-
| '''Pentaho Design Studio (PDS)''' || EE, CE || Desktop Application || [http://sourceforge.net/projects/pentaho/files/Design%20Studio/ 4.0] || The Pentaho BA Server supports special XML scripts called xactions to implement business logic and other forms of automation in the platform.  Design Studio is a modified version of the Eclipse Development Environment with a plugin designed to understand the components supported by xaction scripts.  Xactions are very powerful, and useful, but sometimes prove difficult to troubleshoot because of the low-level way they interact with parts of the BA server.  Developers are starting to use Pentaho Data Integration transformation files to carry out automation and business logic tasks.  The transformations can be run directly by the BA Server and visually debugged in Pentaho Data Integration (PDI) and are quickly gaining favor in the community over xactions. It is a small leap to imagine PDI transformations will eventually replace xactions entirely.

|}

=== Community Driven, Open-Source Pentaho Server Plugins ===
All of these plugins function with Pentaho Enterprise Edition (EE) and Pentaho Community Edition (CE).
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Product !! Type !! Recent version !!Description
|-
| '''Ctools''' || Server Plugin Suite || Various || Known as the ''Community'' tools, it includes a growing array of features usually contained in a package with an abbreviated name where the first C always stands for community and simultaneously represents its status as being both free of cost and open-source.  The tools are produced and managed by Webdetails.&lt;ref name="webdetails" /&gt;  Documentation on the tools is found at [http://ctools.webdetails.org/ ctools.webdetails.org]. Most often the Ctools suite is installed by using a linux script.,&lt;ref name = "ctoolsinstaller" /&gt; but there are plans in an upcoming release to have a package manager included in the BA Server that helps with installation.&lt;ref name="baservermarketplace"&gt;Will, Gorman Pentaho Wiki [http://wiki.pentaho.com/display/PMOPEN/Pentaho+BI+Server+Marketplace+Plugin "Pentaho BI Server Marketplace Plugin] February 17, 2012, Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''Community Charting Components (CCC)''' || Server Plugin || Various || A charting library on top of Protovis,&lt;ref name="protovis" /&gt; a very powerful free and open-source visualization toolkit.  The aim of CCC is to provide developers with a way to include into their dashboards the basic chart types without losing the main principle:  Extensibility.  The charts created with CCC become components that appear in dashboards.
|-
| '''Community Build Framework (CBF)''' || Build Script Framework || 3.7 || Focused on a multi-project/ multi-environment scenario, the Community Build Framework (CBF) provide a way to set up and deploy Pentaho-based applications.  It is an Apache Ant, Java build-script that allows a user to create a template of their Pentaho BA Server installation, including patches and any customizations or special content and roll it out quickly.  It can help migrations to new versions of the BA Server, and with rapidly producing customized Pentaho servers for clients.

|-
| '''Community Data Access (CDA)''' || Server Plugin || [http://cda.webdetails.org/?q=content/download latest] || Acts as a common layer for accessing data on the Pentaho BA server.  CDA files can contain SQL, MDX, Pentaho Data Integration transformation files, scripted data sources and more.&lt;ref name="cda" /&gt; CDA also provides a [[REST]] API interface for directly calling the Pentaho BA server and receiving the results of a query back as JSON, XML, XLS, HTML or CSV. The default is JSON.&lt;ref name="cdadoquery"&gt;[http://cda.webdetails.org/?q=content/documentation-web-api-reference CDA web API reference: doQuery] Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; HTML output makes it easy for MS Excel users to perform Web queries and pull results directly into an Excel workbook without additional software in the middle.  CDA comes bundled in all of Pentaho's servers.
|-
| '''Community Data Browser (CDB)''' || Server Plugin ||  || Community Data Browser uses a visual OLAP browser called Saiku to create a query which can be used by [[R (programming language)|R]] for performing analytics on the result set.
|-
| '''Community Distributed Cache (CDC)''' || Server Plugin || [http://cdc.webdetails.org/?q=content/download latest] ||
CDC stands for Community Distributed Cache and allows for high-performance, scalable and distributed memory clustering cache based on Hazelcast for both CDA and Mondrian. CDC is a pentaho plugin that provides the following features:
* CDA distributed cache support
* Mondrian distributed cache support
* Ability to switch between default and CDC cache for cda and mondrian
* Gracefully handles adding / removing new cache nodes
* Allows to selectively clear cache of specific CDE dashboards
* Allows to selectively clear cache of specific schemas / cubes / dimensions of Mondrian cubes
* Provides an API to clean the cache from the outside (e.g.: after running ETL)
* Provides a view over cluster status
* Supports multiple pentaho servers using the same cluster (e.g.: stage and production)
* Supports several memory configuration options
|-
| '''Community Data Generator (CDG)''' || PDI Jobs || N/A ||CDG is a data warehouse generator that helps create sample data for creating proof of concept dashboards.  Given the definition of dimensions that we want, CDG will randomize data within certain parameters and output 3 different things:
* Database and table for the fact table.
* A file with inserts for the fact table.
* Mondrian schema file to be used within Pentaho.
|-
| '''Community Data Validation (CDV)''' || Server Plugin ||  || CDV adds the ability of creating validation tests on the Pentaho BA server for the purpose of verifying both the integrity of the server itself and also the data being used by the server.
|-
| '''Community Graphics Generator (CGG)''' || Server Plugin || [http://cgg.webdetails.org/?q=content/download latest] ||
Pentaho Plugin that allows the user to export CCC/CDE charts as images, enabling the inclusion of CDE charts inside Pentaho Report Designer reports. In short, this plugin is able to render server-side exactly the same chart that is rendered on the browser by CDE/CDF.
&lt;br&gt;
Main characteristics:
* Executes a CCC chart definition server-side and outputs the chart as an image or a svg file.
* Exposes the chart as an url - use your chart exports wherever you can embed a link.
* Seamless integration with CDE.
* Can also be used to render custom-made svg transformations and javascript files server side and output them as images.
|-
|'''Community Dashboard Editor (CDE)''' || Server Plugin || [http://cde.webdetails.org/?q=content/download 20120719] || CDE is an advanced user tool for creating dashboards in the Pentaho BA server.  CDE and the technology underneath (CDF, CDA and CCC) allows to develop and deploy dashboards in the Pentaho platform in a fast and effective way.  It is not as user friendly as Pentaho Dashboard Designer plugin, but enables users to create much more sophisticated designs.
|-
|'''Community Dashboard Framework (CDF)''' || Server Plugin || 4.8-stable || CDF comes bundled in all of Pentaho's servers. It is the framework used both by CDE and Pentaho's Dashboard Designer to create dashboards on the system.&lt;ref name="cdf"&gt;[http://cdf.webdetails.org/ CDF Documentation]&lt;/ref&gt;
* It separates logic (JavaScript) of the presentation (HTML, CSS)
* It features a life cycle with components interacting with each other
* It uses AJAX
* It is extensible, which gives the users a high level of customization
* Advanced users can extend the library of components.
* They also can insert their own snippets of JavaScript and jQuery code.
|-
|'''Community Startup Tabs (CST)''' || Server Plugin || [http://cst.webdetails.org/?q=content/download 1.0] || Out of the box a Pentaho BA Server comes with a user interface called the ''Pentaho User Console'' (PUC) which show all content by opening tabs within itself.  Community Startup Tabs provide an easy way to define and show specialized content to users by automatically opening tabs when they sign in.&lt;ref name="cst"&gt;[http://cst.webdetails.org/ CST Documentation]&lt;/ref&gt;
* it allows you to define different startup tabs for each user that logs into the PUC. .it is easy to configure.
* it allows to define startup tabs based on user names or user roles.
* for the definition of the startup tabs it allows you to specify user names or roles using regular expressions.
|-
| '''Saiku''' || Server Plugin || [http://analytical-labs.com/ 2.4] || Saiku is a modular open-source analysis suite offering lightweight OLAP which remains easily embeddable, extendable and configurable.  It is similar in form and function to the Pentaho Analyzer Plugin.

A RESTful server connects to existing OLAP systems, which then powers user-friendly, intuitive analytics via a lightweight JQuery-based frontend.
|-
| '''Saiku-Reporting''' || Server Plugin || [http://mgiepz.github.com/saiku-reporting 1.0-GA] || A rapidly developing AD-HOC reporting tool, similar to Pentaho's Interactive Reporting Plugin.&lt;br&gt;Key Features:
* Drag &amp; Drop Report-Design
* Export to: PDF,CSV,XLS,CDA,PRPT
* Uses Pentaho Report Designer PRPT-Templates
* Grouping
* Aggregation
* Totals
* OpenFormula Support

|}

== Social Media Communication ==
&lt;br&gt;
'''Official Sources'''
* [http://blog.pentaho.com Pentaho's Official Blog]
** The blog is a good resource to read about Pentaho's corporate direction, current commercial development focus and company philosophy.
* [http://www.pentahoevalcenter.com/ Pentaho's Official Evaluation Center]
** Pentaho employees post video demonstrations and tutorials of accomplishing tasks frequently found to add value for companies pursuing enterprise solutions.  Frequently, interesting and educational usage of the commercial features of the suite are on display.
* [http://infocenter.pentaho.com/ Pentaho's Official Documentation Center]
** Previously known as the 'Knowledge Base' and included only in commercial offerings, it is now fully open to the public.  The information helps users come up to speed on Pentaho products and understand what is required to achieve and manage an enterprise grade deployment.
* [http://forums.pentaho.com Pentaho Community Forums]
** Enterprise subscribers, product evaluators, hobbyists, developers et al. post messages and respond to questions, learning quests and problems encountered while using or creating solutions with all of the products in the suite.  Everyone is welcome to read and post.
* [http://wiki.pentaho.com/ Pentaho Community Wiki]
** The Pentaho Community Wiki provides not only product configuration and usage information, but also developer oriented information to help newcomers acquire the source code, set up a development environment, understand scrum development, see current development objectives, and understand the architecture of the business analytics platform and surrounding products.
* [http://wiki.pentaho.com/display/COM/Previous+Community+Technical+WebEx+Recordings Pentaho Community Techical WebEx Recordings]
* [http://jira.pentaho.com Pentaho Enhancement and Bug Tracking System]
* Twitter: @pentaho
&lt;br&gt;
'''Prominent Pentaho Figures and Social Media'''
* '''Quentin Gallivan''', Pentaho CEO (2011–present)&lt;ref name="2011ceo"&gt;Pentaho, [http://www.pentaho.com/press-room/releases/pentaho-appoints-quentin-gallivan-as-ceo/ "Pentaho Appoints Quentin Gallivan As CEO"] October 4, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pentaholeadership"&gt;Pentaho, [http://www.pentaho.com/about/leadership/ "Meet the Pentaho Team"] Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Richard Daley''', Pentaho Chief Strategy Officer (2011–present)&lt;ref name="2011ceo" /&gt; Pentaho founder and CEO from (2004 to Oct 2011)&lt;ref name="2011ceo" /&gt;
* '''James Dixon''', Pentaho Chief Geek (CTO)&lt;ref name="pentaholeadership" /&gt;&lt;ref name="jamesdixon"&gt;James, Dixon, [http://jamesdixon.wordpress.com/about "James Dixon's Blog - Dixon's thoughts on commercial open source and open source business intelligence"] Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
** Blog: [http://jamesdixon.wordpress.com http://jamesdixon.wordpress.com]
* '''Will Gorman''', Pentaho VP of Engineering and author of "Pentaho Reporting 3.5 for Java Developers"&lt;ref name="pentahoreporting35"&gt;Will, Gorman, Packt Publishing, [http://www.packtpub.com/pentaho-reporting-3-5-for-java-developers/book?mid/070909sc6dlh "Pentaho Reporting 3.5 for Java Developers"], Published September 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
** Blog: [http://www.willgorman.com http://www.willgorman.com]
* '''Julian Hyde''', founder and developer of the Pentaho Analysis (Mondrian open-source OLAP engine)&lt;ref name="julianhyde"&gt;Julian Hyde, [http://julianhyde.blogspot.com/ "Julian Hyde on Streaming Data, Open Source OLAP. And stuff."] Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
** Blog: [http://julianhyde.blogspot.com http://julianhyde.blogspot.com]
* '''Matt Casters''', founder and developer of Pentaho Data Integration (PDI/Kettle)&lt;ref name="mattcasters"&gt;Matt Casters, [http://www.ibridge.be/?page_id=2 "matt casters on data integration"] Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; and author of the book "Pentaho Kettle Solutions"&lt;ref name="pentahokettlesolutions"&gt;Matt Casters, Bouman, Dongen, Wiley [http://www.wiley.com/WileyCDA/WileyTitle/productCd-0470635177.html Pentaho Kettle Solutions: Building Open Source ETL Solutions with Pentaho Data Integration"] September 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
** Blog: [http://www.ibridge.be/ http://www.ibridge.be]
* '''Thomas Morgner''', founder and developer of Pentaho Report Designer (PRD)&lt;ref name="thomasmorgner"&gt;Thomas, Morgner, [http://www.sherito.org/ "Reporting Tales - Pentaho Reporting Tips and Tricks from the Author"] Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
** Blog: [http://www.sherito.org/ http://www.sherito.org/]
* '''Roland Bouman''', Pentaho Software Engineer&lt;ref name="rolandbouman"&gt;Roland, Bouman, [http://rpbouman.blogspot.com/ "Roland Bouman's blog"] Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; and author of the book "Pentaho Solutions"&lt;ref name="pentahosolutions"&gt;Roland Bouman, Dongen, Wiley, [http://www.wiley.com/WileyCDA/WileyTitle/productCd-0470484322.html "Pentaho Solutions: Business Intelligence and Data Warehousing with Pentaho and MySQL"], August 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
** Blog: [http://rpbouman.blogspot.com http://rpbouman.blogspot.com]
* '''Slawomir Chodnicki''', Pentaho Enterprise Engineer
** Author of many tutorials
** PDI Transformation Steps (Google Analytics Plugin,&lt;ref name = "slawogoogleanalytics"/&gt; Excel Writer Plugin,&lt;ref name = "slawoexcelwriter" /&gt; EDI2XML Plugin,&lt;ref name = "slawoedi2xml"/&gt; Ruby Scripting Plugin&lt;ref name = "slaworuby"/&gt;)
** Blog: [http://type-exit.org/adventures-with-open-source-bi http://type-exit.org/adventures-with-open-source-bi]

'''Notable Pentaho Partners and Community Members'''
* '''Pedro Alves''', founder and CEO of Webdetails and originator and maintainer of the Ctools suite of Pentaho Plugins.
** Blog: [http://pedroalves-bi.blogspot.com/ http://pedroalves-bi.blogspot.com/]
** Company: [http://www.webdetails.pt http://www.webdetails.pt]
* '''Ricardo Pires''', BI Division Manager &amp; Pentaho Official Trainer @ Xpand IT - Originator and maintainer of the FusionCharts Pentaho Plugin.
** Linkedin: [http://www.linkedin.com/pub/ricardo-pires/1/537/b28/ http://www.linkedin.com/pub/ricardo-pires]
** Company: [http://www.xpand-it.com http://www.xpand-it.com]
* '''Tom Barber''', Technical Director of Meteorite BI and co-originator of Saiku the graphical OLAP browser Pentaho Plugin.
** Blog: [http://themagicaltrout.wordpress.com/ http://themagicaltrout.wordpress.com]
** Blog: [http://pentahomusings.blogspot.com/ http://pentahomusings.blogspot.com/]
** Company: [http://www.meteorite.bi/ http://www.meteorite.bi]
* '''Paul Stoellberger''', lead developer and co-originator of Saiku the graphic OLAP browser Pentaho Plugin.&lt;ref name="paulstoellberger"&gt;Paul, Stoellberger, Saiku, [http://analytical-labs.com/downloads/rockstar_analytics_pcm11.pdf "Paul Stoellberger - Pentaho Community Meetup 2011 / Frascati"] Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Jos van Dongen''', co-author of two popular books, Pentaho Solutions&lt;ref name="pentahosolutions" /&gt; and Pentaho Kettle Solutions&lt;ref name="pentahokettlesolutions" /&gt;
* '''Prashant Raju''', community member and developer of Saiku the graphic OLAP browser Pentaho Plugin&lt;ref name="paulstoellberger"/&gt;
** Blog: [http://www.prashantraju.com http://www.prashantraju.com]
* '''Francisco Javier Martínez Guzmán''', blogger with illustrative tutorials for installing the Pentaho Suite and creating a CDE dashboard with bullet charts
** Blog: [http://interestingittips.wordpress.com http://interestingittips.wordpress.com]

== Licensing ==
Pentaho follows a [[commercial open source]] business model.  It provides two different editions of Pentaho Business Analytics:  a community edition and an enterprise edition.  The enterprise edition needs to be purchased on a [[subscription]] model.  The subscription model includes support, services, and product enhancements via annual subscription.&lt;ref name="lic1"&gt;Torben Pedersen and Mukesh Mohania. "[http://books.google.de/books?id=6292rhpRJWMC&amp;lpg=PP12&amp;dq=Open%20Source%20BI%20Platforms%3A%20A%20Functional%20and%20Architectural%20Comparison&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Data Warehousing and Knowledge Discovery]." Heidelberg, Germany:  Springer Science and Business Media, 2009. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special%3ABookSources&amp;isbn=9783642037290 ISBN 978-3642037290]. p.296-298.  Retrieved April 6, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  The enterprise edition is available under a commercial license.  There are three variants of the enterprise edition:  Basic, Professional, and Enterprise.  The community edition is a free open source product licensed under the [[GNU General Public License]] version 2.0 (GPLv2), [[GNU Lesser General Public License]] version 2.0 (LGPLv2), and [[Mozilla Public License]] 1.1 (MPL 1.1).

== Accolades and Awards ==
* InfoWorld Bossie Award 2008, 2009, 2010, 2011, 2012 &lt;ref name="BOSSIE Award"&gt;[http://www.infoworld.com/slideshow/65165/bossie-awards-2012-the-best-open-source-applications-202530#slide22/InfoWorld] Retrieved Oct 1, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ventana Research Leadership Award 2010 for StoneGate Senior Care [http://www.ventanaresearch.com/resources/resources.aspx?id=508]
* CRN Emerging Technology Vendor 2010[http://www.crn.com/news/channel-programs/225700504/2010-emerging-vendors-by-technology-sector.htm?pgno=6]
* ROI Awards 2012 - [http://nucleusresearch.com/research/roi-case-studies/roi-case-study-pentaho-stonegate/ Nucleus Research]
* More awards on [http://www.pentaho.com/about/awards/ Pentaho's Awards Page]

==See also==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[Nutch]] - An effort to build an open source search engine based on [[Lucene]] and Hadoop, also created by Doug Cutting
* [[Datameer]] Analytics Solution (DAS) - data source integration, storage, analytics engine and visualization
* [[Apache Accumulo]] - Secure Big Table
* [[HBase]] - [[BigTable]]-model database
* [[Hypertable]] - HBase alternative
* [[MapReduce]] - Google's fundamental data filtering algorithm
* [[Apache Mahout]] - Machine Learning algorithms implemented on Hadoop
* [[Apache Cassandra]] - A column-oriented database that supports access from Hadoop
* [[HPCC]] - [[LexisNexis]] Risk Solutions High Performance Computing Cluster
* [[Sector/Sphere]] - Open source distributed storage and processing
* [[Cloud computing]]
* [[Big data]]
* [[Data Intensive Computing]]

== References ==
&lt;references&gt;
&lt;ref name="computerworlduk"&gt;Glyn Moody, Computerworld UK. [http://blogs.computerworlduk.com/open-enterprise/2010/05/how-do-you-make-a-pentaho/index.htm "How Do You Make a Pentaho?"] May 5, 2010. Retrieved April 9, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="informationweek-grimes"&gt;Seth Grimes, InformationWeek. [http://www.informationweek.com/news/software/enterprise_apps/164900429 "Open-Source BI Startup Pentaho Makes Debut."] June 16, 2005. Retrieved April 5, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "ovum-sheina"&gt;Madan Sheina, Ovum. [http://ovum.com/research/pentaho-pentaho-bi-suite-enterprise-edition "Pentaho BI Suite Enterprise Edition."] September 15, 2010. Retrieved February 12, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "sfbt"&gt;Steven Brown, San Francisco Business Times. [http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/news/2011/10/04/pentaho-hires-quentin-gallivan-ceo.html "Florida’s Pentaho hires Quentin Gallivan as CEO in San Francisco."] October 4, 2011. Retrieved April 12, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "webdetails"&gt;[http://www.webdetails.pt Webdetails Consulting Company, Portugal]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "ctoolsinstaller"&gt;Pedro, Alves [http://pedroalves-bi.blogspot.com/2011/12/back-to-basics-step-by-step-pentaho.html "Back to basics: Step by step Pentaho + Ctools installation"] December 15, 2011, Retrieved July 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "protovis"&gt;Stanford Visualization Group, Protovis [http://mbostock.github.com/protovis/ http://mbostock.github.com/protovis/]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "cda"&gt;[http://cda.webdetails.org/?q=content/documentation-data-accesses CDA Documentation] Retrieved July 26, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "slawogoogleanalytics"&gt;Slawomir Chodnicki - [http://type-exit.org/adventures-with-open-source-bi/kettle-plugins/google-analytics-plugin-for-kettle/ Google Analytics Plugin]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "slawoexcelwriter"&gt;Slawomir Chodnicki - [http://type-exit.org/adventures-with-open-source-bi/kettle-plugins/excel-writer-plugin/ Excel Writer Plugin]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "slawoedi2xml"&gt;Slawomir Chodnicki - [http://type-exit.org/adventures-with-open-source-bi/kettle-plugins/edi2xml-plugin/ Edi2Xml Plugin]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = "slaworuby"&gt;Slawomir Chodnicki - [http://type-exit.org/adventures-with-open-source-bi/kettle-plugins/ruby-scripting-plugin/ Ruby Scripting Plugin]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.pentaho.com/ Pentaho website]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=cwNYPgAACAAJ&amp;dq=Pentaho&amp;ei=wQw6S77XIpO2NeKtrasF&amp;cd=1 Pentaho Solutions: Business Intelligence and Data Warehousing with Pentaho]
* [http://drdobbs.com/database/230800051 Introduction to OLAP4J] Programming introduction on Dr. Dobb's
* [http://www.einfobuzz.com/?s=Pentaho BI, Data warehousing, ETL examples using Pentaho]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=79bL9IfYLUQC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;dq=Pentaho&amp;ei=wQw6S77XIpO2NeKtrasF&amp;cd=5#v=onepage&amp;q=Pentaho&amp;f=false Data Warehousing]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=yud7PgAACAAJ&amp;dq=Pentaho&amp;ei=wQw6S77XIpO2NeKtrasF&amp;cd=4 Pentaho Reporting 3.5 for Java Developers]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=fyB6Rj20Z-0C&amp;dq=Pentaho&amp;lr=&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Ogrs 2009]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=SVpWyBsglAAC&amp;dq=Pentaho&amp;lr=&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Data Warehouse]
* [http://www.informationweek.com/news/software/open_source/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=206904925 Startup Of The Week: Pentaho Offers Opens Source BI Alternative]

[[Category:Business intelligence]]
[[Category:Free business software]]
[[Category:Free reporting software]]
[[Category:ETL tools]]</text>
      <sha1>82vevonv1ycfu3vp28qt7o9ebafqymq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>