<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Peyman Faratin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3028895</id>
    <revision>
      <id>530170668</id>
      <parentid>522824078</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-12-28T17:48:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>80.184.114.195</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox scientist
| image                   = 
| name                    = Dr. Peyman Faratin
| birth_date              = {{Birth date |1965|9|16|mf=y}}
| birth_place             = Tehran, Iran
| death_date              = 
| death_place             = 
| residence               = New York, USA
| citizenship             = US and UK
| nationality             = [[United States|American]]
| ethnicity               =
| field                   = [[Computer Science]]
| work_institution        = RobustLinks
| alma_mater              = MIT, London University
| known_for               = [[Negotiation algorithms]]
| footnotes               = 
}}
'''Peyman Faratin''' is the founder of Robust Links, an Internet company building algorithms for creating and processing a knowledge graph.

== Background ==
Peyman completed his PhD in computer science under the supervision of Prof. Nicholas R. Jennings and Prof. Carles Sierra. He made significant contributions in the area of artificial intelligence, particularly to automated negotiation in [[multi-agent system]]s. He was then a research scientist at [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]]'s [[CSAIL|Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence (CSAIL)]] laboratory, working with [[David D. Clark]] in the Advanced Network Architecture group.

Peyman has over eighteen years of experience in design and implementation of online marketplaces. He graduated from University of London (EECS department) in 2000 completing his doctoral thesis on algorithms for online bargaining and auction mechanisms, with application to business process management and supply chain management in telecommunication domains. Between 2000-2008 he was a researcher at MIT (Computer Science and AI Lab and Sloan School of Management) working with David Clark (the chief Internet protocol architect between 81-89) on design, analysis and implementation of various online market mechanisms for multi-scaled provisioning, control and access problems to IP networks. Work included design of various markets at both layer 3 and 7 applications. Dr. Faratin joined Strands Inc. as VP of innovation in 2008, where he served as SVP of Innovation, responsible for the entire innovation pipeline of the $55 million startup. While at Strands, he envisaged, developed, marketed and sold a prediction market technology to BBVA. He has published over fifty scientific articles in peer reviewed publications, served as reviewer for the NSF and won multiple competitive NSF and DARPA grants.

== Current ==
Peyman is currently the founder of [http://robustlinks.com RobustLinks], funded by the [http://nsf.gov National Science Foundation]. The mission of RobustLinks is to use state of the art AI, NLP, and ML to compose what we call Knowledge as a Service (KaaS). KaaS takes unstructured (textual) "big data" and reduces it to searchable knowledge. It integrates end-to-end technology stack that continuously gather, summarize and represent the semantics of unstructured text, in real-time and at scale. The derived semantics is then analyzed to condense the big data to a compact and searchable semantic graph.

== Associations ==
Peyman is a board member of number of emerging startups, as well as member of the [[Association_for_Computing_Machinery|Association of Computing Machinery]], [[New York Academy of Science]], the New York City CTO club and a visiting scholar at [[Courant_Institute|Courant Institute of Mathematics]] at NYU. Dr. Faratin is an active member of the NYC technology community.

==External links==
*[http://robustlinks.com/ RobustLinks]
*[http://ana.csail.mit.edu/peyman MIT personal page]
*[http://csail.mit.edu Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence (CSAIL)]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Faratin, Peyman
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = September 16, 1965
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Tehran, Iran
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Faratin, Peyman}}
[[Category:Iranian computer scientists]]
[[Category:Iranian scientists]]
[[Category:Iranian inventors]]
[[Category:Computer scientists]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1965 births]]</text>
      <sha1>o76zdwegkvvo4x9284sefqwnmvoryl1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>