<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Pure Storage</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31422319</id>
    <revision>
      <id>536741931</id>
      <parentid>536738646</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-05T19:26:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Cn}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{overly detailed|date=December 2012}}
{{primary sources|date=December 2012}}
{{technical|date=December 2012}}
{{advert|date=December 2012}}
}}
{{Infobox company |
| company_name   = Pure Storage
| company_logo   = [[Image:Pure Storage logo.jpg|275px]]
| company_type   = [[Private company|Private]]
| company_slogan = Flash changes everything
| foundation     = 2009
| location       = [[Mountain View, California|Mountain View]], [[California]]
|  key_people     = CEO: Scott Dietzen &lt;BR&gt; Co-founder &amp; CTO: John Colgrove &lt;BR&gt; Co-founder &amp; Chief Architect: John Hayes
|  num_employees  =
|  industry       = [[data storage device|Data storage]]
|  funding       =
|  revenue        =
|  homepage       = [http://www.purestorage.com/ www.purestorage.com]
}}

==Overview==
Founded in 2009, '''Pure Storage''' is a [[Mountain View, California]]-based venture-backed ([[Greylock Partners]], [[Index Ventures]], [[Redpoint Ventures]], [[Samsung Ventures]], [[Sutter Hill Ventures]]) enterprise storage company founded by John "Coz" Colgrove, one of the original founders of [[Veritas]] and John Hayes, who joined from the office of the CTO at [[Yahoo]]. The company launched from stealth in August 2011.&lt;ref name="PR082312"&gt;[http://www.marketwire.com/press-release/Pure-Storage-Breaks-Cost-Barrier-Mainstream-Flash-Adoption-With-First-All-Flash-1552544.htm Press Release, August 23, 2011: "Pure Storage Breaks Cost Barrier to Mainstream Flash Adoption With First All-Flash Enterprise Storage Array"]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pure Storage FlashArray==
Pure Storage is pioneering a new class of [[all-flash enterprise storage]]  with the Pure Storage [[FlashArray]]. Deployed in the data center, the [[FlashArray]]  leverages [[flash memory]]  to target primary (Tier 1) storage and accelerate random I/O-intensive applications like [[server virtualization]], [[desktop virtualization]] (VDI), database ([[OLTP]], rich analytics/[[OLAP]], [[SQL]], [[NoSQL]]) and [[cloud computing]].&lt;ref name="PR040411"&gt;[http://www.marketwire.com/press-release/Pure-Storage-Present-Leveraging-Flash-Memory-Enterprise-Storage-Tutorial-Spring-2011-1422098.htm Press Release, April 4, 2011: "Pure Storage to Present "Leveraging Flash Memory in Enterprise Storage" Tutorial at Spring 2011 Storage Networking World"]&lt;/ref&gt;  

The first generation FlashArray was released on August 23, 2011, featuring high availability, out-of-the-box compatibility, and enterprise class scalability.&lt;ref name="PR082312"&gt;[http://www.marketwire.com/press-release/Pure-Storage-Breaks-Cost-Barrier-Mainstream-Flash-Adoption-With-First-All-Flash-1552544.htm Press Release, August 23, 2011: "Pure Storage Breaks Cost Barrier to Mainstream Flash Adoption With First All-Flash Enterprise Storage Array"]&lt;/ref&gt;  
The second generation of the Pure Storage FlashArray with the 2.0 release of the Purity Operating Environment, FlashCare Technology and enhanced data integrity fabric became generally available on May 16, 2012.&lt;ref name="InformationWeek"&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/news/storage/systems/240000478 Deni Connor, InformationWeek, May 16, 2012: "Pure Storage Rolls Out Next-Gen Storage Array"]&lt;/ref&gt;
Additional advances of the second generation of the FlashArray include higher resiliency via active/active high availability, always-on encryption with zero key management, a new web user interface, command line interface, and VMware vStorage API for Array Integration (VAAI) support.&lt;ref name="PR051612"&gt;[http://www.marketwire.com/press-release/pure-storage-unveils-next-generation-flasharray-with-high-availability-flashcare-technology-1658047.htm Press Release, May 16, 2012: "Pure Storage Unveils Next Generation FlashArray With High Availability, FlashCare™ Technology and Data Integrity Fabric"]&lt;/ref&gt;  In August 2012, Pure Storage released a bevy of new software features for the Pure Storage [[FlashArray]], adding [[iSCSI]] connectivity, ZeroSnap™ [[snapshots]], and complete integration with, and management within, [[VMware]] via a new vCenter Web Client Plugin.&lt;ref name="PR082312"&gt;[http://www.marketwire.com/press-release/pure-storage-advances-flasharray-with-ethernet-connectivity-protection-vmware-integration-1693848.htm  Press Release, August 23, 2012: " Pure Storage Advances FlashArray With Ethernet Connectivity, Protection, and VMware Integration Features, Enabling More Customers to Join the Affordable Flash Revolution "]&lt;/ref&gt;  

Pure’s FlashCare Technology and use of in-line and global data deduplication enables the FlashArray to leverage less costly MLC flash. By bringing an average of 5.8 to 1 dedupe ratio {{cn|date=February 2013}}, in addition to the use of MLC flash, Pure is drives the cost of flash down, making the FlashArray competitive with the price of traditional disk-centric arrays.&lt;ref name="CRN"&gt;[http://www.crn.com/news/storage/240000515/pure-storage-releases-all-flash-array-priced-more-like-disk-array.htm?pgno=2 Joseph Kovar, CRN, May 17, 2012: "Pure Storage Releases All-Flash Array Priced More Like Disk Array"]&lt;/ref&gt; Pure Storage uses flash, packaged in the form of shelves of SSDs, from two known suppliers, STEC and Samsung.&lt;ref name="STEC"&gt;[http://memtechinc.com/press/articles/ps_partnership_zeusiops_nr.pdf STEC Press Release, October 3, 2011: "STEC Collaborates with Pure Storage to Advance Development of the Industry’s First All-Flash Enterprise Array"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="The Register"&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/08/23/pure_storage_fa_300/ Chris Mellor, The Register, August 23, 2011: "New Samsung-funded Flash disruptor uncloaks"]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Pure Storage FlashArray features a scalable storage architecture and combines the sub-millisecond latency capabilities of [[solid state memory]] devices with inline [[data deduplication]] to reduce the cost of flash to be inline with traditional rotating disk; FlashArray is priced at under $5 per GB of usable storage capacity, which compares to between $5 to $10 per GB for traditional disk-based arrays and requires about 20 percent of the power and space required for traditional arrays.&lt;ref name="CRN"&gt;[http://www.crn.com/news/storage/231500599/pure-storage-exits-stealth-mode-with-flash-only-array-55-million-in-funding.htm?itc=refresh Joe Kovar, CRN, August 23, 2011: "Pure Storage Exits Stealth Mode With Flash-Only Array, $55 Million In Funding"]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and Recognitions==

'''Silver Winner of the [[Wall Street Journal]]’s 2012 Technology Innovation Awards''': Pure Storage took top honors in the  prestigious competition's Computing Systems category and nabbed the program's 2012 Silver designation beating out close to 540 entrants  for overall innovation across the program's 18 categories.&lt;ref name ="WSJ"&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10000872396390444138104578032572557387496.html Michael Totty, October 16, 2012: “Alternative to Disk Storage”]&lt;/ref&gt; 

'''2012 Best of Show Winner for Most Innovative Flash Memory Enterprise Business Application by the Flash Memory Summit''':  Pure storage was selected from a wide group of enterprise class systems using flash memory as the Best in Show for Business Applications. Reserved for what the judges call the "next killer app" for flash, the award acknowledges the unique and innovative architecture of the FlashArray.  
&lt;ref name="Flash Memory Summit"&gt;[http://www.flashmemorysummit.com/English/Conference/BOS_winners.html  Flash Memory Summit, August 23, 2012: "Congratulations to the 2012 FMS Best of Show Awards Winners! "]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Winner of the Red Herring Top 100 Americas Awards''': Pure Storage was selected by the Red Herring editorial team as a winner for Red Herring Top 100 Americas Award, a prestigious list celebrating the 100 leading and most innovative private technology startups in the North American business region.&lt;ref name="Red Herring"&gt;[http://www.redherring.com/red-herring-americas/americas-2012-top-100-winners/ Red Herring,  May 2012: "Americas 2012 Top 100 "]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''10 Hot Emerging Vendors by CRN for May 2012''': Pure Storage was named one of the 10 hot emerging companies ready to make their mark on the technology landscape.&lt;ref name="CRN 2 "&gt;[http://www.crn.com/slide-shows/cloud/240000670/10-hot-emerging-vendors-for-may-2012.htm Jack McCarthy, May 22, 2012: "10 Hot Emerging Vendors for May 2012"]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''San Francisco Business Times/Silicon Valley Business Journal Best Places to Work''': Pure Storage was recognized as one of the Bay Area's Best Places to work by the San Francisco Business Times and San Jose/Silicon Valley. Pure Storage was ranked among the top 25 companies employing 51-101 employees.&lt;ref name="SF Business Times"&gt;[http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/2012/03/best-places-to-work-finalists-revealed.html SF Business Times, March 13, 2012: "Best Places to Work finalists revealed"]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Silver Winner of the Best in Biz Awards for Enterprise Product of the Year''': Pure Storage was honored as the silver winner of the Enterprise Product of the Year in Best in Biz Awards 2011 for its FlashArray.  Winners of Best in Biz Awards 2011 were determined by scores from a panel of high-caliber judges from top-tier business and technology publications, as well as analyst firms, including: eWeek Channel Insider, Financial Times, Network World, PC Magazine, Tech-Gaming and Wired. The 20 judges on this year’s panel boast more than 470 years of combined experience and have written for a combined total of more than 180 consumer, business, financial, trade and technology publications nationwide.&lt;ref name="PR 110911"&gt;[http://www.purestorage.com/company/pure-storage-honored-for-enterprise-product-of-the-year-in-best-in-biz-awards-2011.html  Press Release, November 9, 2011: "Pure Storage Honored for Enterprise Product of the Year in Best in Biz Awards 2011  "]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Management==

The Pure Storage management team includes:

'''Scott Dietzen, CEO''': former president and CTO of open source messaging and collaboration software vendor [[Zimbra]] (acquired by [[VMware]] in January 2010), and former CTO of enterprise software company [[BEA Systems]] (acquired by [[Oracle Corporation]] in April 2008).&lt;ref name="GigaOM" /&gt; Dietzen also serves on the board of [[Apache Hadoop]] software, training and services provider [[Cloudera]]. He earned his Ph.D. and M.S. in Computer Science and B.S. in Applied Mathematics and Computer Science from [[Carnegie Mellon University]].

'''John "Coz" Colgrove, Cofounder and CTO''':  one of the founding engineers at [[VERITAS]] Software (merged with [[Symantec]] in 2005), where his 20-year career culminated as Fellow and Chief Technology Officer for the company's Data Center Management Group. Coz was the primary architect for the hugely successful VERITAS Volume Manager (VxVM) and VERITAS File System (VxFS), and later served in various other engineering, management, and consultative roles. During his time at VERITAS Coz became one of the industry's foremost experts on optimizing I/O streams and data structures for the unique idiosyncrasies of rotational hard drives, a challenge he's now re-solving for solid state Flash memory.&lt;ref name="Pure Storage Website"&gt;[http://www.purestorage.com/company/management-team.html: "Pure Storage Management"]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''John Hayes, Cofounder and Chief Architect''':  joined from [[Yahoo!'s]] Office of the Chief Technologist, where he investigated web architectures for collaborative development of highly-reliable systems. He joined Yahoo! via the acquisition of [[Bix]], where he was a founding engineer. His diverse experiences have led him to develop new approaches to make today's increasingly complex distributed systems more reliable.&lt;ref name="Pure Storage Website"&gt;[http://www.purestorage.com/company/management-team.html: "Pure Storage Management"]&lt;/ref&gt; Hayes holds a degree in Computer and Systems Engineering from [[University of Guelph]] in Ontario, Canada

'''Matt Kixmoeller, VP Product Marketing''':  former VP of Enterprise Product Management for [[Symantec]]'s Information Management products, including [[NetBackup]] and [[Enterprise Vault]].  Kixmoeller oversaw product strategy and vision, engineering direction, and go-to-market activities for this $1B+ global product line.&lt;ref name="Pure Storage Website"&gt;[http://www.purestorage.com/company/management-team.html: "Pure Storage Management"]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Bob Wood, VP Engineering''':  joined Pure Storage from [[Harmonic]]/[[Omneon]]. Wood served as Vice President of File System Engineering at [[NetApp]], where he led a development team spanning five development centers worldwide and was responsible for NetApp's WAFL file system and their next generation clustered file system. Wood earlier served as a Vice President for all software engineering on the original executive team of Decru. Bob then led the integration of the Decru engineering organization into NetApp, after its acquisition.&lt;ref name="SVSJBJ"&gt;[http://www.bizjournals.com/sanjose/news/2011/08/25/bob-wood-to-head-engineering-for-pure.html Staff, Silicon Valley/San Jose Business Journal, August 25, 2011: "Bob Wood to head engineering for Pure Storage"]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Todd Engle, VP of Operations''': served as VP of Manufacturing at [[Xiotech]]. Under Engle's direction, Xiotech successfully expanded its global manufacturing operations, implemented an improved supply chain management system and streamlined its order fulfillment processes, achieving 99-percent on-time delivery and 95-percent production forecast accuracy rates.&lt;ref name="Pure Storage Website"&gt;[http://www.purestorage.com/company/management-team.html: "Pure Storage Management"]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Matt Burr, VP of Sales''': held sales leadership roles at [[Symantec]] and [[Limelight Networks]]. Matt led the growth of the Western Region for Limelight Networks yielding 100% growth in revenue during his time.&lt;ref name="Pure Storage Website"&gt;[http://www.purestorage.com/company/management-team.html: "Pure Storage Management"]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Venture Funding and Investors==

In mid-2010 Pure Storage raised $18.4 million in Series B financing, led by [[Greylock Partners]] and [[Sutter Hill Ventures]], following a $5 million [[Series A round]] in October 2009. In August 2011 Pure Storage announced an unspecified investment from the venture-capital arm of [[Samsung Electronics]], the biggest flash-memory maker. [[Samsung]] and [[Redpoint Ventures]] contributed to a $30 million Series C funding round.&lt;ref name="WSJ"&gt;[http://blogs.wsj.com/digits/2011/08/23/startup-places-pure-bet-on-flash-memory/ Don Clark, Wall Street Journal, August 23, 2011: "Start-Up Places Pure Bet On Flash Memory"]&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2012, Pure Storage raised $40 million in Series D funding round led by [[Index Venture’s]] [[Mike Volpi]], along with contributions from existing investors [[Greylock Partners]], [[Redpoint Ventures]] and [[Sutter Hill Ventures]], which brings the company's total capital raised to $95 million.&lt;ref name="PR081512"&gt;[http://www.marketwire.com/press-release/pure-storage-receives-40m-cash-infusion-accelerate-explosive-growth-initiate-european-1690999.htm Press Release, August 15, 2012: Pure Storage Receives $40M Cash Infusion to Accelerate Explosive Growth, Initiate European Expansion"]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to venture funding, Pure Storage has received private investment from tech industry leaders, including [[Diane Greene]], the founder and former CEO of [[VMware]] and Frank Slootman, the former CEO of [[Data Domain]].&lt;ref name="GigaOM"&gt;[http://gigaom.com/cloud/pure-storage/ Om Malik, GigaOM, October 4, 2010: "Zimbra Executive Heads To Hot Storage Startup"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Silicontap"&gt;[http://www.silicontap.com/pure_storage_raises__8_4m_/s-0030400.html Silicontap, August 12, 2010: "PURE Storage Raises $18.4M"]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pure Storage Partner Program  ==

In July 2012, Pure Storage launched its P3 partner program, which has made the Pure Storage [[FlashArray]] available to purchase exclusively from qualified IT solutions providers. The program is designed to make selling FlashArray solutions simple and flexible, enabling partners to capitalize on the high-growth, $4 billion solid-state enterprise storage market.&lt;ref name= "PR072512"&gt;[http://www.marketwire.com/press-release/pure-storage-unveils-channel-partner-program-1683701.htm Press Release, July 25, 2012: “Pure Storage Unveils Channel Partner Program”]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.purestorage.com}}

{{Solid-state Drive}}

[[Category:Companies based in California]]
[[Category:Computer storage companies]]
[[Category:Computer peripherals]]
[[Category:Solid-state computer storage media]]</text>
      <sha1>6op2ss09pqmbuzc9qt6msqa4blriend</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>