<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Quantum Content</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33939495</id>
    <revision>
      <id>546459330</id>
      <parentid>473492844</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-23T03:18:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theopolisme</username>
        <id>14159121</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>General cleanup: filling in references</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Quantum Content''' is a concept that describes the complexity, granularity and connectivity of the current state of content creation, consumption and curation.
&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|last=Cotsakos|first=Christos|title=The Age of Quantum Content|url=http://www.endplay.com/quantum|work=Speech|accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==

While the exact origins of the term Quantum Content remain unknown, the term was brought to relevance by [[Christos Cotsakos|Dr. Christos M. Cotsakos]] at the 2011 Gilbane Conference for the [[Web content management system|Web Content Management (WCM)]] industry.  In his keynote speech, titled The Age of Quantum Content, Dr. Cotsakos defined Quantum Content as a function of [[Big data|Big Data]] and its granularity, complexity and connectivity, plus elements of serendipity and sizzle (also known as the e or error term in statistics).

'''Quantum Content''' = ''f'' {Big Data (Granularity + Complexity + Connectivity) + ''e''}&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

==Characteristics of Quantum Content==

Prior to the Age of Quantum Content, there were two elements: content creation and audience engagement—that focused on three areas: a creator or idea, a medium/channel and an audience. In the age of Quantum Content, Dr. Cotsakos identified three new variables that have entered the equation: 

# Granularity: the ways in which a seemingly single piece of data can be viewed, processed and chopped up into various smaller pieces of data, depending on the lens, or “dimension” through which it is being viewed;
# Complexity: the real-time nature of today’s content, as well as the evolution of content types, formats, and distribution channels;
# Connectivity: the connections, context and unique attributes surrounding any piece of data depending on the person(s) it involves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=EndPlay CEO Keynotes Gilbane Boston With Discussion On "Quantum Content|url=http://www.1888pressrelease.com/endplay-ceo-keynotes-gilbane-boston-with-discussion-on-quan-pr-354582.html|work=Press Release|publisher=1 (888) Press Release|accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Similarities with Quantum Physics==

[[Quantum physics]] theory holds that energy comes in very small, discrete units. Each unit can have multiple characteristics. It can behave both like a particle and like a wave, depending on how it's measured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What is Quantum Physics|url=http://library.thinkquest.org/3487/qp.html|work=Journal|publisher=Oracle ThinkQuest|accessdate=5 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Quantum content is not Big Data but rather it is a function of Big Data and its granularity, complexity, and connectivity. Big Data includes both machine- and human-generated data, and it is as granular as the tiniest elements of content – for example, whether or not a website was visited in the past day or what was said in a tweet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Cotsakos|first=Christos|title=The Age of Quantum Content|url=http://www.endplay.com/quantum|work=Speech|accessdate=5 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As in quantum physics, even discrete data elements in the Age of Quantum Content have multiple meanings, depending on how you look at them.

== References ==
&lt;!--- See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.cmswire.com/cms/customer-experience/bold-statements-about-content-collaborations-customers-gilbane-013673.php Bold Statements About Content, Collaborations, Customers #gilbane]
* [http://www.1888pressrelease.com/endplay-ceo-keynotes-gilbane-boston-with-discussion-on-quan-pr-354582.html EndPlay CEO Keynotes Gilbane Boston With Discussion On "Quantum Content"]
* [http://www.endplay.com/quantum The Age of Quantum Content Keynote Transcript]

&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;





[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Web development]]</text>
      <sha1>cv05vxh73bbk7uwr92mestsvin93w5b</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>