<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Queer Cyprus Association</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26286832</id>
    <revision>
      <id>545847317</id>
      <parentid>513925714</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-21T02:04:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 1 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q7271147]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Initiative_Against_Homophobia_logo.png|thumb|right|Initiative Against Homophobia recently changed to Queer Cyprus Association&lt;br&gt;www.queercy.org ]]
'''Initiative Against Homophobia''' (HOKI) was established in 2007 as the first [[LGBTQ]] organisation in [[Cyprus]] north aimed to deal with criminal laws amendments of [[TRNC]] which criminalises [[same-sex relationships]].&lt;ref name=ILGBTIA/&gt;&lt;ref name=ILGAE&gt;{{cite web|title=ILGA Europe 2011 Annual Review|url=https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:xnUJcN69D2kJ:www.ilga-europe.org/content/download/23132/144966/file/Cyprus.pdf+%22queer+cyprus+association%22&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEEShxCWR9t2YrNcDG7w05q-86erVwbitXVt1JxxR9rq2fHeeBn6uJFCX-G_Z1opqVHxyJ7-bHTUPaawhUkXELHMs0_OeSZ2d1PZVULsqTyQeBNuZYjq-rD3o6W1J3UKVjzq0xIm_z&amp;sig=AHIEtbSHDfsz7mx8nGlE-pkMzqSPsNfSZQ&amp;pli=1|publisher=ILGA Europe|accessdate=12 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; They seek equal [[human rights]] including to "fully decriminalize homosexuality, equalize the [[age of consent]] and better protect LGBTQ people under the law.”&lt;ref name=pn/&gt; 

In March 2012, Initiative Against Homophobia has gone through a constitutional amendments and continues its work under its new name '''Queer Cyprus Association''' (Kuir Kıbrıs Derneği).

==Background==
HOKI was established in [[Northern Cyprus]] to deal with the rights of [[LGBT]] people. In April 2008, the initiative presented a proposal regarding the repeal of criminal law to the president of Parliament [[Fatma Ekenoglu]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Initiative Against Homophobia |url=http://en.queercy.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=7&amp;Itemid=9 |title=Proposal of Criminal law presented by Initiative Against Homophobia |publisher=En.queercy.org |date= |accessdate=20 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Criminal laws in Cyprus north still have articles from British Colonial period where [[homosexual]] activities are defined as [[Crimes Against Nature]] and are penalised. Cyprus north is the last territory in European Council where homosexuality is a crime.&lt;ref name=pn&gt;{{cite news|title=Michael Cashman MEP meets Northern Cyprus leaders over anti-gay law|url=http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2012/04/16/michael-cashman-mep-meets-northern-cyprus-leader-over-anti-gay-law/|accessdate=12 August 2012|newspaper=Pink News|date=April 16, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Canning|first=Paul|title=MILESTONE: Northern Cyprus becomes last place in Europe to decriminalize homosexuality|url=http://sdgln.com/news/2011/12/15/northern-cyprus-agrees-decriminalize-homosexuality|accessdate=13 August 2012|newspaper=San Diego Gay &amp; Lesbian News|date=December 15, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

British Colonial Laws, Articles 171, 172 and 173 of Chapter 154 of the penal code, "punishes 'unnatural sex' with five years jail and gives three years imprisonment for attempts to commit such acts."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Jenkin|first=Matthew|title=Cashman calls for end to gay ban in Northern Cyprus: Gay MEP Michael Cashman met with leaders in Northern Cyprus to discuss decriminalization of homosexuality|url=http://www.gaystarnews.com/article/cashman-calls-end-gay-ban-northern-cyprus160412|publisher=Gay Star News|accessdate=12 August 2012|date=April 16, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Press Release by Hoki regarding last court case: "crimes against nature"|url=http://www.ilga-europe.org/home/guide/country_by_country/cyprus/press_release_by_hoki_regarding_last_court_case_crimes_against_nature|publisher=ILGA Europe|accessdate=12 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2011 Cyprus is seen as the least [[gay-friendly]] EU country followed by [[Italy]], [[Latvia]] and [[Malta]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Reitman|first=Andrew|title=Cyprus is least gay-friendly EU country, study says|url=http://euobserver.com/lgbti/32341|publisher=EU Observer|accessdate=12 August 2012|date=May 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In 2008, and in association with the [[International Day Against Homophobia and Transphobia]] (IDAHO), HOKI applied to the local authorities in Nicosia to become a fully established and recognised association.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Initiative Against Homophobia takes steps to become a recognised association|url=http://ilga-europe.org/home/guide/country_by_country/cyprus/initiative_against_homophobia_takes_steps_to_become_a_recognised_association|accessdate=12 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2008 HOKI presented a request to repeal 171, 172, and 173 of Punishment Regulations-Chapter 154 along with a resolution to Fatma Ekenoglu, the head of the Parliamentary of Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus.&lt;ref name=elong&gt;{{cite web|title=Resolution regulating the presence of different sexual orientations has been presented to Ekenoglu|url=http://www.ilga-europe.org/home/guide/country_by_country/cyprus/resolution_regulating_the_presence_of_different_sexual_orientations_has_been_presented_to_ekenoglu|publisher=ILGA Europe|accessdate=12 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They stated the rules "provide the main framework for regulating discrimination against [[sexual orientation]], and they have not been revised since [[British Empire|British colonial time]]."&lt;ref name=elong/&gt;

In 2010 HOKI organized an international conference, "Solidarity and Networking Conference Cyprus 2010," in co-operation with the International Lesbian and Gay Association (ILGA) - Europe and hosted by the Journalists Union.&lt;ref name=tapan&gt;{{cite news|last=Tapan|first=Berivan|title=Cyprus On Track to Decriminalize Homosexuality: International and local non-governmental organizations took an important step for the recognition of freedom for homosexual individuals in Cyprus. President of the Northern Cyprus Assembly Bozer promised to amend the laws that define homosexuality as a crime.|url=http://www.bianet.org/english/minorities/126459-cyprus-on-track-to-decriminalize-homosexuality|accessdate=13 August 2012|newspaper=Bianet|date=December 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The event emphasized that homosexuality is recognized as a crime only in Cyprus and assessed this fact as a "violation of human rights."&lt;ref name=tapan/&gt;

In July 2011 "two men were arrested and charged with 'unnatural intercourse.'"&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt; According to Article 171 of Chapter 154 of the Criminal Code applicable in Cyprus north “whoever has sexual intercourse against the order of nature with any person, or, allows sexual intercourse against the order of nature with a male, commits a serious crime and is punishable with up to five years in prison.”&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt;  The men were arrested after neighbor's complaints, and accusations have been made that one of them was "bringing men home".&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt;  "The judge said they should be held in custody for a day."&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt;  HOKI publicised the case and others followed suit including LGBTQI organisations from Greece, Malta, Turkey, Albania and Cyprus, who supported HOKI and reiterated calls for a change in the law.&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt; 

In a similar incident in October 2011, five men, one of whom was Michalis Sarris, former Cypriot Minister of Finance, were arrested over a few days and detained on charges of “unnatural intercourse.”&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt;&lt;ref name=sdlgn&gt;{{cite news|last=Canning|first=Paul|title=More arrests for "gay sex" reported in Northern Cyprus|url=http://sdgln.com/news/2011/10/19/more-arrests-gay-sex-reported-northern-cyprus|accessdate=13 August 2012|newspaper=San Diego Gay &amp; Lesbian News|date=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  During remand hearings all the detainees apart from Michalis Sarris reported being beaten by the police.&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt; HOKI raised alarm at the arrests which led to protests from Members of the European Parliament, and international human rights organisations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Submitted by Initiative Against Homophobia|title=Old-fashioned law|url=http://www.ilga-europe.org/home/guide/country_by_country/cyprus/old_fashioned_law|publisher=ILGA Europe|accessdate=12 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Joint Statement to Northern Cyprus Regarding Arrests Under Article 171|url=http://www.trust.org/trustlaw/news/joint-statement-to-northern-cyprus-regarding-arrests-under-article-171|accessdate=13 August 2012|newspaper=Trust Law|date=October 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; HOKI also alleged the Cyprus north media, in their reporting, normalized attitudes of hatred and fed "homophobic reports and comments to the public."&lt;ref name=sdlgn/&gt; The story was covered by ''Cypriot'' and international media, raising the issue of the continued existence and use of the law.&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt; The men were released on bail.&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt; HOKI led a group of NGOs to declare "The current law in effect does not protect the rights of the children nor the rights of people’s control over their own bodies. It aims to protect the ‘morality’ of the society."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Mullen|first=Fiona|title=Sarris: let's spread the facts, not the fiction|url=http://www.financialmirror.com/blog-details.php?nid=838|accessdate=13 August 2012|newspaper=Financial Mirror|date=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Also in 2011 HOKI hosted [[ILGA-Europe]]’s family exhibition ''Different Families, Same Love'' in Nicosia (north).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=HOKI hosts the ILGA-Europe LGBT Family Exhibition in the northern part of Cyprus|url=http://www.ilga-europe.org/home/guide/country_by_country/cyprus/hoki_hosts_the_ilga_europe_lgbt_family_exhibition_in_the_northern_part_of_cyprus|publisher=ILGA Europe|accessdate=12 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt; The opening included a range of media including state television with the exhibition receiving positive press coverage and provided a different and positive facets of the LGBT community to the general public.&lt;ref name=ILGAE/&gt;

In March 2012, Initiative Against Homophobia has gone through a constitutional amendment and continues its work under its new name Queer Cyprus Association. QCA aims to promote equal rights for [[LGBTQ]] people in Cyprus and to eliminate discriminations based on [[gender]], [[gender expression]], [[sexual orientation]] and [[gender identity]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.queercy.org Queer Cyprus Association]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Banks|first=Martin|title=North Cyprus called on to 'urgently update' homosexuality laws|url=http://www.theparliament.com/latest-news/article/newsarticle/cyprus-urged-to-urgently-update-homosexuality-laws/#.UCg1QkLlf0c|accessdate=12 August 2012|newspaper=The Parliament|date=April 16, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have been a member of the [[International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association]] (ILGBTIA) since 2011.&lt;ref name=ILGBTIA&gt;{{cite web|title=ILGA’S Directory of LGBTI and Allied Organizations: Queer Cyprus Association|url=http://ilga.org/directory/en/detail?o_id=4248|publisher=International Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans and Intersex Association|accessdate=12 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In August the [[European Court of Human Rights]] (ECHR) has agreed to examine a legal challenge against Turkey for the north’s continued failure to repeal a law banning homosexuality, Queer Cyprus Association said Turkey must now defend the legacy of British colonialism at the ECHR.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Evripidou|first=Stefanos|title=ECHR agreed to examine north gay ban case|url=http://www.cyprus-mail.com/cyprus/echr-agreed-examine-north-gay-ban-case/20120802|accessdate=12 August 2012|newspaper=Cyprus Mail|date=August 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]
[[Category:Queer]]</text>
      <sha1>n3dcjk257xz83aexnnkmi0d2x1p2ldw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>