<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Rackspace Cloud</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19127563</id>
    <revision>
      <id>557983843</id>
      <parentid>555233300</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-02T15:20:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Disinterest</username>
        <id>10076746</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>/* Server Locations */ The text claimed that there are four datacenters but the list consists of three datacenters.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| name     = Rackspace Cloud 
| logo     = [[File:RackspaceCloudLogo.png|279px]] 
| parent           = [[Rackspace]] 
| type     = [[Division (business)|Division]] 
| foundation       = March 4, 2006 
| industry         = [[Cloud computing]]
| License          = Open Source (Apache 2.0)&lt;ref name="rackspace.com"/&gt;
| homepage         = {{URL|http://www.rackspace.com/}}
}}
'''The Rackspace Cloud''' is a growing set of Cloud-related products and services billed on a [[utility computing]] basis. Offerings include [[web application]] [[web hosting|hosting]]/[[Platform as a service|Cloud Platform]] ("''Cloud Sites''"), [[Cloud Storage]] ("''Cloud Files''"), [[Virtual private server|VPS]] ("''Cloud Servers''"), Cloud Load Balancers, Cloud Databases, Cloud Backup, and Cloud Monitoring.  The Rackspace Cloud was one of the first commercial [[cloud computing]] services.{{citation needed|date=May 2013}}

== History ==
[[File:MossoLogo.png|right|thumb|The original Mosso logo]]
'''The Rackspace Cloud''' was originally launched as '''Mosso LLC''' on March 4, 2006, a wholly owned subsidiary startup billed as a [[utility computing]] offering.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.netcraft.com/archives/2006/03/04/new_reseller_service_offers_utility_computing_for_100_a_month.html Netcraft: New Reseller Service Offers Utility Computing for $100 a Month]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://investing.businessweek.com/research/stocks/private/snapshot.asp?privcapId=33334866 BusinessWeek: Mosso, LLC]&lt;/ref&gt; As it pre-dated mainstream adoption of [[cloud computing]] it was "retooled" and relaunched on February 19, 2008, adopting the tagline "Mosso: The Hosting Cloud".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.datacenterknowledge.com/archives/2008/02/19/mosso-evolves-into-the-hosting-cloud/ Mosso Evolves Into The Hosting Cloud]&lt;/ref&gt; The "Mosso" branding (including the '''mosso.com''' domain) was then dropped on June 17, 2009 in favour of "The Rackspace Cloud" branding (including the '''rackspacecloud.com''' domain).&lt;ref name="sneakpeek"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rackspace.com/blog/?p=284|title=A Sneak Peek at our Plans in the Cloud|last=Moorman|first=Lew|date=2009-06-17|publisher=Rackspace|accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since then, customer contracts have been executed with Rackspace US, Inc. d/b/a The Rackspace Cloud rather than with the Mosso LLC subsidiary.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rackspacecloud.com/legal/tos Rackspace Cloud Terms of Service]&lt;/ref&gt;

Other companies (such as [[EMC Corporation|EMC]] with its "Decho" subsidiary) also use alternative branding for their [[cloud computing]] offerings.

In 2011, the "Rackspace Cloud" brand merged with Rackspace.com.  In 2012, Rackspace rebranded as "Rackspace, the open cloud company.".

== Services ==

=== Cloud Files ===
'''Cloud files''' is a [http://www.rackspace.co.uk/cloud-hosting/ cloud hosting] service that provides "unlimited online storage and [[Content delivery network|CDN]]" for media (examples given include backups, video files, user content) on a [[utility computing]] basis (at USD 0.10/GB*month).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rackspace.com/blog/cloud-files-updates/&lt;/ref&gt; It was originally launched as ''Mosso CloudFS'' on May 5, 2008 and is similar to [[Amazon Simple Storage Service]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rackspace.com/information/mediacenter/release.php?id=205 Mosso Unveils Cloud Storage Service]&lt;/ref&gt; Unlimited files of up to 5 GB can be uploaded, managed via the online control panel or [[REST]]ful API and optionally served out via [[Akamai Technologies]]' [[Content Delivery Network]].&lt;ref name="cf-intro"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/cloud_hosting_products/files/|title=Cloud Files Introduction Documentation|publisher=Rackspace|accessdate=2011-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

; API
In addition to the online control panel the service can be accessed over a [[REST]]ful API with [[open source]] client code available in [[C Sharp (programming language)|C#]]/[[.NET Framework|.NET]], [[Python (programming language)|Python]], [[PHP]], [[Java (programming language)|Java]]  and [[Ruby (programming language)|Ruby]]. Rackspace-owned [[Jungle Disk]] allows Cloud Files to be mounted as a local drive within supported [[operating system]]s ([[Linux]], [[Mac OS X]] and [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]).

; Security

Redundancy is provided by replicating three full copies of data across multiple computers in multiple "zones" within the same data center, where "zones" are physically (though not geographically) separate and supplied separate power and Internet services. Uploaded files can be distributed via [[Akamai Technologies]] to "hundreds of endpoints across the world" which provides an additional layer 
of data redundancy.&lt;ref name="cf-intro"/&gt;

The control panel and API are protected by [[Secure Sockets Layer|SSL]] and the requests themselves are signed and can be safely delivered to untrusted clients. Deleted data is zeroed out immediately.&lt;ref name="cf-intro"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://docs.rackspace.com/files/api/v1/cf-devguide/content/Delete_Object-d1e2264.html&lt;/ref&gt;

; Use cases

Use cases considered as "well suited" include backing up or archiving data, serving images and videos (which are streamed directly to the users' browsers), serving content over [[content delivery network]]s, storing secondary static web-accessible data, developing data storage applications, storing fluctuating and/or unpredictable amounts of data and reducing costs.&lt;ref name="cf-intro"/&gt;{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

; Caveats
There is no native [[operating system]] support for the Cloud Files API so it is not yet possible to "map" or "mount" it as a virtual drive without third-party software like [http://www.jungledisk.com/ JungleDisk] that translates to a supported standard such as [[WebDAV]]. There are no concepts of "appending" or "locking" data within Cloud Files (which may affect some disk mirroring or backup solutions), nor support for permissions or transcoding. Data is organised into "containers" but it is not possible to create nested folders without a translation layer.&lt;ref name="cf-intro"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://docs.rackspace.com/files/api/v1/cf-devguide/content/Containers-d1e458.html&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cloud Servers ===
'''Cloud Servers''' is a [[cloud infrastructure]] service that allows users to deploy "one to hundreds of cloud servers instantly" and create "advanced, high availability architectures" similar to the [[Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud]].&lt;ref name="apipr"/&gt; The "cloud servers" are [[virtual machine]]s running on the [[Xen]] hypervisor for Linux-based instances, and [[Citrix]] XenServer for Windows and Linux instances. Each quad core hardware node has between 16 and 32 GB of [[RAM]], allowing for allocations between 256 MB and 30 GB. Disk and CPU allocations scale up with memory, with disk sizes ranging from 10 GB to 620 GB.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/cloud_hosting_products/servers/pricing/ Rackspace Cloud: Cloud Servers Technical Specifications]&lt;/ref&gt; Various distributions of [[Linux]] are supported, including [[Arch Linux|Arch]], [[CentOS]], [[Debian]], [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]], [[Gentoo Linux|Gentoo]], [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]] and [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]].

The technology behind the service was purchased in Rackspace's October 22, 2008 acquisition of ''Slicehost'' and the servers were formerly known as "slices". These are "much cheaper and generally easier to use than a traditional dedicated server", though it is still necessary to maintain the [[operating system]] and [[solution stack]] which is not required for the ''Cloud Sites'' product.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.techcrunch.com/2008/10/22/rackspace-acquires-jungledisk-slicehost-to-take-on-amazon-web-services/ Rackspace Acquires JungleDisk, Slicehost To Take On Amazon Web Services]&lt;/ref&gt; This is one of the main differentiators between the two services; where Cloud Servers includes full root access and thus allows for more customisation, the Cloud Sites product is less flexible but requires less maintenance.

On December 14, 2010, The Rackspace Cloud began offering a managed service level on the Cloud Servers product, which adds additional support for the operating system and common applications as well as patching and other routine services.&lt;ref&gt;[http://adtmag.com/articles/2010/12/15/rackspace-managed-cloud-service.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;  This additional support level does come at an increased cost, however.

RackSpace also offers Cloud Tools, which is a catalog of applications and infrastructure software built to run on the RackSpace cloud.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/tools/]&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the notable applications listed are [[Zend]], a PHP stack, [[Cloudkick]], a cloud performance testing services, [[CopperEgg]], a real-time cloud server and application monitoring service, [[Xeround]], a MySQL cloud database, and MongoLab, the cloud version of the popular [[NoSQL]] database [[MongoDB]].

; API
The Cloud Servers API launched on July 14, 2009 under the [[Creative Commons]] Attribution 3.0 license allows clients to create, configure and control virtual servers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS137483+23-Jul-2009+BW20090723 The Rackspace Cloud Goes Open Source with APIs]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to issuing basic management commands this "enables elastic scenarios" whereby servers are instantiated and destroyed in response to fluctuating load (one of the key characteristics of [[cloud computing]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.networkworld.com/news/2009/071409-rackspace-api.html Rackspace API gives developers greater access to cloud platform]&lt;/ref&gt; [[RightScale]] is among third-party providers to have announced support for this API.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.betanews.com/article/Cloud-Expo-RightScale-adds-RackSpace-Eucalyptus-to-its-hybrid-clouds/1238701208 Cloud Expo: RightScale adds RackSpace, Eucalyptus to its 'hybrid clouds']&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cloud Sites ===
Cloud Sites is a [[Platform as a service|cloud platform]] offering, similar to traditional [[web hosting]] only built on [[scalability|horizontally scalable]] hardware infrastructure. A fixed monthly credit card payment gives users access to the service with an allocation of compute, storage and bandwidth resources. Should this allocation be exhausted then subsequent usage is billed on a [[utility computing]] basis. It allows an "unlimited" number of sites, databases and email accounts and includes reseller options such as client billing and support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/cloud_hosting_products/sites/pricing|title=Cloud Sites: Pricing|publisher=Rackspace|accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Touted as "the fastest way to put sites on the cloud", it runs Windows or Linux applications across "hundreds of servers".&lt;ref name="apipr"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS114233+14-Jul-2009+BW20090714|title= businesswire The Rackspace Cloud Announces Public API for Cloud Servers|last=Puccio|first=Krisana|date=2009-07-14|accessdate=2009-07-29|work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cloud Sites supports the [[PHP 5]], [[Perl]], [[Python (programming language)|Python]], [[MySQL]], [[.NET Framework|.NET]] 2.0+, [[Active Server Pages|ASP]] and [[Microsoft SQL Server 2008]] application frameworks.&lt;ref name="isitafit"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rackspace.com/cloud |title=Cloud Sites: Is it a fit?|publisher=Rackspace|accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

; Compute cycles
The service includes up to 10,000 "compute cycles" per month which "is roughly equivalent to running a server with a 2.8 GHz modern processor for the same period of time" (with additional cycles priced at USD 0.01). This non-standard unit of measurement primarily reflects CPU processing time but also includes [[I/O]] operations so pages with many database queries will consume more "compute cycles".&lt;ref name="faq"&gt;[http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/cloud_hosting_faq Rackspace Cloud Hosting FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; It can however be difficult to compare services between providers without standard units of measurement.

; Caveats

Cloud Sites does not support [[Java (programming language)|Java]], [[Apache Tomcat|Tomcat]], [[ColdFusion]], [[Secure Shell|SSH]], [[Remote Desktop Protocol|RDP]], [[API]] access, [[Microsoft Exchange Server|Microsoft Exchange]] or custom server-side components at this time.&lt;ref name="isitafit" /&gt; It is also not possible to set up multiple top level domains to point to the same web root directory.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.appnovation.com/hosting-high-traffic-drupal-site-with-mosso-cloud-hosting Hosting High Traffic Web Sites with Mosso]&lt;/ref&gt; The .NET environment dropped support for "full trust" in favour of "modified medium trust" despite having previously announced on their blog that they had been able to work directly with Microsoft to engineer a system that could accommodate Full Trust without compromising the security, scalability, and performance of other users.&lt;ref name="mediumtrust"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://help.rackspacecloud.com/article.php?id=383|title=Overview of modified Medium Trust|publisher=Rackspace|accessdate=2009-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="fulltrust"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/blog/2007/12/11/iis-7-%E2%80%93-how-mosso-is-taking-advantage-of-microsoft%E2%80%99s-new-hosting-platform/|title=IIS 7: How Mosso is Taking Advantage of Microsoft's New Hosting Platform|publisher=Rackspace|accessdate=2009-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Server Locations ==

[http://www.rackspace.co.uk/cloud-hosting/cloud-products/cloud-servers/ Cloud servers] are physically located in any of three datacenters:&lt;ref&gt;According to Chris A., a Rackspace Sales Representative&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Chicago|Chicago, IL]], [[Dallas|Dallas, TX]], or [[London|London, UK]].  Separate accounts are required to utilize servers on separate continents.  Cloud Sites are available in the Dallas and Chicago datacenters only.

== Control Panel ==
[[Image:Rackspace Cloud control panel screenshot.png|right|300px|thumb|Rackspace Cloud online control panel]]
The online control panel was custom built by and for the Rackspace Cloud service (as opposed to using control panel software like [[cPanel]] as is often the case with traditional [[web hosting]] providers).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/blog/tag/control-panel/ Mosso’s New Control Panel and Provisioning System]&lt;/ref&gt;

The control panel includes management interfaces for the Cloud Sites, Cloud Servers and Cloud Files services. There was once a web based file manager, but this was removed for undisclosed reasons. It also allows users to manage multiple clients and the plans and products (e.g. databases, 24x7 support) that apply to them, with white label branding options for messaging. The clients themselves have access to a restricted version of the control panel that allows them to conduct administrative tasks such as managing mail accounts.&lt;ref name="cp"&gt;[http://manage.rackspacecloud.com/ Rackspace Cloud Control Panel]&lt;/ref&gt;

The control panel is also home to the billing and reporting functions and provides access to support materials including developer resources, a knowledge base, forums and live chat.&lt;ref name="cp"/&gt;

== OpenStack ==
{{Main|OpenStack}}
In 2010, RackSpace contributed the source code of its Cloud Files product to the [[OpenStack]] project under the [[Apache License]] to become the OpenStack Object Storage component.&lt;ref name="rackspace.com"&gt;http://www.rackspace.com/blog/?p=1047&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rackspace.com/blog/?cat=253&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2012, Rackspace announced it is in the process of implementing OpenStack Compute as the underlying technology for their Cloud Servers product.  With the change will come a new control panel as well as add-on cloud services offering [[databases]], server [[System monitoring|monitoring]], [[block storage]], and [[virtual network]]ing.&lt;ref name="csopenstack"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rackspace.com/blog/next-generation-rackspace-cloud-servers/|title=The Rackspace Cloud Powered By OpenStack|publisher=Rackspace|accessdate=2012-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Cloud computing]]
* [[Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud]]
* [[CloudSigma]]
* [[ElasticHosts]]
* [[Linode]]
* [[Liquid Web]]
* [[Rackspace]]
* [[Skytap]]
* [[Enlight cloud]]
* [[Zadara Storage]]
* [[HP Cloud Services]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.rackspace.com/ Rackspace Cloud Computing] - official site
* [http://openstack.org/ OpenStack]
* [http://www.rackspacecloudreview.com/ Rackspace Cloud Reviews] - user reviews
* [http://www.devguide.net/books/rackspacecloudservers/ Managing Rackspace Cloud Servers]—an unofficial guide to Rackspace Cloud Servers management
{{Cloud computing}}

[[Category:Cloud platforms]]
[[Category:Cloud storage]]
[[Category:Cloud infrastructure]]</text>
      <sha1>t4f5w0g36oj5luusyaw7tdab0lvz9f2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>