<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Saffron Technology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35815790</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521912513</id>
      <parentid>495978734</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T00:12:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Snotbot</username>
        <id>13752234</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>Fixing section headings [[Wikipedia:Bots/Requests for approval/Snotbot 5|(task 5)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Saffron Technology''', Inc. a company headquartered in Cary, North Carolina, is a creator of [[big data analytics]] tools based on [[Associative Memory Base]] technology.

==History==

Saffron was founded in 1999 by Dr [[Manuel Aparicio]], a recognized pioneer in the field of Associative Memories, and Dr Jim Fleming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Company Overview of Saffron Technology, Inc.|url=http://investing.businessweek.com/research/stocks/private/person.asp?personId=627899&amp;privcapId=99166&amp;previousCapId=99166&amp;previousTitle=Saffron%20Technology,%20Inc.|work=Bloomberg BusinessWeek|accessdate=4 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2000, former National Security Advisor Admiral [[John Poindexter]] joined the board with a focus of applying Associative Memory technology in the fields of National Security and Intelligence&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harris|first=Shane|title=The Watchers: The Rise of the Surveillance State|year=2010|publisher=Penguin Group|location=London|isbn=1-101-195332-0|pages=281}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first years, the company did most of its work with the U.S. Department of Defense, including in Iraq, analyzing and predicting where IED’s would be located so insurgent bombers could be proactively targeted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=deBruyn|first=Jason|title=Making a Computer ‘Think’|url=http://www.bizjournals.com/triangle/print-edition/2011/12/02/making-a-computer-think.html?page=2|work=Triangle Business Journal|accessdate=4 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2010, the analyst firm [[Gartner]] identified Saffron as a “Cool Vendor” in Information Infrastructure for Enterprise Information Management &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Gartner|title=Cool Vendors 2010|url=http://www.gartner.com/technology/research/cool-vendors/2010.jsp|work=Gartner|accessdate=4 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Associative Memory Base Technology==


Associative memory bases identify entities that are defined as people, places and things. The technology mimics human memory by recalling associations between those people, places and things, and specifically the context and frequency of association. As each entity in a set of data has its own memory about all the other entities it is associated with, the engine can learn the way humans do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harris|first=Shane|title=The Watchers: The Rise of the Surveillance State|year=2010|publisher=Penguin Group|location=London|isbn=1-101-195332-0|pages=281}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The technology has proved to be highly scalable and efficient in cases of extremely large datasets. Saffron exploits a proprietary loss less compression routine that is capable of creating extremely compact models. 

The Saffron implementation is able to operate on compressed datasets thereby enabling dramatic reduction in storage and CPU hardware, thus enabling the application of associative memory technology in a distributed environment.

==National Security &amp; Iraq==


During the [[Iraqi insurgency]] Saffron was used by coalition forces in Iraq to help identify entities that were defined as people, places and things involved in insurgent networks. The tool mimicked human memory by recalling associations between those people, places and things. Unlike other tools Saffron focused on context and frequency of association. Each word representing an entity in a set of data had its own memory about all the other words it had been used in association with. In this way the tool could learn the way humans did.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harris|first=Shane|title=The Watchers: The Rise of the Surveillance State|year=2010|publisher=Penguin Group|location=London|isbn=1-101-195332-0|pages=281}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Engineering==


A Global 100 manufacturing company uses Saffron Technology in a number of operational areas to leverage past engineering decisions and business experiences, such as component and part order optimization, failure root-cause analysis, and predictive maintenance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Evelson|first=Boris|title=It's The Dawning of the Age of BI DBMS|accessdate=4 May 2012|newspaper=Forrester|date=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Computer memory companies]]</text>
      <sha1>0gfuemmwp70d1393kdexs5d2vbcg98x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>