<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Slavín</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1533708</id>
    <revision>
      <id>552831704</id>
      <parentid>552821648</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-30T03:33:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yopie</username>
        <id>493489</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/177.183.19.116|177.183.19.116]] ([[User talk:177.183.19.116|talk]]) to last revision by Addbot. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the war memorial and cemetery|people called Slavin|Slavin (surname)|other uses|Slavin (disambiguation)}}
{{for|the tomb at [[Prague]]'s [[Vyšehrad Cemetery]]|Slavín (Prague)}}
{{Infobox Military Memorial
|name=Slavín
|country=Slovakia
|body=
|image=[[Image:Slavin memorial, Bratislava.jpg|220px]]
|caption=Slavín war memorial and cemetery for fallen Soviet Army
|commemorates=[[World War II]]
|coordinates= {{coord|48|09|14|N|17|05|59|E}} in [[Bratislava]], [[Slovakia]]
|designer=[[Ján Svetlík]]
|unveiled=April 3, 1960
|total= 6,845 Soviet soldiers
}}

'''Slavín''' is a [[War memorial|memorial]] monument and [[military cemetery]] in [[Bratislava]], the capital of [[Slovakia]]. It is the burial ground of thousands of [[Soviet Army]] soldiers who fell during [[World War II]] while liberating the city in April 1945 from the occupying German [[Wehrmacht]] units and the remaining Slovak troops who supported the [[clero-fascism|clero-fascist]] [[Tiso]] government. It is situated on a hill amidst a rich villa quarter of the capital and embassy residences close to the centre of Bratislava.

It was constructed between 1957 and 1960 on the site of a field cemetery, and opened on April 3, 1960 on the occasion of the 15th anniversary of the city's liberation. The monument was constructed similar in kind to the [[Palace of Culture and Science]] in [[Stalinist architecture|Stalinist architectural]] style. In 1961 it was declared a National Cultural Monument. Its designer was Ján Svetlík.

== History ==
The monument was dedicated in 1960 on the occasion of the 15th anniversary of the deliverance of the city by the Soviet army. In the cemetery are buried 6,845 soldiers. Exactly 63 years after the war, this monument represents the city Lucenec as one of the important cities by acquirement of freedom and the peace.{{fact|date=September 2011}} On its walls are listed cities with dates of their deliverance.

== Description ==
This grandiose monument and cemetery of soldiers of the Soviet Army who were killed in deliverance of Bratislava during the Second World War has been designated the National Cultural Monument. On top of the 39.1 metre high pylon stands an 11 metre high sculpture of a soldier by A. Trizuljak. The bronze [[Caisson (western architecture)|caisson]] door of the memorial auditorium is decorated with reliefs by R. Pribiš.

The site consists of:

*A solemn staircase
*A cemetery with graves (6 mass graves, 278 individual graves) of 6,845 Soviet soldiers who fell while liberating Bratislava
*The central solemn hall with various statues, inscriptions, and a symbolic [[sarcophagus]] made of white [[marble]]. It also features a 39.5 m high [[obelisk]] topped with a statue of a Soviet soldier, and on the outside walls are inscriptions of the dates of liberation of various places in Slovakia during 1944–45.

Other facts about Slavín:

*This monument is situated in Malé Karpaty and it is very often attended because of its beautiful view.
*In the area of Slavín are also more statues of Slovak famous artists, such as Jan Kulich, Tibor Bártfay and Jozef Kostka.
*In 2005, Vladimir Putin, Russian president, visited it during his meeting with G. W. Bush in Bratislava.
*There is day of Bratislava's liberation on 4 April, when people and president show their honor to fallen Soviet soldiers.

== See also ==
* [[Devín Carpathians]]

[[Image:Slavin-pano.jpg|thumb|left|600px|Panorama from Slavin Memorial.]]

{{Cemeteries in Bratislava}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Slavin}}
[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 1960]]
[[Category:1960 in Czechoslovakia]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Bratislava]]
[[Category:Monuments and memorials in Slovakia]]
[[Category:Socialist realism]]
[[Category:Stalinist architecture]]
[[Category:Cemeteries in Slovakia]]
[[Category:Soviet military memorials and cemeteries]]
[[Category:Czechoslovakia–Soviet Union relations]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Bratislava]]</text>
      <sha1>k5hhbld92p3igrku9blltzrk3ygnvu0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>