<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Social data analysis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11459836</id>
    <revision>
      <id>560879072</id>
      <parentid>560878626</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-21T10:43:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>58.97.195.105</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Verify|date=April 2011}}
'''Social data analysis''' is a style of analysis in which people work in a social, collaborative context to make sense of data. The term was introduced by [[Martin M. Wattenberg|Martin Wattenberg]] in 2005 &lt;ref&gt;2005: Baby Names, Visualization, and Social Data Analysis  Martin Wattenberg. IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization.&lt;/ref&gt; and recently also addressed as big social data analysis &lt;ref name = "Cambria13"&gt;
{{cite book
 | author = Erik Cambria
 | coauthors = Dheeraj Rajagopal, Daniel Olsher, and Dipankar Das
 | title = Big social data analysis
 | booktitle = Big Data Computing
 | chapter = 13
 | year = 2013
 | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis
 | url = http://tmrfindia.org/bigdata.html
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; in relation to [[big data]] computing.

On a Social Data Analysis system or network, users store data sets and create visual representations. The datasets and visualisations/graphs are accessible to other users of the network or website.  Users can create new and interesting visualisations/graphs as well as associated commentary from the same data sets.  The discussion mechanisms often use frameworks such as a [[blog]]s and [[wiki]]s to drive this social exploration/[[Collaborative intelligence]].  

This is a new slant on [[business intelligence]] where social exploration of data can lead to serious analysis and important insight that the initiating user did not envisage/explore (for whatever reason).

Universities all over the world are opening graduate program in Social Data Analysis. University of Windsor is one of such universities to introduce interdisciplinary approach in Social Data Analysis by starting their Master's program in Social Data Analysis. 

== See also ==
* [[Data Analysis]]
* [[Big Data]]
* [[Business intelligence]]
* [[Collaborative intelligence]]

==External links==
* [http://www1.uwindsor.ca/masda Most Advanced Interdisciplinary Master's Program in Social Data Analysis by University of Windsor]
* [http://www.socialdata.com.br Social Data - Ferramenta para Redes Sociais]
* [http://researchweb.watson.ibm.com/visual/social_data_analysis_workshop/ Social Data Analysis Workshop at CHI 2008]
* [http://csdl2.computer.org/persagen/DLAbsToc.jsp?resourcePath=/dl/trans/tg/&amp;toc=comp/trans/tg/2006/04/v4toc.xml&amp;DOI=10.1109/TVCG.2006.65 Designing for Social Data Analysis]
* [http://www.istrategylabs.com/2011/09/announcing-grandstand-a-social-data-product-for-rewarding-crowds/ Social Data Analysis Application: Grandstand]
* [http://sentic.net/mabsda Multidisciplinary Approaches to Big Social Data Analysis (WWW13 workshop)]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Visualization (graphic)]]
[[Category:Collective intelligence]]
[[Category:Internet terminology]]</text>
      <sha1>bx32n7wqvcaj29273ofdwwuum6odyot</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>