<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Spatial database</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4533551</id>
    <revision>
      <id>555930040</id>
      <parentid>555462646</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-20T11:16:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.183.151.75</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed self reference</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A '''spatial database''' is a [[database]] that is optimized to store and query data that represents objects defined in a geometric space.  Most spatial databases allow representing simple geometric objects such as points, lines and polygons.  Some spatial databases handle more complex structures such as 3D objects, topological coverages, linear networks, and TINs. While typical databases are designed to manage various numeric and character types of data, additional functionality needs to be added for databases to process spatial data types efficiently. These are typically called ''geometry'' or ''feature''. The [[Open Geospatial Consortium]] created the [[Simple Features]] specification and sets standards for adding spatial functionality to database systems.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opengeospatial.org OGC Homepage]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Features of spatial databases==
Database systems use indexes to quickly look up values and the way that most databases index data is not optimal for [[spatial query|spatial queries]]. Instead, spatial databases use a [[spatial index]] to speed up database operations. 

In addition to typical SQL queries such as SELECT statements, spatial databases can perform a wide variety of spatial operations. The following operations and many more are specified by the [[Open Geospatial Consortium]] standard:

*Spatial Measurements: Computes line length, polygon area, the distance between geometries, etc.
*Spatial Functions: Modify existing features to create new ones, for example by providing a buffer around them, intersecting features, etc.
*Spatial Predicates: Allows true/false queries about spatial relationships between geometries.  Examples include "do two polygons overlap" or 'is there a residence located within a mile of the area we are planning to build the landfill?' (see [[DE-9IM]])
*Geometry Constructors: Creates new geometries, usually by specifying the vertices (points or nodes) which define the shape.
*Observer Functions: Queries which return specific information about a feature such as the location of the center of a circle

Some databases support only simplified or modified sets of these operations, especially in cases of [[NoSQL]] systems like [[MongoDB]] and [[CouchDB]].

==Spatial index==
'''Spatial indices''' are used by spatial databases (databases which store information related to objects in space) to optimize [[spatial query|spatial queries]].  Conventional index types do not efficiently handle spatial queries such as how far two points differ, or whether points fall within a spatial area of interest. Common spatial index methods include:

*[[Grid (spatial index)]]
*[[Z-order (curve)]]
*[[Quadtree]]
*[[Octree]]
*[[UB-tree]]
*[[R-tree]]: Typically the preferred method for indexing spatial data.{{Citation needed|date=June 2012}} Objects (shapes, lines and points) are grouped using the [[minimum bounding rectangle]] (MBR). Objects are added to an MBR within the index that will lead to the smallest increase in its size.
*[[R+ tree]]
*[[R* tree]]
*[[Hilbert R-tree]]
*[[X-tree]]
*[[kd-tree]]
*[[m-tree]] - an m-tree index can be used for the efficient resolution of similarity queries on complex objects as compared using an arbitrary metric.

==Spatial database systems==
*All OpenGIS Specifications compliant products&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opengeospatial.org/resources/?page=products All Registered Products at opengeospatial.org]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Open source]] spatial databases and APIs, some of which are OpenGIS compliant&lt;ref&gt;[http://opensourcegis.org/ Open Source GIS website]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Spatial Query Server|Boeing's Spatial Query Server]] spatially enables Sybase ASE.
*[[Smallworld]] [[VMDS]], the native GE [[Smallworld]] GIS database
*[[SpatiaLite]] extends [[Sqlite]] with spatial datatypes, functions, and utilities.
*[[IBM DB2]] Spatial Extender can be used to enable any edition of DB2, including the free [[IBM DB2 Express-C|DB2 Express-C]], with support for spatial types
*[[Oracle Database|Oracle]] Spatial
*[[Microsoft SQL Server]] has support for spatial types since version 2008
*[[PostgreSQL]] DBMS (database management system) uses the spatial extension [[PostGIS]] to implement the standardized datatype ''geometry'' and corresponding functions.
*[[MySQL]] DBMS implements the datatype ''geometry'' plus some spatial functions that have been implemented according to the OpenGIS specifications.&lt;ref&gt;http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.5/en/gis-introduction.html&lt;/ref&gt; However, in MySQL version 5.5 and earlier, functions that test spatial relationships are limited to working with minimum bounding rectangles rather than the actual geometries. MySQL versions earlier than 5.0.16 only supported spatial data in MyISAM tables. As of MySQL 5.0.16, InnoDB, NDB, BDB, and ARCHIVE also support spatial features.
*[[Neo4j]] - [[Graph database]] that can build 1D and 2D indexes as [[Btree]], [[Quadtree]] and [[Hilbert curve]] directly in the [[Graph (mathematics)|graph]]
*[[AllegroGraph]] - a [[Graph database]] provides a novel mechanism for efficient storage and retrieval of two-dimensional geospatial coordinates for [[Resource Description Framework]] data.  It includes an extension syntax for [[SPARQL]] queries
*[[MongoDB]] supports geospatial indexes in 2D
*[[Esri]] has a number of both single-user and multiuser geodatabases.
*[http://paralleluniverse.co SpaceBase] is a real-time spatial database.&lt;ref&gt;[http://paralleluniverse.co/product SpaceBase product page on the Parallel Universe website]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[CouchDB]] a document based database system that can be spatially enabled by a plugin called [[Geocouch]]
*[http://cartodb.com/ CartoDB] is a cloud based geospatial database on top of [[PostgreSQL]] with [[PostGIS]].
*[http://www.stormdb.com StormDB] is an upcoming cloud based database on top of [[PostgreSQL]] with geospatial capabilities.

*[http://www.minerpsolutions.com/en/software/enterprise/spatialDB SpatialDB] by MineRP is the worlds first open standards [[Open_Geospatial_Consortium|(OGC)]] spatial database with spatial type extensions for the [[Mining|Mining Industry]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minerpsolutions.com/en/software/enterprise/spatialDB SpatialDB product page on the MineRP website]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Object-based spatial database]]
* [[Spatiotemporal database]]
* [[Spatial query]]
* [[Spatial analysis]]
* [[Location intelligence]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*[http://www.spatial.cs.umn.edu/Book/ Spatial Databases: A Tour], Shashi Shekhar and Sanjay Chawla, Prentice Hall, 2003 (ISBN 0-13-017480-7)
*[http://gis.esri.com/esripress/ ESRI Press]. ESRI Press titles include '''Modeling Our World: The ESRI Guide to Geodatabase Design''', and '''Designing Geodatabases: Case Studies in GIS Data Modeling ''', 2005 [http://www.pma-online.org/benfrank2005_winnerfinalist.cfm Ben Franklin Award] winner, PMA, The Independent Book Publishers Association.
*[http://mkp.com/books/data-management Spatial Databases - With Application to GIS] Philippe Rigaux, Michel Scholl and Agnes Voisard. Morgan-Kauffman Publishers. 2002 (ISBN 1-55860-588-6)

==External links==
*[http://www.mapbender.org/presentations/Spatial_Data_Management_Arnulf_Christl/html/ An introduction to PostgreSQL PostGIS]
*[http://www.gisdevelopment.net/magazine/years/2006/jan/18_1.htm PostgreSQL PostGIS as components in a Service Oriented Architecture] [[Service-oriented architecture|SOA]]
*[http://www.springerlink.com/content/vn7446g28924jv5v/ A Trigger Based Security Alarming Scheme for Moving Objects on Road Networks] Sajimon Abraham, P. Sojan Lal, Published by Springer Berlin / Heidelberg-2008.

[[Category:Spatial databases| ]]
[[Category:Web mapping]]</text>
      <sha1>eb05id8j6pbstr578fe5npbfs27fmnp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>