<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Spectra Logic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22458665</id>
    <revision>
      <id>539796889</id>
      <parentid>539796682</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-23T00:39:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.166.27.196</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Spectra Logic''' Corporation is a [[computer data storage]] company based in [[Boulder, Colorado]] in the United States. The company builds [[backup]] and archive solutions for [[secondary storage]] to protect data after it migrates from primary disk. Spectra Logic's primary product is [[tape libraries]]. The company was founded in 1979,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.storagesearch.com/spectralog.html|title=Spectra Logic}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is a [[privately held company]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hpcwire.com/features/Spectra-Logic-Finds-Niche-in-High-End-Tape-Storage-35578829.html?viewAll=y|title=Spectra Logic Finds Niche in High-End Tape Storage}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History==
Spectra Logic was founded in 1979 by Nathan C. Thompson in his apartment while he was an engineering student at the [[University of Colorado at Boulder]]. Thompson is currently the Chairman and CEO of the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colorado.edu/engineering/deaa/cgi-bin/display.pl?id=258|title=Nathan C. Thompson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The company was the first to automate [[Advanced Intelligent Tape]] (AIT) magnetic tape in a robotic autoloader ([[tape library]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.enterprisestorageforum.com/hardware/news/article.php/2193411/Storage-Notes-Every-ISP-Will-Need-a-Tape-Library.htm|title=Storage Notes: Every ISP Will Need a Tape Library}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was also the first tape library vendor to implement the [[iSCSI]] networking protocol in its products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.networkworld.com/news/2003/0415spectralogic.html|title=Spectra Logic enables iSCSI on tape libraries}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spectra Logic was again first when it released a tape library with integrated hardware-based [[data encryption]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.infoworld.com/t/storage/spectra-gets-backup-encryption-right-351|title=Spectra gets backup encryption right}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Spectra's T-Finity tape library was introduced in November 2009, offering 99.9% reliability and scaling to 180 [[petabyte]]s of storage capacity in an [[Linear_Tape-Open#Generations|LTO-5]] configuration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.networkcomputing.com/tapes-and-disks/229502380|title=Spectra Logic:Taking Tape to Infinity}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2010, Spectra's tape library product line won first place in all 14 categories of ''Storage'' magazine/SearchStorage.com's 2010 Quality Awards for enterprise and midrange tape libraries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spectralogic.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=home.displayFile&amp;DocID=3506 |title=Spectra Logic Reigns Supreme}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spectra Logic again earned top honors in the 2012 ''Storage'' magazine/SearchStorage.com's Quality Awards, winning both the enterprise and midrange tape library categories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://searchdatabackup.techtarget.com/ezine/Storage-magazine/Which-data-storage-technologies-will-reshape-storage-shops-in-2013/Spectra-Logic-gets-midrange-and-enterprise-tape-storage-systems-awards|title=Spectra Logic gets midrange and enterprise tape storage systems awards}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In May 2012, DCIG, LLC released a Tape Library Buyer's Guide, which evaluated over 60 tape libraries from 8 storage vendors. Only the Spectra Logic T-Finity and T950 received the highest "Best-in-Class" ranking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/g/a/2012/05/17/prweb9515119.DTL|title=DCIG, LLC Announces Big Data Tape Library Buyers Guide}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also that month, Spectra Logic announced that it would provide Spectra T-Finity tape libraries to the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA) for their Blue Waters supercomputing system. The T-Finity tape libraries will be able to store hundreds of petabytes of data and will be one of the world's largest active file repositories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bio-itworld.com/2012/05/22/spectra-logic-tape-storage-beefs-up-ncsa-blue-waters-supercomputer.html |title=Spectra Logic Tape Storage Beefs Up NCSA Blue Waters Supercomputer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Spectra Logic is a founding member of the Active Archive Alliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.activearchive.com/content/active-archive-alliance-formed-promote-simplified-online-access-all-archived-data|title=Active Archive Alliance Formed to Promote Simplified, Online Access to All Archived Data}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Active Archive]]  is a method of tiered storage which gives the user access to data across a virtualized file system that migrates data between multiple storage systems.

== Spectra T950 ==

The Spectra T950 tape library stores media tapes in the tape library bundled in trays called TeraPacks. A TeraPack holds ten tapes, which increases the density of the tape storage, which the company claims simplifies the loading and unloading of the tapes from the library.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hpcwire.com/features/Spectra-Logic-Finds-Niche-in-High-End-Tape-Storage-35578829.html?viewAll=y|title=Spectra Logic Finds Niche in High-End Tape Storage}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are Spectra T950 installations in several [[high performance computing]] (HPC) facilities, including the NASA [[Ames Research Center]], [[Argonne National Laboratory]], and [[Los Alamos National Laboratory]]. These customers chose the Spectra T950 because at the time it offered the highest storage density and energy efficiency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spectralogic.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=home.displayFile&amp;DocID=2683|title=Spectra Logic Scores Data Archive Wins as HPC Market Gets "Greener"}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 April 2009, NASA Ames announced that it would replace ten of their 20 year-old silo tape libraries with two Spectra Logic T950 tape libraries. This allowed the center to reclaim {{convert|1400|sqft|m2}} of floor space and increase its storage capacity from 12 petabytes to 32 petabytes. The new tape libraries used 20,000 tape cartridge slots and LTO-4 ([[Linear Tape-Open]]) drives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9131838|title=NASA dumps Sun, sticks with tape for archives}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also==
* [[Tape library]]
* [[Tape drive]]
* [[Computer data storage]]

==External links==
* [http://www.spectralogic.com/ Spectra Logic]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Computer storage companies]]</text>
      <sha1>l0fgs9cc5osvcg8up9alj1s5628h1gu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>