<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Sqlstream</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31824158</id>
    <revision>
      <id>542694865</id>
      <parentid>539783004</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-07T22:55:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>/* See also */[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] errors fixed + general fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8961)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=August 2012}}

{| class="infobox vcard" cellspacing="5" style="width:22em; style="float: right;""
|+ SQLstream
|-
! scope="row" style="text-align:left;" | Industry 
| [[Software]]
|- 
! scope="row" style="text-align:left;" | Founded
| 2003
|- 
! scope="row" style="text-align:left;" | Headquarters 
| [[San Francisco]], [[California]]
|-
! scope="row" style="text-align:left;" | Website 
| http://www.sqlstream.com
|}

'''SQLstream, Inc.''' is a real-time streaming Big Data software company headquartered in [[San Francisco]], [[California]]. SQLstream was established in 2003 by Damian Black, Edan Kabatchnik and Julian Hyde, author of the open source [[Mondrian OLAP server|Mondrian Relational OLAP Server Engine]].

==Technology==
The rapid increase in the volume of available service and sensor data has led to new, real-time market segments which augment the traditional monitoring, [[business intelligence]] and 
[[data warehousing]] domains.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/node/15557421 All too much, monstrous amounts of data] The Economist&lt;/ref&gt;

SQLstream provides a relational stream computing platform for analyzing large volumes of service, sensor and machine and log file data in real-time. It performs real-time collection, aggregation, integration, enrichment and real-time analytics on the streaming data.  Data streams are analyzed using the industry standard SQL language, with an enhancement of the SQL window function to analyze and aggregate real-time streaming data over fixed or sliding time windows. Unlike a traditional [[relational database|RDBMS]] SQL query, which returns a result and exits, streaming SQL queries do not exit, generating results continuously as soon as new data become available. Patterns and exception events in data streams are detected, analyzed and reported 'on the fly' as the data arrive, that is, before the data are stored.  Like a database or data warehouse, SQLstream allows you to create multiple views over the data so that different applications and users can each get their own customized view of the streaming data.  It also allows changes to be made to the queries and views without bringing down and recompiling existing applications.  In this way, it provides a platform for performing real-time operational intelligence, which you can view as real-time business intelligence over streaming operational data.  SQLstream utilizes dataflow technology to execute many queries over high-velocity high-volume Big Data with a massively parallel standards-compliant SQL engine.  Unlike databases, SQL in SQLstream becomes a language for performing continuous parallel processing, in contrast to a language for data retrieval as commonly found in relational databases.

Applications include real-time service and sensor data management, real-time data integration, streaming log file analytics 
and real-time data warehousing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.b-eye-network.com/blogs/vanderlans/archives/2010/03/visit_of_sqlstr.php Reporting on SQLstream] Rick van der Lans, BeyeNetwork&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dashboardinsight.com/articles/one-on-one-with-dashboard-insight/chatting-with-sqlstream.aspx Interview with SQLstream] Dashboard Insight&lt;/ref&gt;

==Products==
SQLstream launched its first product to market in January 2008.  The website lists four products: s-Server, s-Analyzer, s-Transport, and s-Cloud. Professional services for strategy, certification, and training are also offered on the website.

==See also==
* [[Operational Intelligence]]
* [[Extract, transform, load|Extract, transform and load (ETL)]]
* [[sensor network|Wireless sensor network]]
* [[intelligent transportation system|Intelligent Transportation Systems]]
* [[Real-time business intelligence]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.sqlstream.com SQLstream website]

[[Category:Software companies based in California]]
[[Category:Companies based in San Francisco, California]]</text>
      <sha1>oxwky2c622g596xmavl92kkk34w7whw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>