<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Strozzi NoSQL (RDBMS)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31399333</id>
    <revision>
      <id>554731743</id>
      <parentid>554729264</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-12T13:43:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.53.15.59</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>infobox</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{No footnotes|date=August 2011}}
{{About|a specific relational database management system|the class of non-relational database management systems|NoSQL}}

{{Infobox software
| name                   = Strozzi NoSQL (RDBMS)
| title                  = Strozzi NoSQL (RDBMS)
| logo                   = &lt;!-- [[File: ]] --&gt;
| logo caption           = 
| screenshot             = &lt;!-- [[File: ]] --&gt;
| caption                = 
| collapsible            = 
| author                 = Carlo Strozzi
| developer              = 
| released               = {{Start date|1998}}
| discontinued           = 
| latest release version = 4.1.10
| latest release date    = {{Start date and age|2010|09|13}}
| latest preview version = 
| latest preview date    = &lt;!-- {{Start date and age|YYYY|MM|DD|df=yes/no}} --&gt;
| frequently updated     = &lt;!-- DO NOT include this parameter unless you know what it does --&gt;
| status                 = 
| programming language   = 
| operating system       = 
| platform               = [[Unix]]-like (e.g., [[Cygwin]])
| size                   = 
| language               = 
| language count         = &lt;!-- DO NOT include this parameter unless you know what it does --&gt;
| language footnote      = 
| genre                  = [[Relational database management system|RDBMS]]
| license                = [[GNU General Public License|GPL]]
| alexa                  = 
| website                = {{URL|http://www.strozzi.it/cgi-bin/CSA/tw7/I/en_US/nosql/Home%20Page}}
| standard               = 
| AsOf                   = 
}}
'''Strozzi NoSQL''' is a [[Shell (computing)|shell]]-based [[relational database management system]] initialized and developed by Carlo Strozzi that runs under [[Unix]]-like operating systems, or others with compatibility layers (e.g., Cygwin under Windows). Its file name ''NoSQL'' merely reflects the fact that it does not express its queries using [[Structured Query Language]]; the NoSQL RDBMS is distinct from the circa-2009 general concept of [[NoSQL|NoSQL databases]], which are typically non-relational, unlike the NoSQL RDBMS. Strozzi NoSQL is released under the [[GNU GPL]].

==Construction==
NoSQL uses the [[operator-stream paradigm]], where a number of "operators" perform a unique function on the passed data. The stream used is supplied by the UNIX input/output redirection system so that over the [[Pipeline (Unix)|pipe]] system, the result of the calculation can be passed to other operators. As UNIX pipes run in memory, it is a very efficient way of implementation.

NoSQL, with development led by Carlo Strozzi, is the latest and perhaps the most active in a line of implementations of the stream-operator database design originally described by Evan Shaffer, Rod Manis, and Robert Jorgensen in a 1991 Unix Review article and an [http://www.rdb.com/lib/4gl.pdf associated paper].  Other implementations include the Perl-based rdb, a commercial version by the original authors called [http://www.rdb.com/ /rdb], and [https://www.cfa.harvard.edu/~john/starbase/starbase.1.html Starbase], a version with added astronomical data operators by John Roll of Harvard and the Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory.  Because of its strengths in dealing with pipe data, most implementations are a mixture of [[awk]] and other programming languages, usually C or Perl.

The concept was originally described in a 1991 Unix Review article, and later expanded in a paper (see reference above), as well as in the book, "Unix Relational Database Management".  NoSQL (along with other similar stream-operator databases) is well-suited to a number of fast, analytical database tasks, and has the significant advantage of keeping the tables in ASCII text form, allowing many powerful text processing tools to be used as an adjunct to the database functions themselves.  Popular tools for use with NoSQL include Python, Perl, awk, and shell scripts using the ubiquitous Unix text processing tools (cut, paste, grep, sort, uniq, etc.)

NoSQL is written mostly in interpretive languages, slowing actual process execution, but its ability to use ordinary pipes and filesystems means that it can be extremely fast for many applications when using RAM filesystems or heavily leveraging pipes, which are mostly memory-based in many implementations.

==Philosophy==
The reasons for avoiding SQL are as follows:
# Complexity: Most commercial database products are often too costly for minor projects, and free databases are too complex. They also do not have the shell-level approach that NoSQL has.
# Portability:
## Data: The data from NoSQL can be easily ported to other types of machines, like [[Macintosh]]es or [[Windows]] computers, since tables exist as simple ASCII text and can be easily read from or redirected to files at any point in processing.
## Software: NoSQL can run on any UNIX machine that has the [[Perl]] and the [[AWK programming language]]s installed, and perhaps even on the [[Cygwin]] UNIX-like environment for [[Microsoft Windows]].
# Unlimited: NoSQL has no arbitrary limits, like a data field size, column number, or file size limit, and can principally work where other products cannot. (The number of columns in a table may actually be limited to 32,768 by some implementations of the AWK1 programming language).
# Usability: With its straight forward and logical concept, NoSQL can easily be used by non-computer people. For instance, rows of data are selected with the 'row' operator, columns with the 'column' operator.

In contrast to other RDBMS, NoSQL has the full power of UNIX during application development and usage. Its user interface uses the UNIX shell. So, it is not necessary to learn a set of new commands to administer the database. From the view of NoSQL, the database is not more than a set of files similar to any other user file. No scripting or other type of database language is used besides the UNIX shell. This shell-nature encourages casual use of this database, which makes its use familiar, resulting in formal use. In other words, NoSQL is a set of shell routines that access normal files of the operating system.

== Examples==
To retrieve information about a particular employee, a query in SQL might look like this:

 select e.*, a.*, mgr.* from EMPLOYEES e, ADDRESSES a, MANAGERS mgr
 WHERE .....

Since a document-oriented NoSQL database often retrieves a pre-connected document representing the entire employee, the query might look like this:

 $e = doc("/employee/emp_1234")
 return $e/address/zip

The stream-operator paradigm differs from conventional SQL, but since the NoSQL DB is relational, it is possible to map NoSQL operators to their SQL equivalents:
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! SQL !! NoSQL or /rdb
|-
| select col1 col2 from filename || column col1 col2 &lt; filename
|-
| where column - expression || row ’column == expression’
|-
| compute column = expression || compute ’column = expression’
|-
| group by || subtotal
|-
| having || row
|-
| order by column || sorttable column
|-
| unique || uniq
|-
| count || wc -l
|-
| outer join || jointable -al
|-
| update || delete, replace
|-
| nesting || pipes
|}

==See also==
* [[Relational database management system]] (RDBMS)

==Further reading==
*{{cite web
|first=Larry
|last=Ayers
| title =  How Not To Re-Invent The Wheel
| work = [[Linux Gazette]]
| date = November 1998
| url = http://linuxgazette.net/issue34/ayers2.html
| accessdate = 2011-05-03}}
*{{cite web
|first=Steve
|last=Litt
| title =  NoSQL: The Unix Database (With awk)
| work = Linux Productivity Magazine
| date = April 2007
| url = http://www.troubleshooters.com/lpm/200704/200704.htm
| accessdate = 2011-05-03}}
*{{cite journal
| first=Giuseppe
| last=Paterno
| journal = [[Linux Journal]]
| title =  NoSQL Tutorial
| date = November 1, 1999
| url = http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/3294
| accessdate = 2011-05-03}}

==External links==
* [http://www.strozzi.it/cgi-bin/CSA/tw7/I/en_US/nosql/Home%20Page NoSQL: a non-SQL RDBMS]

[[Category:Relational database management systems]]
[[Category:Free database management systems]]</text>
      <sha1>7420j0f0xe69v5ubog8be46joli8m5n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>