<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Talend Open Studio for Data Integration</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12930529</id>
    <revision>
      <id>560096877</id>
      <parentid>553012582</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-16T02:03:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Joelm</username>
        <id>50027</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>Small grammatical fixes and slight rewording</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
|name          = Talend Open Studio for Data Integration
|logo          =
|screenshot    = [[File:2011 Talend MDM studio.png|200px]]
|caption       = Talend MDM studio
|developer     = [[Talend]]
|license          = [[GNU General Public License]] 2.0
| latest release version = 5.3.0
|programming language = [[Java (programming language)|Java]]
|genre         = [[data integration]]
|website       = [http://www.talend.com/download.php Download Talend Open Studio for Data Integration]
}}
{{News release|date=July 2011}}
'''Talend Open Studio for Data Integration''' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eweek.com/c/a/Database/REVIEW-Talend-Open-Studio-Makes-Quick-ETL-Work-of-Large-Data-Sets-281473/ REVIEW: Talend Open Studio Makes Quick ETL Work of Large Data Sets]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcworld.idg.com.au/review/software_and_services/talend/open_studio_3_0/276900 Talend Open Studio 3.0]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoworld.com/d/developer-world/test-center-review-open-source-data-aces-054 Test Center review: Open source data aces]&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[open source]] [[data integration]] product developed by [[Talend]] and designed to combine, convert and update data in various locations across a business.

== History ==

Talend Open Studio for Data Integration is distributed under [[GPLv2]] and was launched in October 2006,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/042407-talend-data-integration.html?page=1 Open source start-up upgrades data integration software]&lt;/ref&gt; under ''Talend Open Studio'', its previous name. In January 2008, it had been downloaded over 1 million times. In January 2012, the product totaled 20 million downloads and over 3500 clients.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infogroup.com/about-us/news--events/infogroup-continues-cutting-edge-data-evolution-le.aspx Infogroup Continues Cutting-Edge Data Evolution Leveraging Open-Source Technology]&lt;/ref&gt;

Talend also provides ''Talend Enterprise Data Integration'', a commercial extension to Talend Open Studio for Data Integration with additional features, technical support and IP indemnification.

== Product Description ==

Talend Open Studio for Data Integration operates as a code generator allowing data transformation scripts and underlying programs to be generated in [[Java (programming language)|Java]]. Its [[GUI]] is made of a [[metadata]] repository and a graphical designer. The metadata repository contains the definitions and configuration for each job - but not the actual data being transformed or moved. The information in the metadata repository is used by all of the components of Talend Open Studio for Data Integration.

The product is based on [[Eclipse (software)#Rich Client Platform|Eclipse RCP]]. Most of its contributors work for commercial open source vendor [[Talend]].

Individual jobs are designed using graphical components,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.talendforge.org/components/index.php|title=Talend Component page}}&lt;/ref&gt; of which over 400 are available, for transformation, connectivity, or other operations. The jobs created can be executed from within the studio or as standalone [[Scripting language|scripts]].

An organization might typically use Talend Open Studio for Data Integration for:

*	Synchronization or replication of databases
*	Right-time or batch exchanges of data
*	[[Extract, transform, load|ETL]] (Extract Transform Load) for analytics
*	[[Data migration]]
*	Complex data transformation and loading
*	[[Data quality]]
*	[[Big Data]]

The Primary difference between Talend Open Studio for Data Integration and Talend Enterprise Data Integration is that the Enterprise version has a Subversion plug-in built in as well as support for Joblets. Using Talend Enterprise Data Integration, ETL and ELT jobs can have a dynamic schema.

== See also ==
* [[Talendforge]], the [[Talend]] Community
* [[Talend Open Studio for Data Quality]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.talend.com/download.php Download Talend Open Studio for Data Integration]

[[Category:ETL tools]]
[[Category:Talend]]</text>
      <sha1>9qxjaa1e1hihchi66l52gvet9cpllat</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>