<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Talend</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24143094</id>
    <revision>
      <id>559843813</id>
      <parentid>559452501</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-14T08:24:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>112.66.25.149</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| name             = Talend
| logo             = [[File:Talend logo.png]]
| type             = Private
| genre            =
| fate             =
| predecessor      =
| successor        =
| foundation       = 2005
| founder          =
| defunct          =
| location_city    = [[Suresnes]], France &amp; [[Los Altos, California]], US
| location_country =
| location         =
| locations        =
| area_served      = Worldwide
| key_people       = Bertrand Diard, co-founder &amp; CEO / Fabrice Bonan, co-founder &amp; COO
| industry         = Computer Software
| products         = Talend Open Studio for Data Integration, Talend Enterprise Data Integration, Talend Open Studio for Data Quality, Talend Enterprise Data Quality, Talend Open Studio for MDM, Talend Enterprise MDM, Talend Open Studio for ESB, Talend Enterprise ESB, Talend ESB Standard Edition, Talend Open Studio for Big Data, Talend Integration Express, Talend Enterprise BPM, Talend Cloud
| production       =
| services         =
| revenue          =
| operating_income =
| net_income       =
| aum              =
| assets           =
| equity           =
| owner            =
| num_employees    = 400
| parent           =
| divisions        =
| subsid           =
| homepage         = http://www.talend.com/
| footnotes        =
| intl             =
}}
'''Talend''' is an [[open source]] software vendor that provides [[data integration]], [[data management]], [[enterprise application integration]] and [[big data]] software and solutions. Headquartered in Suresnes, France and Los Altos, California, Talend has offices in North America, Europe and Asia, and a global network of technical and services partners.  Customers include [[eBay]], [[Virgin Mobile]], [[Sony Online Entertainment]], [[Deutsche Post]] and [[Allianz]].
Talend is an [[Apache Software Foundation]] sponsor and many of its engineers are major contributors to Apache including [[CXF]], [[Apache Camel|Camel]], [[ServiceMix]], Karaf, Santuario, and [[ActiveMQ]]. The company has also joined the [[Java Community Process]] (JCP) and is a Strategic Developer Member of the [[Eclipse Foundation]], a Corporate Member of [[OW2]], and has active involvement in the OASIS project.

Talend is notable for being one of the [http://momentumindex.com/96-open-source-start-ups-ranked-by-momentum-index-3/ hottest venture-backed companies with an open source business model] in 2011.

Talend has 400 employees in 14 offices across 7 countries.

== History ==
Talend was founded in 2005 by Bertrand Diard and Fabrice Bonan. It was the first [[commercial open source software|commercial open source]] vendor of data integration software. Other vendors have since entered this market, including [[Apatar]], [[Jitterbit]], [[Pentaho]], and [[SnapLogic]].  Non open source data integration vendors include [[Software AG]], [[Ab Initio (company)|Ab Initio]], [[SAS Institute]], [[Pervasive Software]], [[IBM]], [[Informatica]], and [[SAP AG|SAP]].

Talend's first product, [[Talend Open Studio for Data Integration]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.networkworld.com/news/2007/042407-talend-data-integration.html?page=1 Open source start-up upgrades data integration software]. Networkworld.com (2007-04-24). Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt; was launched in October 2006, under its previous name: ''Talend Open Studio''. In January 2008, it had been downloaded over 1 million times. In January 2012, the product totaled 20 million downloads and the company had over 3500 clients around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://apache.ulitzer.com/node/2294767 Talend’s Enterprise Manageability Capabilities Streamline Hadoop Deployments]. Apache.ulitzer.com. Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt;

Talend is backed by four [[venture capital]] firms. The first two rounds of funding were provided by AGF Private Equity and Galileo Partners. In January 2009, [[Bernard Liautaud]], the founder of Business Objects, led a $12 million round C&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latribune.fr/journal/archives/edition-du-2301/126471/bernard-liautaud-finance-lediteur-de-logiciels-talend.html Bernard Liautaud finance l'éditeur de logiciels Talend]. LaTribune.fr. Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/01/26/more-validation-for-open-source-software-talend-raises-12-million/ More Validation For Open Source Software: Talend Raises $12 Million]. TechCrunch (2009-01-26). Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itbusinessedge.com/cm/community/news/inf/blog/talends-fundraising-validates-open-source-data-integration/?cs=30028 Talend's Fundraising Validates Open Source Data Integration]. Itbusinessedge.com (2009-01-26). Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sdtimes.com/DATA_INTEGRATOR_TALEND_SCORES_12M_IN_FUNDING/About_DATAINTEGRATION_and_OPENSOURCE_and_TALEND/33208 Data integrator Talend scores $12M in funding]. Sdtimes.com. Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt; for his firm [[Benchmark Capital|Balderton Capital]]. In November 2010, [[Silver Lake Partners|Silver Lake Sumeru]] led a $34 million round and Talend announced at the same time the acquisition of Sopera, a strategic member of the [[Eclipse Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;Flinn, Ryan. (2010-11-10) [http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2010-11-10/silver-lake-sumeru-invests-in-data-management-company-talend.html Silver Lake Sumeru Invests in Data Management Company Talend]. Bloomberg.com. Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://techcrunch.com/2010/11/10/open-source-software-company-talend-raises-34m-acquires-sopera/ Open Source Software Company Talend Raises $34M; Acquires Sopera]. Techcrunch.com (2010-11-10). Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.france24.com/en/20101113-bertrand-diard-ceo-talend-internet-data-softwar-open-source Bertrand DIARD, CEO and Co-founder of Talend]. France24.com. Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latribune.fr/blogs/blog-initie/20101110trib000571525/nouvelle-etape-de-croissance-pour-talend.html Nouvelle étape de croissance pour Talend]. Latribune.fr. Retrieved on 2013-01-10.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2011 Talend introduced its Unified Integration Platform – an important milestone subsequent to the acquisition.  In June 2011 the company also released Talend Cloud to support all forms of Cloud-based computing. In February 2012, Talend Open Studio for Big Data, an integration solution dedicated to big data, was released.

Today, Talend has more than 4000 paying customers including eBay, Virgin Mobile, Sony Online Entertainment, Deutsche Post and Allianz.

== Products ==

=== Data Management ===
[[File:Talend Open Studio.jpg|thumb|[[software]] Talend Open Studio for Data Integration Screenshot]]
* ''Talend Open Studio for Data Integration'': an open source solution for data integration to improve the efficiency of data integration job design through a graphical development environment.
* ''Talend Enterprise Data Integration'': a subscription service that extends Talend Open Studio for Data Integration with technical support and enterprise-class features.
* ''Talend Open Studio for Data Quality'': an open source data profiling tool that examines the content, structure and quality of complex data structures.
* ''Talend Enterprise Data Quality'': an open source data quality product that cleanses inaccurate and inconsistent data, ''identifies and resolves duplicate records and provides the capability to augment and enhance data''.&lt;ref&gt;Foley, John (2008-06-24) [http://web.archive.org/web/20110613082534/http://www.informationweek.com/blog/main/archives/2008/06/open_source_too.html New Open Source Tool For Data Quality Control]. Information Week&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Talend Open Studio for MDM &amp; Talend Enterprise MDM'': a set of functions for master data management that provides functionality for integration, quality, governance, mastering and collaborating on enterprise data.
* ''Talend Integration Express'': a hosted service that extends Talend Open Studio for Data Integration with technical support and additional features for teamwork and productivity.

=== Application Integration ===
[[File:Talend Open Profiler.gif|thumb|[[software]] Talend Open Studio for Data Quality Screenshot]]
* ''Talend Open Studio for [[Enterprise service bus|ESB]] &amp; Talend Enterprise ESB'': an enterprise service bus and a standards-based connectivity layer used to integrate distributed systems across functional, enterprise and geographic boundaries. It is powered by the Apache CXF, Apache Camel and Apache ActiveMQ open source integration projects.
* ''Talend ESB Studio'': an Eclipse-based tooling environment for modeling, configuring and deploying integration solutions using Talend ESB.

=== Cloud Based Integration ===
[[File:Talend MDM.gif|thumb|[[software]] Talend Open Studio for MDM Screenshot]]
* ''Talend Cloud'': a unified platform for data integration, data quality, master data management and enterprise service bus that enables integration in cloud deployments and hybrid environments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gardner|first=Dana|title=Talend open-source approach provides holistic integration capability across, data, devices, services|url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/gardner/talend-open-source-approach-provides-holistic-integration-capability-across-data-devices-services/4245|work=ZD Net|publisher=ZD Net|accessdate=June 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Dubray|first=Jean-Jacques|title=Talend Releases a Cloud Version of its Unified Integration Platform|url=http://www.infoq.com/news/2011/06/talend-cloud-uip|work=InfoQ|publisher=InfoQ|accessdate=June 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Vaughan|first=Jack|title=Integration platform set for cloud, on-premise and hybrid setups|url=http://searchsoa.techtarget.com/news/2240036932/Unified-integration-platform-set-for-cloud-on-premise-and-hybrid-computing|work=SearchSOA.com|publisher=SearchSOA.com|accessdate=June 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kanaracus|first=Chris|title=Options for cloud, SaaS data integration grow|url=http://www.networkworld.com/news/2011/060811-options-for-cloud-saas-data.html?hpg1=bn|work=Network World|publisher=Network World|accessdate=June 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Community ==
Talend publishes the code of its core modules under the [[GNU Public License]] or the [[Apache License]]. Talend is also a contributor to key open source projects, and a member of the [[Eclipse Foundation]] and the [[Apache Software Foundation]] (ASF).

Talend sponsors the Apache Software Foundation which has been instrumental in fostering open source adoption and providing structure to build successful open source communities.

Talend is part of the [[Java Community Process]] (JCP) and is a Strategic Developer Member of the Eclipse Foundation, a Corporate Member of OW2, and has active involvement in the OASIS project.

[[Java]] is the development language of Talend’s products and solutions.

== Partners ==
* [[Cloudera]]
* [http://www.hortonworks.com Hortonworks]
* [[Jaspersoft]]
* [http://www.teradata.com Teradata]
* [[Netezza]]
* [[Greenplum]]
* [[Vertica]]
* [http://www.uniserv.com/en/news-data-quality/news2011/aktuelles_040.php Uniserv]
* [[Bonitasoft]]
* [[Google]]

== Competitors ==
Talend competitors include but are not limited to:
* Application Integration: [[IBM]], [[Oracle corporation|Oracle]], [[Software AG]], [[TIBCO]], [[Progress Software]], [[SnapLogic]]
* Data Management: [[Informatica]], [[IBM]], [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]], [[Red Hat]]
* ESB: [[MuleSoft]], [[Fusesource]], [[WSO2]]

== License ==
Talend uses the [[open core]] [[business model]].&lt;ref&gt;Aslett,Matthew (2009-07-08) [http://web.archive.org/web/20100801004103/http://blogs.the451group.com/opensource/2009/07/08/what-is-open-core-licensing-and-what-isnt/ What is Open Core Licensing (and what isn’t)]. blogs.the451group.com&lt;/ref&gt; It provides core functionality under the GPL v2 and Apache open source licenses, and value added features and services under a commercial subscription license.

The commercial subscription license includes:
* Access to value added features (such as teamwork, [[Load balancing (computing)|load balancing]], [[Network monitoring|monitoring]])
* Technical support
* IP indemnification (legal protection)

== See also ==
* [[Talendforge]]

== References ==
{{reflist|35em}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Talend}}
* [http://www.talend.com/ Official web site]
* [https://help.talend.com/ Talend Help Center: provides latest online documentation and knowledge base]

[[Category:Enterprise application integration]]
[[Category:Business intelligence]]
[[Category:Software companies based in California]]
[[Category:Data warehousing products]]
[[Category:Talend|*]]
[[Category:Big Data]]</text>
      <sha1>45eg8fd5qwynn4xb9ng64urxlg812wp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>