<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Terracotta, Inc.</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32708406</id>
    <revision>
      <id>559105743</id>
      <parentid>553783498</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-09T19:03:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (9241)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{infobox company
| industry = [[software|Computer Software]]
| foundation = [[San Francisco, California]], 2003
| parent = [[Software AG]]
| products = BigMemory&lt;br /&gt;Enterprise Ehcache&lt;br /&gt;Quartz Scheduler&lt;br /&gt;Web Sessions&lt;br /&gt;Terracotta Enterprise Suite&lt;br /&gt;In-Genius
| num_employees = {{formatnum:50-100}}
| website = [http://terracotta.org/ www.terracotta.org]
}}
'''Terracotta, Inc.''' is a computer software company that specializes in increasing scalability, availability, and performance of real-time [[Big Data]] applications. The company's flagship product is BigMemory, an in-memory data management suite. Terracotta software is used in 190 countries on 500,000+ deployments by more than one million developers. The company is owned by [[Software AG]].

== History ==
Terracotta began as a provider of [[cluster (computing)|clustering]] technologies for Java intended to simplify development, deployment, testing and management of enterprise applications by moving clustering and caching services to the Java Virtual Machine (JVM) instead of the application. 

In August 2009, Terracotta purchased [[Ehcache]]. The company expanded the capabilities of Ehcache and developed enterprise-class products based on the open source project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Luck|first=Greg|title=Ehcache: The Year In Review|url=http://gregluck.com/blog/archives/2010/12/ehcache-the-year-in-review/|work=Greg Luck's Blog|publisher=Greg Luck}}&lt;/ref&gt;   That year, Terracotta also acquired Quartz, the de facto standard job scheduler for Java. 

[[Software AG]] acquired Terracotta in May 2011. Wolfram Jost, CTO of Software AG, cited Terracotta’s scalability, performance, cloud enablement and in-memory strategy as the most critical factors for the acquisition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bruno|first=Eric J.|title=Software AG / Terracotta at Process World 2011|url=http://drdobbs.com/blogs/java/231001154|work=Drdobbs.com|publisher=UBM}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Terracotta is the in-memory technology in the Software AG product stack. Additionally, its in-memory processing provides the foundation for Software AG’s cloud offerings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Software AG Acquires Terracotta Inc., a Leader in In-Memory and Cloud Enabling Technology|url=http://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20110522005123/en/Software-AG-Acquires-Terracotta-Leader-In-Memory-Cloud|work=Business Wire|publisher=Berkshire Hathaway}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Products and Projects ==
* '''BigMemory''': a commercial in-memory data management suite for real-time Big Data applications that stores up to hundreds of terabytes in distributed memory across multiple servers without performance hits from the Java garbage collector
* '''[[Ehcache]]''': an open source, standards-based cache used to boost performance, offload the database and simplify scalability&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ehcache Overview|url=http://ehcache.org/about|work=Ehcache.org|publisher=Ehcache for Terracotta}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''Enterprise Ehcache''': a commercial product based on the open source Ehcache project
* '''Quartz''': an open source job scheduling service
:'''Quartz Scheduler''': a commercial product, based on the open source Quartz project
* '''Web Sessions''': a commercial product that provides high availability for Java Servlet Sessions, allowing user session data to survive server restarts and failures&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Terracotta for Web Sessions|url=http://terracotta.org/products/web-sessions|work=Terracotta.org|publisher=Terracotta}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Terracotta Enterprise Suite''': a commercial product that includes Enterprise Ehcache, Web Sessions and Quartz Scheduler
* '''In-Genius''': a native, in-memory platform for real-time insight and intelligent action on Big Data. General availability is planned for the third quarter of calendar 2013

== Community ==
In addition to selling commercial solutions, Terracotta leads several [[open source]] projects, including [[Ehcache]], with source code available for anonymous access on Subversion. The software produced by these projects is used by an active community of over one million developers across 190 countries on 2.5 million deployments. Terracotta provides a number of resources to facilitate communication amongst these users:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Terracotta Community|url=http://terracotta.org/community|work=Terracotta.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* '''Forums''': free discussion boards where users can post questions as they integrate Terracotta with their application
* '''Email lists''': special interest email groups
* '''Jira BugTracker''': an issue and feature tracking application where users can post issues or feature requests and see a work schedule for the development community

== Awards ==
* DataWeek's 2012 Big Data Technology Top Innovator Award&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Terracotta BigMemory Wins 2012 Big Data Technology Top Innovator Award|url=http://www.terracotta.org/news/press-releases/2012/2012-09-04-terracotta-bigmemory-wins-2012-big-data-technology-award|work=Terracotta.org|publisher=Terracotta}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
* [http://terracotta.org/ Official Terracotta Website]
* [http://ehcache.org/ Official Ehcache Website]
* [http://www.quartz-scheduler.org/ Official Quartz Website]
* [http://www.softwareag.com/corporate/default.asp Official Software AG Website]
 

&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;

[[Category:Java platform software]]
[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Software companies based in California]]</text>
      <sha1>a2qujywwhmhyu05anjn3l6j3ynuw7sm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>