<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Tervela</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25337256</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562422219</id>
      <parentid>495630767</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-01T17:27:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.177.64.39</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Corrects ISBN</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Company |
company_name = Tervela |
company_type = [[Private company|Private]] |
homepage = [http://www.tervela.com www.tervela.com] |
}}
'''Tervela Inc.''' is a privately held technology company based in [[New York City|New York]], [[New York]] and [[Acton, Massachusetts]]. The company is backed by [[Goldman Sachs]], [http://www.sigmapartners.com/ Sigma Partners], [[Acartha Technology Group]], and [[North Hill Ventures]]. Tervela was founded by Barry Thompson and Kul Singh.

== History ==

Tervela was founded in 2004, at the beginning of a massive transformation in the way businesses built and operated high-performance distributed applications. Tervela's Data Fabric consists of both hardware appliances and software (virtual) appliances that overlay on top of existing data center infrastructure and cloud services.  The company introduced the first hardware accelerated messaging switch in 2007 prior to this hardware accelerated message switching was done primarily on XML data. In 2009 the company introduced several products that allowed scalable middleware to deliver messages incrementally scalable well into the millions of messages per second. In 2011 Tervela introduced a set of virtual appliances compatible with the hardware accelerated appliances. Tervela's message fabric begins to incorporate together in one set of middleware the different classification of messaging described in the Judith Hurwitz article ''Sorting Out Middleware''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|first=Judith|last=Hurwitz|url=http://www.dbmsmag.com/9801d04.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20061017153344/http://www.dbmsmag.com/9801d04.html|archivedate=2006-10-17|title=Sorting Out Middleware|accessdate=2011-06-15|publisher=DBMS 11.1|date=January, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;
This technology provides the underpinnings of the merger of big data with the cloud, ''Forrester: Big Data, Cloud will merge in 2011'' &lt;ref name="Forrester: Big Data, Cloud will merge in 2011"&gt;{{cite web | last=Harris | first=Derrick | authorlink=Derrick Harris | title=Forrester: Big Data, Cloud will merge in 2011 | publisher=Forrester | url=http://gigaom.com/cloud/forrester-big-data-cloud-will-merge-in-2011/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Products ==
Tervela provides both [http://www.tervela.com/data-fabric-components hardware and software appliances]. Hardware and software appliances are compatible with the APIs which consist of C, C++, C# JAVA and [[JMS]]. Downloads of the software (virtual appliances are available on the company website). Capacity of the data fabric can be increased by adding additional appliances. Information about messaging can be found in [[Enterprise Integration Patterns]] &lt;ref name="Enterprise Integration Patterns"&gt;{{cite book |last=Hohpe|first= &amp; Woolf | authorlink=Gregor Hohpe &amp; Bobby Woolf |title=Enterprise Integration Patterns|edition=8th printing |year=2004 |publisher=Addison Wesley|isbn=0321200683 101112 CRW 07 06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Message Switch ===
The TMX-500 Message Switch is the primary gateway appliance that applications use to communicate across the message fabric.

=== Persistence Engine ===
The TPE-500 is a storage engine that is embedded in the data fabric and optimized for message persistence and retrieval.

=== Provisioning and Management ===
The Tervela TPM-500 Provisioning &amp; Management System is the unified, comprehensive administrative platform for Tervela's Data Fabric.

=== Client API ===
The Tervela Client API is the interface to Tervela's Data Fabric and the vehicle by which your applications sends data to and receives data from other applications on the fabric.

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Technology companies]]</text>
      <sha1>9gwxcu96t4kcjziz5wix9aoh0y6ho1r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>