<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>The Joker: Devil's Advocate</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24245059</id>
    <revision>
      <id>545721673</id>
      <parentid>532443767</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-20T16:53:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 1 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q2891519]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox comic book title
&lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt; 
| title = The Joker : Devil's Advocate 
| image = Joker-devil's advocate.jpg
| caption = Cover to ''The Joker : Devil's Advocate''. Art by [[Graham Nolan]].
| schedule = 
| format = 
|1shot=y
| publisher = [[DC Comics]]
| date= [[1996 in comics|1996]]
| issues = 
| Superhero = y
| Genre = [[Crime fiction|Crime]], [[superhero]]
| main_char_team = [[Joker (comics)|The Joker]]&lt;BR&gt;[[Batman]]&lt;BR&gt;[[Robin (comics)|Robin]]&lt;BR&gt;[[James Gordon (comics)|James Gordon]]
| writers = [[Chuck Dixon]]
| artists = [[Graham Nolan]]
| letterers=[[John Constanza]]
| colorists=[[Pat Garrahy]]
| inkers = [[Scott Hanna]]
| creators = Chuck Dixon&lt;BR&gt;Graham Nolan
| editors = [[Scott Peterson (comics)|Scott Peterson]]
| TPB=The Joker : Devil's Advocate
| ISBN=1-56389-240-5
| TPB1=
| ISBN1=1563892804
| TPB2=
| ISBN2=
|subcat=Batman
|sort=Joker : Devil's Advocate
}}
'''''The Joker : Devil's Advocate''''' is a [[One-shot (comics)|one-shot]] [[superhero]] [[comic book]] written by [[Chuck Dixon]] and drawn by [[Graham Nolan]], published by [[DC Comics]] in 1996.&lt;ref name="advocate"&gt;[http://www.comics-db.com/comic-book/1022386-Joker_Devils_Advocate.html''The Joker : Devil's Advocate - The Big Database of Comic Books]&lt;/ref&gt; Several recurring characters of the [[Batman (comics)|Batman]] family appear in the story such as : [[Robin (comics)|Robin]], [[James Gordon (comics)|James Gordon]], [[Barbara Gordon]] and [[Alfred Pennyworth]].

==Plot Summary==
[[The United States of America|The United States]] post office issues a commemorative series of stamps featuring some of the great [[comedian]]s in [[American History]]. The Joker, greatly disgruntled by the fact that no stamp was printed in his name, vandalises the post office. Subsequently, a succession of death occurs in [[Gotham City]] as a result of licking the back of the stamps, and The Joker's gruesome grin is drawn on the victims faces. The Joker is caught by Batman and Robin while attempting to rob the post office's vault. The [[District Attorney]] seeks to hold The Joker responsible of all the crimes, and succeeds to do so in court, as The Clown Prince of Crime is sentenced to death for the first time, after many inane attempts to get away with an insanity plea. The Joker is offended of being accused of such ludicrous crime, considering that a mastermind like him, will operate on a much smarter level, and therefore considers himself innocent. However, Batman is convinced as well that he is guiltless, and aims to prove it. A scrap of paper is found, with a partial address on it. After finding out that it's a storage container, the police break in and finds a hoard of [[Joker venom]]. Further investigation leads to the discovery of a man linked to the storage company, which happened to be the husband of a former victim. As he is questioned by the police, he confesses everything holding himself responsible for the crime, and The Joker receives a pardon from the governor seconds before being electrocuted. As the story ends, The Joker is seen in [[Arkham Asylum]] expressing his joy at being alive, only to be shattered when Batman informs him that it's due to his investigation. The issue ends with a series of stamps, with The Joker's face on one of them.&lt;BR&gt;The plot revolves around Batman's devotion to justice, as he helps The Joker out, despite his numerous murders in the past.

==Characters==
*Batman
*Robin
*The Joker
*James Gordon
*Alfred Pennyworth
*Barbara Gordon
*[[Harvey Bullock (comics)|Harvey Bullock]]
*[[Renee Montoya|Renée Montoya]]
*[[Billy Pettit]]
*[[Sarah Essen-Gordon]]
*[[Stan Kitch]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Joker: Devil's Advocate}}</text>
      <sha1>hpyj4bh5zautu65qxguudrsrg76gq3k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>