<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>The Crystal Palace</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>81837</id>
    <revision>
      <id>563111974</id>
      <parentid>563111916</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-06T14:12:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GrindtXX</username>
        <id>12418561</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>/* External links */  what I meant</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Crystal Palace (disambiguation){{!}}Crystal Palace}}
{{Use  British English|date=June 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox building
| name                = The Crystal Palace
| former_names        = 
| alternate_names     = 
| image               = [[File:Crystal Palace General view from Water Temple.jpg|340px]]
| image_alt           = 
| caption             = The Crystal Palace at Sydenham (1854)
| map_type            = 
| map_alt             = 
| map_caption         = 
| altitude            = 
| building_type       = 
| architectural_style = 
| structural_system   = 
| cost                = 
| ren_cost            = 
| client              = 
| owner               = 
| current_tenants     = 
| landlord            = 
| address             = 
| location_town       = London
| location_country    = United Kingdom
| iso_region          = 
| coordinates_display = 
| latitude            = 
| longitude           = 
| latd                = 
| latm                = 
| lats                = 
| latNS               = 
| longd               = 
| longm               = 
| longs               = 
| longEW              = 
| coordinates         = 
{{Coord|51|25|20.26|N|0|4|32.84|W|region:GB|display=title}}
| start_date          = 
| completion_date     = 
| inauguration_date   = 
| renovation_date     = 
| demolition_date     = 
| destruction_date    = 
| height              = 
| diameter            = 
| antenna_spire       = 
| roof                = 
| top_floor           = 
| other_dimensions    = 
| floor_count         = 
| floor_area          = 
| seating_type        = 
| seating_capacity    = 
| elevator_count      = 
| main_contractor     = 
| architect           = [[Joseph Paxton]]
| architecture_firm   = 
| structural_engineer = 
| services_engineer   = 
| civil_engineer      = 
| other_designers     = 
| quantity_surveyor   = 
| awards              = 
| ren_architect       = 
| ren_firm            = 
| ren_str_engineer    = 
| ren_serv_engineer   = 
| ren_civ_engineer    = 
| ren_oth_designers   = 
| ren_qty_surveyor    = 
| ren_awards          = 
| url                 = 
| references          = 
}}

'''The Crystal Palace''' was a [[Cast iron|cast-iron]] and [[plate-glass]] building originally erected in [[Hyde Park, London]], England, to house the [[The Great Exhibition|Great Exhibition]] of 1851. More than 14,000 exhibitors from around the world gathered in the Palace's {{convert|990000|sqft|m2}} of exhibition space to display examples of the latest technology developed in the [[Industrial Revolution]]. Designed by [[Sir Joseph Paxton]], the Great Exhibition building was {{convert|1851|ft|m|0}} long, with an interior height of {{convert|128|ft|m|0}}.&lt;ref name="oregon"&gt;{{cite web |url = 
http://darkwing.uoregon.edu/~struct/resources/case_studies/case_studies_simplebeams/paxton_palace/paxton_palace.html| title = The Crystal Palace of Hyde Park|accessdate=4 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the recent invention of the [[cast plate glass]] method in 1848, which allowed for large sheets of cheap but strong glass, it was at the time the largest amount of glass ever seen in a building and astonished visitors with its clear walls and ceilings that did not require interior lights, thus a "Crystal Palace". 

After the exhibition, the building was rebuilt in an enlarged form on Penge Common next to [[Sydenham Hill]], an affluent South London suburb full of large villas. It  stood there from 1854 until its destruction by fire in 1936.  

The name ''Crystal Palace'' came from the playwright [[Douglas Jerrold]]. On 13 July 1850 he wrote in the satirical magazine [[Punch magazine|''Punch'']] as 'Mrs Amelia Mouser' about the forthcoming [[Great Exhibition of 1851]], referring to a ''palace of very crystal'', a name that was subsequently picked up and repeated even though the building had not been approved at that stage.&lt;ref&gt;The ''Punch'' issue of 13 July 1850 carried a contribution by Douglas Jerrold, writing as Mrs Amelia Mouser, which referred to a ''palace of very crystal''.{{cite book | title  =''Douglas Jerrold'' | first= Professor Michael | last = Slater | publisher= Duckworth | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-7156-2824-0 | page =243 | location = London}}  Other sources refer to the 2 November 1850 Punch issue bestowing the "Crystal Palace" name on the design by {{cite book | title  = Nineteenth-Century European Art: A Topical Dictionary | first = Terry  | last = Strieter | isbn = 0-313-29898-X| page = 50 | year = 1999 | publisher=Greenwood Press | location = Westport, Conn.}} (And {{cite web | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/london/content/articles/2004/08/10/cp_dinosaur_feature.shtml | title = Crystal Palace | quote = The term 'Crystal Palace' was first applied to Paxton's building by Punch in its issue of 2nd November 1850 |publisher=BBC  | accessdate =21 November 2007}}.) Punch had originally sided with ''The Times'' against the Exhibition committee's own proposal of a fixed brick structure, but featured the Crystal Palace heavily throughout 1851 (for example in {{cite web | title = Punch Issue 502 | url = http://www.hrionline.ac.uk/luceneweb/hri3/display.jsp?mode=sciper&amp;file=PU1-20.html&amp;reveal=issue_PU1-20-17}} included the article "Travels into the Interior of the Crystal Palace" of February 1851). Any earlier name has been lost, according to {{cite web | year = 2003 | title = Everything2 ''Crystal Palace'' Exhibition Building Design #251| url = http://everything2.com/index.pl?node=Crystal%20Palace}}. The use by Mrs Mouser was picked up by a reference in [[The Leader (English newspaper)|''The Leader'']], no.17, 20 July 1850 (p.1): "In more than one country we notice active preparations for sending inanimate representatives of trade and industry to take up their abode in the crystal palace which Mr.Paxton is to build for the Exposition of 1851." Source: [http://britishperiodicals.chadwyck.co.uk British Periodicals  database] or [http://ncse-viewpoint.cch.kcl.ac.uk/ Nineteenth Century Serials Edition]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The name was later used to denote this [[Crystal Palace, London|area of south London]] and the park that surrounds the site, home of the [[Crystal Palace National Sports Centre]]. A re-working of the building, known as [[Garden Palace|The Garden Palace]], was constructed in [[Sydney]] in 1879, but this building too was destroyed by fire.

==Original Hyde Park building==

===Conception===
{{refimprove section|date=November 2012}}
The huge, modular, wood,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | isbn = 0-485-11575-1 | year  = 2002 | first = Hermione | last = Hobhouse | title = The Crystal Palace and the Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All Nations |
 page = 34 | quote = It was essentially a [[modular]] building of iron, wood and glass, built of components which were meant to be recyclable. | publisher=Athlone | location = London}} The [[prefabricated]] parts 
were constructed in the manufacture's ironworks and sawmills (page 36).&lt;/ref&gt; glass and iron structure was originally erected in [[Hyde Park, London|Hyde Park]] in London to house The Great Exhibition of 1851, which showcased the products of many countries throughout the world.&lt;ref name="dukemag"&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.dukemagazine.duke.edu/dukemag/issues/111206/depgal2.html|title=
 The Great Exhibition of 1851|accessdate=30 July 2007 |publisher=Duke Magazine|date= 2006-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Commission in charge of mounting the Great Exhibition was established in January 1850, and it was decided at the outset that the entire project would be funded by public subscription. An executive Building Committee was quickly formed to oversee the design and construction of the exhibition building, comprising [[Isambard Kingdom Brunel]], [[Robert Stephenson]], renowned architects [[Charles Barry]] and [[Thomas Leverton Donaldson]], the [[Duke of Buccleuch]] and the [[Earl of Ellesmere]], and chaired by [[William Cubitt]]. By 15 March 1850 they were ready to invite submissions, which had to conform to several key specifications: the building had to be temporary, simple, as cheap as possible, and economical to build within the short time remaining before the Exhibition opening, which had already been scheduled for 1 May 1851.&lt;ref name="Kate Colquhoun 2004"&gt;Kate Colquhoun, ''A Thing In Disguise: The Visionary Life of Joseph Paxton'' (Harper Collins, 2004), Ch. 16&lt;/ref&gt;

Within three weeks, the committee had received some 245 entries, including 38 international submissions from Australia, the Netherlands, Belgium, Hanover, Switzerland, Brunswick, Hamburg and France. Two designs, both in iron and glass, were singled out for praise - one by Richard Turner, co-designer of the [[Palm House]] at Kew, and the other by French architect [[Hector Horeau]]&lt;ref name=hrh&gt;{{cite book |title=Architecture:Nineteenth and Twentieth Centuries |last= Hitchcock|first=Henry-Russell |authorlink=Henry-Russell Hitchcock |coauthors= |year=1977 |publisher=Penguin Books |location=Harmondsworth |isbn=0-14-056115-3 |page=184 }}&lt;/ref&gt; but despite the great number of submissions, the Committee rejected them all. Turner was furious at the rejection, and reportedly badgered the commissioners for months afterwards, seeking compensation, but at an estimated £300,000, his design (like Horeau's) was too expensive.&lt;ref&gt;Kate Colquhoun, ''A Thing In Disguise: The Visionary Life of Joseph Paxton'' (Harper Collins, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt; As a last resort the committee came up with a standby design of its own, for a brick building in the ''[[rundbogenstil]]'' by Donaldson, featuring a sheet-iron dome designed by Brunel&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.victorianweb.org/history/1851/7.html Victorianweb, "The Committee's design for a structure to house the Great Exhibition"]&lt;/ref&gt; but it was widely criticized and ridiculed when it was published in the newspapers.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;[http://www.crystalpalacefoundation.org.uk/history/history-of-the-crystal-palace-part-1 The Crystal Palace Foundation, "History of the Crystal Palace, Part 1"]&lt;/ref&gt; Adding to the Committee's woes, the site for the Exhibition was still not confirmed; the preferred site was in [[Hyde Park, London|Hyde Park]], adjacent to Princes Gate near Kensington Rd, but other sites considered included [[Wormwood Scrubs]], [[Battersea Park]], the [[Isle of Dogs]], [[Victoria Park, London|Victoria Park]] and [[Regent's Park]]. Opponents of the scheme lobbied strenuously against the use of Hyde Park (and they were strongly supported by ''[[The Times]]''). The most outspoken critic was arch-conservative Col. [[Charles de Laet Waldo Sibthorp]]; he denounced the Exhibition as "one of the greatest humbugs, frauds and absurdities ever known",&lt;ref name="Kate Colquhoun 2004"/&gt; and his trenchant opposition to both the Exhibition and its building continued even after it had closed.

At this point renowned gardener [[Joseph Paxton]] became interested in the project, and with the enthusiastic backing of Commission member [[Henry Cole]], he decided to submit his own design. At this time, Paxton was chiefly known for his celebrated career as the head gardener for the [[William Cavendish, 6th Duke of Devonshire|6th Duke of Devonshire]] at [[Chatsworth House]]; by 1850 he had become a preeminent figure in British horticulture and had also earned great renown as a freelance garden designer - his works included the pioneering public gardens at [[Birkenhead Park]] which directly influenced [[Frederick_Law_Olmstead#New_York_City.27s_Central_Park|design of New York's Central Park]]. At Chatsworth, Paxton had experimented extensively with glasshouse construction, developing many novel techniques for modular construction, using combinations of standard-sized sheets of glass, [[laminated wood]], and prefabricated cast iron. The "Great Stove" (or conservatory) at Chatsworth (built in 1836) was the first major application of Paxton's now-famous ridge-and-furrow roof design, and was at the time the largest glass building in the world,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.victorianweb.org/victorian/art/architecture/iron/21b.html Victorianweb - The Great Stove, Chatsworth]&lt;/ref&gt; covering around 28,000 square feet (2600 sq.m.).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.victorianweb.org/art/architecture/iron/21b.html Victorianweb - The Great Stove, Chatsworth]&lt;/ref&gt; A decade later, taking advantage of the availability of the new [[cast plate glass]], Paxton further developed his techniques with the Chatsworth Lily House, which featured a flat-roof version of the ridge-and-furrow glazing, and a [[curtain wall]] system that allowed the hanging of vertical bays of glass from cantilevered beams.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.engineering-timelines.com/scripts/engineeringItem.asp?id=725 Engineering Timelines - Chatsworth Conservatory and Lily House]&lt;/ref&gt; The Lily House was built specifically to house the giant ''[[Victoria amazonica]]'' waterlily which had only recently been discovered by European botanists; the first specimen to reach England was originally kept at [[Kew Gardens]], but it did not do well. Paxton's reputation as a gardener was so high by that time that he was invited to take the lily to Chatsworth; it thrived under his care and in 1849 he caused a sensation in the horticultural world when he succeeded in producing the first ''amazonica'' flowers to be grown in England (his daughter Alice was famously drawn for the newspapers, standing on one of leaves). The lily and its house led directly to Paxton's design for the Crystal Palace and he later cited the huge ribbed floating leaves as a key inspiration.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.virtualherbarium.org/gardenviews/victoriaamazonica.html Jennifer Davit, "Victoria: The Reigning Queen of Waterlilies", Virtual Herbarium]&lt;/ref&gt;

Paxton left his 9 June 1850 meeting with Henry Cole fired with enthusiasm. He immediately went to Hyde Park, where he 'walked' the site earmarked for the Exhibition. Two days later, on 11 June, while attending a board meeting of the Midland Railway, Paxton made his original concept drawing, which he famously doodled onto a sheet of pink [[blotting paper]]. This rough sketch (now in the [[Victoria &amp; Albert Museum]]) incorporated all the basic features of the finished building, and it is a mark of Paxton's ingenuity and industriousness that detailed plans, calculations and costings were ready to submit in less than two weeks.

The project was a major gamble for Paxton, but circumstances were in his favour - he enjoyed a stellar reputation as a garden designer and builder, he was confident that his design was perfectly suited to the brief, and the Commission was now under enormous pressure to choose a design and get it built - the Exhibition opening was now less than a year away. In the event, Paxton's design fulfilled and surpassed all the requirements, and it proved to be vastly faster and cheaper to build than any other form of building of a comparable size. Indeed, his submission was budgeted at a remarkably low £85,800 - by comparison, this was only about 2-1/2 times more than the Great Stove at Chatsworth&lt;ref&gt;"Paxton and the Great Stove", ''Architectural History'', Vol. 4, (1961), pp. 77-92&lt;/ref&gt; but it was only 28% of the estimated cost of Turner's design, and it promised a building which, with a footprint of over 770,000 sq.ft. (19 acres, or 7 hectares), would cover roughly twenty-five times the ground area of its progenitor.

Impressed by the low bid for the construction contract submitted by the engineering firm Fox, Henderson, the commission accepted the scheme and finally gave its public endorsement to Paxton's design in July 1850. He was exultant, but now had less than eight months to finalize his plans, manufacture the parts and erect the building in time for the Exhibition's opening, which was scheduled for 1 May 1851. Paxton was able to design and build the largest glass structure yet created, from scratch, in less than a year, and complete it on schedule and on budget. He was even able to alter the design shortly before building began, adding a high, barrel-vaulted [[transept]] across the centre of the building, at 90 degrees to the main gallery, under which he was able to safely enclose several large elm trees that would otherwise have had to be felled - thereby also resolving a controversial issue that had been a major sticking point for the vocal anti-Exhibition lobby.

===Design===

Paxton's modular, hierarchical design reflected his practical brilliance as a designer and problem-solver. It incorporated many breakthroughs, offered practical advantages that no conventional building could match and, above all, embodied the spirit of British innovation and industrial might that the Great Exhibition was intended to celebrate.

The geometry of the Crystal Palace was a classic example of the concept of form following function - the shape and size of the whole building was directly based around the size of the panes of glass made by the supplier, Chance Brothers of Birmingham. These were the largest available at the time, measuring 10 inches wide by 49 inches long. Because the entire building was scaled around those dimensions, it meant that nearly the whole outer surface could be glazed using millions of identical panes, thereby drastically reducing both their production cost and the time needed to install them.

The original Hyde Park building was essentially a vast, flat-roofed rectangular hall. A huge open gallery ran along the main axis, with wings extending down either side. The main exhibition space was two stories high, with the upper floor stepped in from the boundary. Most of the building had a flat-profile roof, except for the central transept, which was covered by a barrel-vaulted roof that stood 100 feet high at the top of the arch. Both the flat-profile sections and the arched transept roof were constructed using the key element of Paxton's design - his patented ridge-and-furrow roofing system, which had first use at Chatsworth. The basic roofing unit, in essence, took the form of a long triangular prism, which made it both extremely light and very strong, and meant it could be built with the minimum amount of materials. 

Paxton set the dimensions of this prism by using the length of single pane of glass (49 inches) as the [[hypotenuse]] of a right-angled triangle, thereby creating a triangle with a length-to-height ratio of 2.5:1, whose base (adjacent side) was 4 feet long. By mirroring this triangle he obtained the 8-foot-wide gables that formed the vertical faces at either end of the prism, each of which was 24' long. With this arrangement, Paxton could glaze the entire roof surface with identical panes that did not need to be trimmed. Paxton placed three of these 8' x 24' roof units side-by-side, horizontally supported by a grid of cast iron beams, which was held up on slim cast iron pillars. The resulting cube, with a floor area of 24'x 24', formed the basic structural module of the building. 

By multiplying these modules into a grid, the structure could be extended virtually infinitely. In its original form, the ground level of the Crystal Palace (in plan) measured 1848' x 456', which equates to a grid 77 modules long by 19 modules wide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.iath.virginia.edu/london/model/geo.html "The Crystal Palace" website, University of Virginia Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities]&lt;/ref&gt; Because each module was self-supporting, Paxton was able to leave out modules in some areas, creating larger square or rectangular spaces within the building to accommodate larger exhibits. On the lower level these larger spaces were covered by the floor above, and on the upper level by longer spans of roofing, but the dimensions of these larger spaces were always multiples of the basic 24' x 24' grid unit. The modules were also strong enough to be stacked vertically, enabling Paxton to add an upper floor that nearly doubled the amount of available exhibition space. Paxton also used longer  trellis girders to create a clear span for the roof of the immense central gallery, which was 72 feet wide and 1800 feet long.

Paxton's roofing system incorporated his elegant solution to the problem of draining the building's vast roof area. Like the Chatsworth Lily House (but unlike its later incarnation at Sydnenham) most of the roof of the original Hyde Park structure had a horizontal profile, so heavy rain posed a potentially serious safety hazard. Because normal cast glass is brittle and has low tensile strength, there was a risk that the weight of any excess water build-up on the roof might have caused panes to shatter, showering shards of glass onto the patrons, ruining the valuable exhibits beneath, and weakening the structure. However, Paxton's ridge-and-furrow roof was designed to shed water very efficiently. Rain ran off the angled glass roof panes into U-shaped cast-iron channels which ran the length of each roof section at the bottom of the 'furrow'. These channels were ingeniously multifunctional - during construction, they served as the rails that supported and guided the trolleys on which the glaziers sat as they installed the roofing. Once completed, the channels acted both as the joists that supported the roof sections, and as guttering - a patented design now widely known as a "Paxton gutter". These gutters conducted the rainwater to the ends of each furrow, where they emptied into the larger main gutters, which were set at right angles to the smaller gutters, along the top of the main horizontal roof bearers. These main gutters drained at either end into the cast iron pillars, which also had an ingenious dual function - each was cast with a hollow core, allowing it to double as a concealed down-pipe that carried the storm-water down into the drains beneath the building.

One of the few issues Paxton could not completely solve was leaks - when completed, rain was found to be leaking into the huge building in over a thousand places. The leaks were sealed with putty, but the relatively poor quality of the sealant materials available at the time meant that the problem was never totally overcome.

Maintaining a comfortable temperature inside such a large glass building was another major challenge, because the Great Exhibition took place decades before the introduction of mains electricity and air-conditioning. Glasshouses rely on the fact that they accumulate and retain heat from the sun, but such heat buildup would have been a major problem for the Exhibition, and this would have been be exacerbated by the heat produced by the thousands of people who would be in the building at any given time. Paxton solved this with two clever strategies. One was to install external canvas shade-cloths that were stretched across the roof ridges. These served multiple functions - they reduced heat transmission, moderated and softened the light coming into the building, and acted as a primitive evaporative cooling system when water was sprayed onto them. The other part of the solution was Paxton's ingenious ventilation system. Each of the modules that formed the outer walls of the building was fitted with a prefabricated set of louvres that could be opened and closed using a gear mechanism, allowing hot stale air to escape. The flooring consisted of boards 22&amp;nbsp;cm (9 inches) wide, which were spaced about 1&amp;nbsp;cm apart; together with the louvres, this formed an effective passive air-conditioning system. Due to the pressure differential, the hot air escaping from the louvres generated a constant airflow that drew cooler air up through the gaps in the floor. The floor too had a dual function - the gaps between the boards acted as a grating that allowed dust and small pieces of refuse to fall or be swept through them onto the ground beneath, where it was collected daily by a team of cleaning boys. Paxton also designed machines to sweep the floors at the end of each day, but in practice, it was found that the trailing skirts of the female visitors did the job perfectly.&lt;ref name="bl.uk"&gt;[http://www.bl.uk/learning/timeline/item106135.html British Library - Sketch for the Crystal Palace]&lt;/ref&gt;

Thanks to the considerable economies of scale Paxton was able to exploit, the manufacture and assembly of the building parts was exceedingly quick and cheap. Each module was identical, fully prefabricated, self-supporting, and fast and easy to erect. All of the parts could be mass-produced in large numbers, and many parts served multiple functions, further reducing both the number of parts needed and their overall cost. Because of its comparatively low weight, the Crystal Palace required absolutely no heavy masonry for supporting walls or foundations, and the relatively light concrete footings on which it stood could be left in the ground once the building was removed (they remain in place today just beneath the surface of the site). The modules could be erected as quickly as the parts could reach the site - indeed, some sections were standing within eighteen hours of leaving the factory - and since each unit was self-supporting, workers were able to assemble much of the building section-by-section, without having to wait for other parts to be finished.

===Construction===
Fox, Henderson took possession of the site in July 1850 and erected wooden hoardings which, with typical Victorian efficiency, were constructed using the timber that later became the floorboards of the finished building. More than 5000 [[navvy|navvies]] worked on building during its construction, with up to 2000 on site at one time during the peak building phase. More than 1,000 iron columns supported 2,224 trellis girders and 30 miles of guttering, comprising 4,000 tonnes of iron in all.&lt;ref name="bl.uk"/&gt; 

First, stakes were driven into the ground to roughly mark out the positions for the cast iron columns; these points were then set precisely by [[theodolite]] measurements. Then the concrete foundations were poured, and the base plates for the columns were set into them. Once the foundations were in place, the erection of the modules proceeded rapidly. Connector brackets were attached to the top of each column before erection, and these were then hoisted into position. Since the project took place before the development of powered cranes, the raising of the columns was done manually using [[sheers]] (or shear-legs), a simple crane mechanism. These consisted of two strong poles, which were set several metres apart at the base and then lashed together at the top to form a triangle; this was stabilized and kept vertical by guy ropes fixed to the apex, stretched taut and tied to stakes driven into the ground some distance away. Using pulleys and ropes hung from the apex of the sheer, the navvies hoisted the columns, girders and other parts into place.

As soon as two adjacent columns had been erected, a girder was hoisted into place between them and bolted onto the connectors. The columns were erected in opposite pairs, then two more girders were connected to form a self-supporting square  - this was the basic frame of each module. The sheers would then be moved along and an adjoining bay constructed. When a reasonable number of bays had been completed, the columns for the upper floor were erected (longer shear-legs were used for this, but the operation was essentially the same as for the ground floor). Once the ground floor structure was complete, the final assembly of the upper floor followed rapidly.

For the glazing, Paxton used larger versions of machines he had originally devised for the Great Stove at Chatsworth, installing on-site [[production line]] systems, powered by steam engines, that dressed and finished the building parts. These included a machine that mechanically grooved the wooden window sash bars, and a painting machine that automatically dipped the parts in paint and then passed them through a series of rotating brushes to remove the excess.

The last major components to be put into place were the sixteen semi-circular ribs of the vaulted transept, which were also the only major structural parts  that were made of wood. These were raised into position as eight pairs, and all were fixed into place within a week. Thanks to the simplicity of Paxton's design and the combined efficiency of the building contractor and their suppliers, the entire structure was assembled with extraordinary speed - the team of 80 glaziers could fix more than 18,000 panes of sheet glass in a week&lt;ref name="bl.uk"/&gt; - and the building was complete and ready to receive exhibits in just five months.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;

When completed, The Crystal Palace provided an unrivaled space for exhibits, since it was essentially a self-supporting shell standing on slim iron columns, with no internal structural walls whatsoever. Because it was covered almost entirely in glass, it also needed no artificial lighting during the day, thereby reducing the Exhibition's running costs.

Paxton was acclaimed worldwide for his achievement, and was knighted by Queen Victoria in recognition of his work. The project was engineered by [[William Cubitt|Sir William Cubitt]]; Paxton's construction partner was the ironwork contractor [[Charles Fox (civil and railway engineer)|Sir Charles Fox]]'s Fox and Henderson, whose director Charles Fox was also knighted for his contribution. The 900,000 square feet (84,000&amp;nbsp;m²) of glass was provided by the [[Chance Brothers]] glassworks in [[Smethwick]], Birmingham. They were the only glassworks capable of fulfilling such a large order and had to bring in labour from France to meet it in time.&lt;!--(The [[Hyde Park, London#Poem|Hyde Park]] article features a poem
 written about this construction.)--&gt;The final dimensions were {{convert|1848|ft|m}} long by {{convert|456|ft|m}} wide. The building was {{convert|135|ft|m}} high, with {{convert|772784|sqft|m2}} on the ground floor alone.&lt;ref&gt;Hunt, Lynn, Thomas R. Martin, and Barbara H. Rosenwein. The Making of the West: Peoples and Cultures. Boston/New York: Bedford/St. Martin's, 2009. P 685.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Crystal Palace was built by about 5,000 [[Navvy|navvies]] (up to 2,000 on site at once).&lt;ref&gt;For the peak figure of 2,000 workers daily see: {{cite book | isbn = 0-485-11575-1 | title = The Crystal Palace and the Great Exhibition | page = 34 | author=Hermione Hobhouse. | year = 2002 | publisher=Athlone | location = London }} and the University of Virginia's {{cite web | url = 
http://www.arts.gla.ac.uk/allcach2k/Programme/session1.html | title = Modeling the Crystal Palace | year = 2001 }} project: {{cite web | url = http://www.iath.virginia.edu/london/model/animation.html# | title = 
''The Crystal Palace Animation'' Exterior and Interior | accessdate =20 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Full-size elm trees growing in the park were enclosed within the central exhibition hall near the {{convert|27|ft|m|0|sing=on}} tall Crystal Fountain. [[Sparrows]] became a nuisance; shooting was obviously out of the question in a glass building. [[Queen Victoria]] mentioned this problem to the [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Duke of Wellington]], who offered the famous solution, "[[Eurasian Sparrowhawk|Sparrowhawk]]s, Ma'am". 

The Crystal Palace had the first major installation of [[public toilet]]s,&lt;ref name="bounce"&gt;{{cite book| title= Why does a ball bounce?: 101 questions you never thought of asking |first= Adam |last= Hart-Davis |publisher=Firefly Books |date= 3 October 2005 |isbn= 978-1-55407-113-5 |page = 59 |chapter= 25. Where does "spend a penny" come from? }}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''Retiring Rooms'', in which [[sanitary engineering|sanitary engineer]] [[George Jennings]] installed his [[water closet|"Monkey Closet" flushing lavatory]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title= Now You Know Big Book of Answers |volume= 2  |first= Doug |last= Lennox  |publisher=Dundurn  |date= 2 September 2008 |isbn= 978-1-55002-871-3 |page = 242 |chapter= Where is an Englishman going when he's going to "spend a penny"? }}&lt;/ref&gt; (initially just for men, but later catering for women also).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title= Inclusive urban design: public toilets   |first= Clara |last= Greed |publisher=[[University of British Columbia]] Press |year= 2003 |month = August |isbn= 978-0-7506-5385-5 |edition= first |page = 42 |chapter= The emergence of modern public toilets |quote= Apparently, public provision was not initially provided for women, only men, and a meeting of the RSA (Royal Society of Arts), the [1851 Great Exhibition] organising body, was hurriedly convened to provide more }}&lt;/ref&gt; During the exhibition, 827,280 visitors each [[Penny#Idioms|paid one penny]] to use them.&lt;ref name="Thunder"&gt;{{cite book |oclc= 37934946 |title= Thunder, flush, and Thomas Crapper: an encycloopedia |first= A. |last= Hart-Davis |publisher=Trafalgar Square |date= 28 February 2007 |isbn= 978-1-57076-081-5 |quote= public lavatories for men and women }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title= The culture of flushing: a social and legal history of sewage |first= Jamie |last= Benidickson |publisher=[[University of British Columbia]] Press |date= 28 February 2007 |isbn= 978-0-7748-1291-7 |page = 90 |chapter= The Water Closet Revolution |quote= roughly 14 percent of the six million visitors to the exhibition demonstrated a willingness to 'spend a penny' for such amenities }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Relocation ==
[[File:1854-CrystalPalaceMedallion.jpg|thumb|Relocation commemorative medallion.]]
[[File:Crystal Palace.PNG|thumb|right|250px|The transept façade of the Crystal Palace]]
The life of the Great Exhibition was limited to six months, after which something had to be done with the building.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.crystalpalacefoundation.org.uk/history/default.asp?ID=10 | title = Crystal Palace history ''Leaving Hyde Park'' October 1851}}&lt;/ref&gt; Against the wishes of [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|Parliamentary]] opponents, a consortium of eight businessmen including [[Samuel Laing (science writer)|Samuel Laing]] and [[Leo Schuster]] (both board members of the [[London, Brighton and South Coast Railway|London, Brighton and South Coast Railway (LB&amp;SCR)]]), formed a suitable holding company and proposed that the edifice be erected on a property named Penge Place that had been excised from [[Penge Common]] atop Sydenham Hill.&lt;ref name="dukemag"/&gt;

The building constructed in 1854 on Sydenham Hill, while incorporating most of the constructional parts of the Hyde Park building, was so completely different in form as to be properly considered a quite different structure – a 'Beaux-arts' form in glass and metal. The main gallery was redesigned and covered with a new barrel-vaulted roof, the central transept was greatly enlarged and made even higher, and two new transepts were added at either end of the main gallery. It was modified and enlarged so much that it extended beyond the boundary of Penge Place, which was also the boundary between [[Surrey]] and [[Kent]]. Within two years, [[Victoria of the United Kingdom|Queen Victoria]] again performed an opening [[ceremony]]. On the new site the buildings housed the [[Crystal Palace School|Crystal Palace School of Art, Science, and Literature]] and in the performance spaces hosted concerts, exhibits, and public entertainment.&lt;ref name="dukemag"/&gt; The new site was also the location of one of [[Charles Spurgeon]]'s famous sermons, without amplification, before a crowd of 23,654 people on 7 October 1857.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.charlesspurgeon.net/page5.html "The Prince of Preachers" Live!] at charlesspurgeon.net (Dave Richards evangelical site)&lt;/ref&gt; The reconstruction was recorded for posterity by [[Philip Henry Delamotte]], and his photographs were widely disseminated in his published works.

Several localities claim to be the area to which the building was moved. The street address of the Crystal Palace was Sydenham S.E. (SE26 after 1917), but the actual building and parklands were in Penge.  When built, most of the buildings were in the borough of [[Croydon]], as were the majority of grounds, but in 1899 the county boundary was moved, transferring the entire site to [[Penge Urban District]] in Kent. The site is now within the Crystal Palace Ward of the [[London Borough of Bromley]].

Two [[railway stations]] were opened to serve the permanent exhibition:
*[[Crystal Palace (High Level) railway station|Crystal Palace High Level]]: developed by the SER, it was an impressive building designed by [[Edward Middleton Barry|Edward Barry]], from which a subway under the Parade led directly to the entrance
*[[Crystal Palace railway station|Crystal Palace Low Level]]: developed by laing and Schuster's LB&amp;SCR, it is located just off Anerley Road.

The Low Level Station is still in use as {{stnlnk|Crystal Palace}}, while the only remains of the High Level Station are the subway under the Parade with its [[Italy|Italian]] [[mosaic]] roofing, a Grade II [[listed building]].

The South Gate is served by [[Penge West Railway Station]]. For some time this station was on an [[atmospheric railway]]. This is often confused with a 550-metre pneumatic passenger railway which was exhibited at the Crystal Palace in 1864, which was known as the [[Crystal Palace pneumatic railway]].

== Water features ==
[[File:Iguanodon Crystal Palace.jpg|thumb|An 1853 model of an [[Iguanodon]]; the most recognisable of the [[Crystal Palace Dinosaurs]] ]]
Joseph Paxton was first and foremost a gardener, and his layout of gardens, [[fountain]]s, [[Terrace (gardening)|terrace]]s and [[Plunge waterfalls|cascades]] left no doubt as to his ability. One thing he did have a problem with was water supply. Such was his enthusiasm that thousands of gallons of water were needed to feed the myriad fountains and cascades abounding in the Crystal Palace park: the two main jets were {{convert|250|ft|m|0}} high.  [[Water tower]]s were duly constructed, but the weight of water in the raised tanks caused them to collapse. [[Isambard Kingdom Brunel]] was consulted and came up with plans for two mighty water towers, one at the north end of the building and one at the south. Each supported a tremendous load of water, which was gathered from three reservoirs, at either end of and in the middle of the park.

Two years later, the grand fountains and cascades were opened, again in the presence of the Queen, who got wet when a gust of wind swept mists of spray over the Royal carriage.

==Later years==
[[File:The Crystal Palace grounds.jpg|right|thumb|An 1862 map of the grounds of The Crystal Palace]]
While the original palace cost £150,000 (£{{Formatprice|{{Inflation|UK|150000|1851|{{CURRENTYEAR}}|r=-4}}}} as of {{CURRENTYEAR}}),{{Inflation-fn|UK}} the move to Sydenham cost £1,300,000—(£{{Formatprice|{{Inflation|UK|1300000|1853|{{CURRENTYEAR}}|r=-4}}}} as of {{CURRENTYEAR}}),{{Inflation-fn|UK}} burdening the company with a debt it never repaid,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.crystalpalacefoundation.org.uk/history/default.asp?ID=11 | title = Crystal Palace history'' The Building'' 1852–1854| accessdate =21 November 2007}} These amounts are in successive years, and partly reflect the extension to five stories made at Sydenham. The £150,000 cost of the Hyde Park Crystal Palace includes the (re-usable) component material cost, so the extent to which the reconstructed Palace had an (unexpectedly) higher construction cost is even greater than the comparison of totals implies.&lt;/ref&gt; partly because admission fees were depressed by the inability to cater for Sunday visitors: many people worked every day except the [[Sabbath in Christianity|Sabbath]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/archives/m/memorial_from_the_national_sun.aspx | title = Memorial from the National Sunday League on the Sunday opening of the British Museum | quote = working men and their families [...] worked long hours and all day Saturday. Many could not afford a day's unpaid leave to come to the Museum. }}&lt;/ref&gt; when the Palace had always been closed.&lt;ref&gt;The Great Exhibition was always closed on Sunday, see: {{cite web | title = Crystal Palace – On a hot summer's day ''Facts and Figures'' | url = http://www.crystal.dircon.co.uk/mrskpg.htm | quote = No Sunday opening was allowed, no alcohol, no smoking and no dogs}}. The Crystal Palace at Sydenham continued the observance, opening only to [[shareholder]]s on Sundays: {{cite web | url = http://www.crystalpalacefoundation.org.uk/History/default.asp?ID=12 | title = Crystal Palace History ''Open again'' | quote = neither the building nor grounds were open on Sundays}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Lord's Day Observance Society]] held that people should not be encouraged to work at the Palace or drive on Sunday, and that if people wanted to visit, then their employers should give them time off during the working week. However, the Palace was open on Sundays by May 1861, when 40,000 visitors came.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=1W49qPQKJEwC&amp;dq=sunday+opening+%22palace+of+the+people%22+jan+piggott&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=web&amp;ots=i87UejAB5u&amp;sig=on_SjtKxiLSZKVfPQLq6RpFnoho Google Books: Palace of the People: The Crystal Palace at Sydenham 1854–1936]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1871, the world's first [[cat show]], organised by [[Harrison Weir]], was held at The Crystal Palace. 

By the 1890s the Palace's popularity and state of repair had deteriorated; the appearance of stalls and booths had made it a more downmarket attraction.&lt;ref name="disused"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.disused-stations.org.uk/c/crystal_palace_high_level/index.shtml
|title=Disused Stations: Crystal Palace High Level &amp; Upper Norwood Station
|publisher=www.disused-stations.org.uk
|accessdate=17 June 2010
|last= Catford |first= N.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 

A colourful description of a visit to the Crystal Palace appears in [[John Davidson (poet)|John Davidson's]] poem 'The Crystal Palace' published in 1909.

[[Robert Baden-Powell]] first noticed the interest of girls in [[Scouting]] while attending a [[Boy Scout]] meeting at Crystal Palace in 1909. This observation later led to the formation of [[Girl Guide and Girl Scout|Girl Guides, then Girl Scouts]].&lt;ref name="palacebp"&gt;{{cite web | coauthors = | year = 1997 | url = http://pinetreeweb.com/bp-pix76.htm | title = Baden-Powell and the Crystal Palace Rally | work=Baden-Powell Photo Gallery | publisher=Pinetree web| accessdate =22 January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="palacegs"&gt;{{cite web | coauthors = | year = 1997 | url = http://www.msc.edu.ph/gsp/histo1.html | title = History of the Girl Scouts Movement | publisher=Girl Scouts of the Philippines| accessdate =22 January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1911, the [[Festival of Empire]] was held at the building to mark the [[Coronation of the British monarch|coronation]] of [[George V of the United Kingdom|George V]] and [[Mary of Teck|Queen Mary]].

==Decline==
[[File:AnerleyHill2.jpg|thumb|right|150px|The Crystal Palace as seen from [[Anerley]] around 1910]]
In the years after the Festival of Empire the building fell into disrepair, as the huge debt and [[Corrective maintenance|maintenance]] costs became unsustainable, and in 1911 bankruptcy was declared.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/london/content/articles/2004/07/27/history_feature.shtml |title= Crystal Palace: A History |first= G. |last= Holland |date= 24 July 2004 |publisher=BBC }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1913 the [[Robert Windsor-Clive, 1st Earl of Plymouth|Earl of Plymouth]] bought it, to save it from developers. A public subscription subsequently bought it from the Earl for the nation.

During the First World War, it was used as a naval training establishment under the name of HMS ''Victory VI'', informally known as HMS ''Crystal Palace''. More than 125,000 men from the [[Royal Naval Division]], [[Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve]] and [[Royal Naval Air Service]] were trained for war at ''Victory VI''.&lt;ref name="crystalpalacefoundation.org.uk"&gt;[http://www.crystalpalacefoundation.org.uk/History/default ]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the cessation of hostilities it was re-opened as the first [[Imperial War Museum]], but traffic remained light.&lt;ref name="disused"/&gt; 

In the 1920s, a board of trustees was set up under the guidance of manager Sir Henry Buckland. He is said to have been a firm but fair man, who had a great love for the Crystal Palace,&lt;ref name="norwoodsociety.co.uk"&gt;{{cite web|author=The Norwood Society |url=http://www.norwoodsociety.co.uk/review/afterthefire.shtml |title=The Norwood Review |publisher=The Norwood Society |date=26 February 2008 |accessdate=17 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and soon set about restoring the deteriorating building. The restoration not only brought visitors back, but also meant that the Palace started to make a small profit once more.&lt;ref name="crystalpalacefoundation.org.uk"/&gt; Buckland and his staff also worked on improving the fountains and gardens,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.museumoflondon.org.uk/English/Collections/OnlineResources/X20L/THEMES/1381/112 ]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the Thursday evening displays of [[fireworks]] by [[Brocks]]. On 15–20 October 1934 the [[Pageant of Labour]] was held at the Crystal Palace.&lt;ref&gt;''Official Book and Programme of the Pageant of Labour'', 1934&lt;/ref&gt;

== Destruction by fire ==
[[File:Crystal Palace fire 1936.jpg|thumb|Crystal Palace on fire]]
On 30 November 1936 came the final catastrophe – [[conflagration|fire]]. Within hours the Palace was destroyed: the glow was visible across eight [[Administrative counties of England#Map 1890–1965|counties]].&lt;ref name="LifeFire"/&gt; That night, Buckland was walking his dog near the palace, with his daughter (Crystal Buckland, named after the palace&lt;ref name="LifeFire"&gt;{{cite journal |page= 34 |url= http://books.google.com/?id=PUEEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=34 |last= London
|journal=[[Life (magazine)|Life]] |title= London's Biggest Fire...|date= 21 December 1936 |quote= The Crystal Palace will never be rebuilt |year= 1936 issue.}}&lt;/ref&gt;) when they noticed a red glow within. Inside, he found two of his employees fighting a small office fire,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.crystalpalacefoundation.org.uk/History/default.asp?ID=6 |title= Disaster strikes |publisher=The Crystal Palace Foundation |year= 2010 |first= M. |last= Harrison |quote= The first fire brigade call was received by Penge fire station at 7:59&amp;nbsp;pm, the first fire engine arriving at 8:03. By the morning of Tuesday 1 December the building was no more}}&lt;/ref&gt; that had started after an explosion&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wardsbookofdays.com/1december.htm December 1st – On this day in history in 1936, the Crystal Palace burned down]&lt;/ref&gt; in the women's [[cloakroom]].&lt;ref name="LifeFire"/&gt; Realising that it was a serious fire, they called the Penge fire brigade. But, even though 89 [[fire engine]]s and over 400 firemen&lt;ref&gt;http://www.20thcenturylondon.org.uk/server.php?show=conlnformationRecord.16&lt;/ref&gt; arrived they were unable to extinguish it. (The fire spread quickly in the high winds that night,&lt;ref name="burningFilm"/&gt; because it could consume the dry old timber flooring,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.ideal-homes.org.uk/bromley/crystal-palace/crystal-palace-fire.htm |title= Crystal Palace On Fire, 1936 |quote= The cause of the fire that destroyed the Crystal Palace is unknown, although an electrical fault due to old wiring is suspected. }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the huge quantity of flammable materials in the building.) Buckland said, "In a few hours we have seen the end of the Crystal Palace. Yet it will live in the memories not only of Englishmen, but the whole world". 100,000 people came to Sydenham Hill to watch the blaze, among them [[Winston Churchill]], who said, "This is the end of an age".&lt;ref name="RT"&gt;
{{cite web
 |first1       = R. |last1        = White  |first2= J. |last2= Yorath 
 | title       = The Crystal Palace – Demise
 | url         = http://www.whitefiles.org/b3_q/1_architecture/zqla/qla7/7_xtlplc.htm 
 | work=The White Files – Architecture 
 | year        = 2004 
 | accessdate  =15 June 2010 
}} (Quotations from Yorath's original [[Radio Times]] article.)&lt;/ref&gt; 

Just as in 1866, when the north transept burnt down, the building was not adequately insured to cover the cost of rebuilding (at least two million pounds).&lt;ref name="burningFilm"&gt;{{cite web |url= http://newsfilm.bufvc.ac.uk/article.php?story=2005100819530392 |title= British Paramount News: Crystal Palace Fire |publisher=newsfilm online |date= 30 October 1936 |quote= Film of the fire that completely destroyed the Crystal Palace.}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The South Tower had been used for tests by television pioneer [[John Logie Baird]] for his mechanical television experiments, and much of his work was destroyed in the fire.&lt;ref name="trandsiffusion-baird"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.transdiffusion.org/emc/baird/baird_itv.php|title=Baird's independent television|last=Elen|first=Richard G|date=5 April 2003|accessdate=29 May 2008|publisher=Transdiffusion Broadcasting System}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="soundscapes-baird"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Herbert|first=Ray|year=1998|month=July|title=Crystal Palace Television Studios|journal=Soundscapes|volume=1|issue=4|publisher=University of Groningen|location=Groningen, The Netherlands|issn=1567-7745|url =http://www.icce.rug.nl/~soundscapes/VOLUME01/Crystal_Palace.shtml|accessdate =29 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The last singer to perform there before the fire was the Australian ballad contralto [[Essie Ackland]].&lt;ref name=weekly&gt;[http://trove.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/51587380?searchTerm=&amp;searchLimits=l-publictag=Essie+Ackland Australian Women’s Weekly, 6 March 1937]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Activity since the fire==
[[File:Crystal Palace Destoyed 1936.jpg|thumb|Crystal Palace a few days after the night of the 30 November 1936; totally destroyed]]
All that was left standing after the 1936 fire were the two water towers. In a November 2011 interview with the Crystal Palace Museum the true story of the towers was revealed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://crystalpalacemuseum.org.uk Crystal Palace Museum]&lt;/ref&gt; The south tower to the right of the Crystal Palace entrance was taken down shortly after the fire, as the damage sustained had undermined its integrity and it presented a major risk to houses nearby. 

The north tower was demolished with explosives in 1941.&lt;ref name="time-north-tower"&gt;{{cite journal|date=28 April 1941|title=War's Worst Raid|journal=[[Time (magazine)|TIME]]|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,765495,00.html|accessdate=29 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pescod-north-tower"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pescod|first=David FRS|title=Correspondence|date=10 February 2005|journal=The Linnean|volume=21|issue=2|page=36|publisher=[[Linnean Society of London]]|location=London|url =http://www.linnean.org/fileadmin/images/Publications/Linnean-21-2__2__web_complete.pdf|format =PDF|accessdate=29 May 2008}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; No reason was given for its removal, although it was rumoured that it was to remove a landmark for WWII German aircraft, but [[Luftwaffe]] bombers actually navigated their way to Central London by tracking the River Thames. 
The Crystal Palace grounds were also used as a manufacturing base for aircraft radar screens and other hi-tech equipment of the time. This remained secret until well after the war. 

With the Palace's destruction, the High Level Branch station fell into disuse, and was finally shut in 1954.

After the war the site was used for a number of purposes. Between 1953 and 1973 an [[auto racing]] circuit operated there, supported by the [[Greater London Council]], but the [[Noise pollution#Impact of noise pollution in the UK|noise was unpopular]] with nearby residents and racing hours were soon regulated under a high court judgment.&lt;ref name="norwoodsociety.co.uk"/&gt;

== Future ==
Over the years, numerous proposals for the former site of the palace have not come to fruition. Currently there are several plans. 
* Plans by the London Development Agency to spend £67.5&amp;nbsp;million to refurbish the site, including new homes and a regional sports centre were approved after Public Inquiry in December 2010. Before approval was announced the LDA withdrew from taking on management of the park and funding the project.
* A private consortium announced plans to rebuild the Crystal Palace and its use to house galleries, a snow slope, a music auditorium, leisure facilities and a hotel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard/article-23436111-details/Will+Crystal+Palace+rise+again/article.do Will Crystal Palace rise again? | News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On 20 January 2011, Crystal Palace Football Club announced plans to move to the site. Initial proposals include a 40,000 capacity stadium on the site of the athletics stadium and a new athletics track north of the National Sports Centre.

== See also ==
*[[List of demolished buildings and structures in London]]
*[[List of buildings and structures]] – See for other famous or notable buildings
*[[Crystal Palace pneumatic railway]]
*[[Glass Pavilion]]
*[[Crystal Palace F.C.]]- a football club named after the site
*[[Alexandra Palace]]
*[[Infomart]] a building in Dallas, Texas modelled after the Crystal Palace

== Further reading ==
* John McKean, "Crystal Palace: Joseph Paxton &amp; Charles Fox", Phaidon Press, London, 1994
* ''Dickinson's Comprehensive Pictures of the Great Exhibition of 1851'', Dickinson Brothers, London, 1854.&lt;ref name="dukemag"/&gt;
* Kate Colquhoun – ''A Thing in Disguise: The Visionary Life of Joseph Paxton'' (Fourth Estate, 2003) ISBN 0-00-714353-2
* George F Chadwick – ''Works of Sir Joseph Paxton'' (Architectural Press, 1961) ISBN 0-85139-721-2
* Ian Leith: "Delamotte's Crystal Palace", London, 2005
* Jan Piggott: "Palace of the People", London, 2004&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Phillips|first=Samuel|title=Guide to the Crystal Palace and its park and gardens|year=1860|publisher=Sydenham|pages=10, [2], xvi, 192 p., [3] folded leaves of plates : ill., maps ; 19 cm.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* John McKean “The Invisible Column of The Crystal Palace”   in 'La Colonne – nouvelle histoire de la construction', ed Roberto Gargiani, Lausanne (Suisse), 2008 ISBN 978-2-88074-714-5

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{commons|Crystal Palace}}
* [http://viewfinder.english-heritage.org.uk/search/results.aspx?index=0&amp;form=advanced&amp;collection=P%20H%20Delamotte Historic images of Crystal Palace, dating back to the 1850s]. Taken by [[Philip Henry Delamotte|Philip Delamotte]] but now held by the [[English Heritage Archive]].
* [http://www.crystalpalacemuseum.org.uk/ Crystal Palace Museum]
* [http://www.cocgb.dircon.co.uk/cry_pal_park.htm Crystal Palace Park] – map of the park as was until recently
* [http://www.victorianlondon.org/buildings/crystalpalace.htm The Crystal Palace, sources from www.victorianlondon.org]
* {{mmukscaled|TQ3425070750|25|Map sources for the park and surrounding area}} including Victorian maps showing the palace
* [http://www.ric.edu/rpotter/cryspal.html [[Russell Potter]]'s Crystal Palace Page, with information on the Baird Television studios]
* [http://www.iath.virginia.edu/london/model/ A 3D computer model of the Crystal Palace with images and animation]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/london/7429156.stm Park hosts Crystal Palace replica] – BBC News 31 May 2008

{{DEFAULTSORT:Crystal Palace, The}}
[[Category:History of Bromley]]
[[Category:Cultural and educational buildings in London]]
[[Category:Crystal Palace]]
[[Category:Former buildings and structures of Bromley]]
[[Category:Former buildings and structures of Westminster]]
[[Category:Destroyed landmarks in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Parks and open spaces in Bromley]]
[[Category:Cultural infrastructure completed in 1851]]
[[Category:1851 in England]]
[[Category:Palaces in London]]
[[Category:Greenhouses]]
[[Category:World's fair architecture in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Relocated buildings and structures]]
[[Category:Burned buildings and structures in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Cast-iron architecture]]
[[Category:The Great Exhibition]]
[[Category:Joseph Paxton buildings and structures]]</text>
      <sha1>f281y8uckep55x4h00s631jxzpxep1n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>