<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Trabecular veins</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8132184</id>
    <revision>
      <id>525868287</id>
      <parentid>417056138</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-12-01T15:02:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>clean up /fixed checkwiki error 18 using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8717)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Vein |
  Name        = Trabecular veins |
  Latin       = |
  GraySubject = 278 |
  GrayPage    = 1286 |
  Image       = Gray1192.png |
  Caption     = Section of the spleen, showing the termination of the small bloodvessels. |
  Image2      = Gray1189.png |
  Caption2    = Transverse section of the spleen, showing the trabecular tissue and the splenic vein and its tributaries. |
  DrainsFrom  = [[Sinus (anatomy)|sinus]]  |
  DrainsTo    = [[Splenic vein]] |
  Artery      = [[Trabecular arteries]] |
  MeshName    = |
  MeshNumber  = |
  DorlandsPre = |
  DorlandsSuf = |
}}
The '''trabecular veins''' are the largest veins inside the [[spleen]]. It drains the blood collected in the sinuses of the pulp.

==Details==
The blood is collected from the interstices of the tissue by the rootlets of the [[veins]], which begin much in the same way as the [[arteries]] end. 

The [[connective-tissue]] corpuscles of the pulp arrange themselves in rows, in such a way as to form an elongated space or sinus. 

They become elongated and spindle-shaped, and overlap each other at their extremities, and thus form a sort of [[endothelial]] lining of the path or sinus, which is the radicle of a vein. 

On the outer surfaces of these cells are seen delicate transverse lines or markings, which are due to minute elastic fibrillæ arranged in a circular manner around the sinus. 

Thus the channel obtains an external investment, and gradually becomes converted into a small vein, which after a short course acquires a coat of ordinary connective tissue, lined by a layer of flattened epithelial cells which are continuous with the supporting cells of the pulp. 

The smaller veins unite to form larger ones; these do not accompany the arteries, but soon enter the trabecular sheaths of the capsule, and by their junction form six or more branches, which emerge from the [[Splenic hilum|hilum]], and, uniting, constitute the [[lienal vein]], the largest radicle of the [[portal vein]].

==External links==
* {{BUHistology|07704loa}} - "Lymphoid Tissues and Organs: spleen, central artery and trabecular vein"
* [http://www.udel.edu/Biology/Wags/histopage/colorpage/cst/cst.htm Slide at udel.edu]
* {{EmbryologySwiss|qblood/lymphat06}} (See figure #16)

{{Gray's}}

{{Lymphatic system}}

[[Category:Veins]]
[[Category:Spleen (anatomy)]]


{{circulatory-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>f80pu1iaknecz8fmvhdfsv1gzbalru7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>