<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Versant Corporation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20557048</id>
    <revision>
      <id>543295057</id>
      <parentid>540699211</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-10T22:57:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Migrating 2 interwiki links, now provided by [[Wikipedia:Wikidata|Wikidata]] on [[d:q174893]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|{{Notability|Companies|date=December 2008}}|refimprove =December 2008|advert =December 2008}}

{{Infobox company
| company_name  =  Versant Corporation
| company_logo  =  [[Image:Versant logo 2007.png|250px|Logo]]
| company_type  =  [[Subsidiary]] 
| foundation  =  1988
| key_people        =  Bernhard Woebker, CEO
| location_city  =   [[Redwood City]], [[California]]
| location_country  =  USA
| revenue  =  {{profit}} 25,3 million [[United States dollar|USD]] (2008)
| industry  =  Software
| products  =  [[Object Database]]
}}

'''Versant Corporation''' is a company building speciailized [[NoSQL]] data management systems. Versant products are deployed in a wide variety of industries including: Telecommunications, Defense, Life Sciences/BioMedical, Transportation, Finance, Online Gaming and more. Versant was founded in [[Fremont, California]] (USA) in 1988. It is currently headquartered in [[Redwood City, California]] where all activities related to finances, marketing communications, business development and customer service take place. The engineering team is located in Hamburg, Germany and Redwood City, California.

Versant offers NoSQL [[object database]] technologies, including, “Versant JPA”, "[[Versant Object Database]]", "[[FastObjects]]" and the open source database "[[db4o]]".

== History ==
The company was founded by Dr. Kee Ong in 1988 as "Object Sciences Corporation" in Fremont, California (USA). Among the first employees were CEO Michael Seashols and kernel engineers Dr. Hong-Tai Chou, Stephen Au-Yeung, and Dr. CP Chou. Dr. Ong, who previously worked with the open-source relational database Ingres, recognized that languages were expanding to include [[object-orientated programming]] (OO) and leveraged work done at the [[University of Wisconsin]] (known as the WISC storage system[&lt;ref&gt;"[http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=4439]", acm.org. Retrieved 12 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;) to create a commercial object-oriented database to complement OO languages.

In early 1990 the company was renamed “Versant Object Technology.”  In 1993 David Banks took over as CEO.  In 1996 Versant went public on the [[NASDAQ]] stock exchange and traded under the symbol “VSNT.”  In 1997 Nick Ordon succeeded Banks as CEO.  In 1999 the company was renamed again to “Versant Corporation.”

In March 2004, Versant acquired Poet Software GmbH, a complementary European-focused company targeting the Windows product market. In 2005, Jochen Witte, former President of Poet Software, took over as CEO of Versant Corporation.  Versant's most recent acquisition was db4objects Inc. in 2008, the developer and provider of the open source embedded database technology "[[db4o]]".

The original implementation of Versant was targeted at [[C (programming language)|C]], [[C++]] and [[Smalltalk]] users. In 1995 Versant introduced support for the Java language and then in 2009 for [[C Sharp (programming language)|C#]] and the [[.NET Framework|.NET]] platform.  In 2012 Versant introduced a [[Java Persistence API|JPA]] 2.0 compliant interface for its object database, “Versant JPA” with a technical preview of an Analytics platform including [[Hadoop]] support, to address the scalability, speed and concurrency issues related to Big Data challenges.

In late 2012, after rejecting an offer by Unicom Systems Inc., Versant Corporation announced that it was being acquired by Actian Corporation, the current developer of the [[Ingres (database)|Ingres]] open source database and the SQL relational database, [[Vectorwise]].  The acquisition was heralded by the industry as a marriage of two Big Data players that would be an “enterprise big data database pure-play to be reckoned with going forward.”&lt;ref&gt;[2] “[http://www.esg-global.com/blogs/giving-thanks-for-versant-and-actian/ Giving Thanks for Versant and Actian],” esg-global.com.  November 26, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Executive Team ==

*Bernhard Woebker - CEO
*Jerry Wong - CFO
*Paul McCullugh - EVP Worldwide Sales &amp; Marketing
*Robert Greene - Technology

== Products ==
Versant currently markets three commercial [[object databases]] (OODBMS), “Versant JPA,” "[[Versant Object Database]]" and "Versant FastObjects". In addition, Versant offers the open source database "[[db4o]]".
* Versant JPA is a JPA 2.0 compliant interface for its object database that includes a technical preview of an Analytics platform including Hadoop support.&lt;ref&gt;[3] “[http://www.drdobbs.com/jvm/new-versant-jpa-delivers-multiple-nosql/240012438 New Versant JPA Delivers Multiple NoSQL Analytics],” Dr. Dobb’s Journal. October 28, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; It is available as a server and SDK for use with [[Windows]] and [[Linux]] operating systems.
* [[Versant Object Database]] is used primarily for complex [[Java]], [[.NET Framework|.NET]] and [[C++]] applications, especially those with high concurrency and performance requirements and very large data sets. The [[Versant Object Database]] is available for use with the operating systems [[Windows]], [[Linux]], [[Solaris (operating system)|Solaris]], [[HP-UX]] and [[AIX]] and can be integrated in [[Java]], [[.NET Framework|.NET]] or [[C++]] programs. Unlike in a [[relational database management system]] (RDBMS, e.g., [[Oracle database|Oracle]]), complex logical models can be directly stored, read and modeled as domain objects without having to model them first in relational tables.&lt;ref&gt;[4] "http://www.agiledata.org/essays/relationalDatabases.html#BeyondRelationalDatabases", agiledata.org.&lt;/ref&gt;
* "Versant FastObjects" is a developer-friendly, object-oriented alternative to a relational database for .NET persistence.&lt;ref&gt;[5] “[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dylHRxBcVT4 FastObjects Tutorial,]” YouTube. January 9, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* "[[db4o]]" is a lightweight, open source, easy-to-use native embedded object database for Java and .NET. db4o is 100% coded in Java and translated to C# by an open-source tool called Sharpen.&lt;ref&gt;[6] Db4o website [http://www.db4o.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Application areas ==
Versant solutions are best suited for complex data models, ingesting large amount of data, and/or large numbers of concurrent users. Versant is found in applications within many different vertical industries where those characteristics come into play:  global trading platforms for the world’s largest stock exchanges; network management for the world’s largest telecommunications providers; intelligence analytics for defense agencies; reservation systems for the largest airline/hotel companies; risk management analytics for banking and transportation organizations; massive multi-player gaming systems; network security and fraud detection; local number portability; advanced simulations; and social networking, among others.

== External links ==
* [http://www.versant.com Versant Corporation]

== References ==
{{More footnotes|date=January 2009}}
{{Reflist}}
*[http://www.versant.com/en_US/news_events/pressreleases/pressreleases_2008/earnings_release_FY2008.html/2 Versant Press Release]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Versant Corporation}}
[[Category:Software companies based in the San Francisco Bay Area]]
[[Category:Software companies established in 1988]]
[[Category:1988 establishments in California]]
[[Category:Companies based in Redwood City, California]]</text>
      <sha1>qlcld84a6yj6hifj6497ohcqqul73cp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>