<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Vivisimo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2721561</id>
    <revision>
      <id>562764272</id>
      <parentid>544131944</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-04T00:15:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FifthCircuit</username>
        <id>19172485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>/* History */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=May 2009}}
{{Infobox company
| company_name   = Vivisimo, an IBM Company
| company_logo   = [[File:Vivisimo-logo.PNG|186px|Vivisimo]]
| foundation     = [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]] &lt;br&gt; June 21, 2000 [https://www.corporations.state.pa.us/corp/soskb/Corp.asp?1854566]
| location       = [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]]
| industry       = [[Internet]]
| products       = Vivisimo Velocity Search Platform
| company_slogan = Search Done Right
}}
'''Vivisimo, an IBM Company,''' is a formerly privately held federated discovery and navigation software company that was acquired&lt;ref name="acq-anncmt"&gt;[http://www-03.ibm.com/press/us/en/pressrelease/37833.wss]&lt;/ref&gt; by [[IBM]] in May 2012 and is now an IBM company within the [[IBM Information Management Software]] brand. The Vivisimo team, which is based primarily in [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania|Pittsburgh]], develops and sells software products that provide federated discovery and navigation capabilities on the web and in enterprises. Vivisimo gives organizations access to understand and navigate through vast amounts of structured and unstructured information. Vivisimo provides a single point of access to a variety of information sources, extracting relevant information and providing ad hoc analysis without moving the data. The Vivisimo approach adds to traditional approaches, such as [[data warehouse]], by giving insight via new methods and sources.

On 25 Apr 2012, [[IBM]] announced a definitive agreement to acquire Vivisimo to boost its [[Big Data]] Analytics capabilities .&lt;ref name=V-IBM-00&gt;[http://blogs.forrester.com/boris_evelson/12-04-25-data_discovery_and_exploration_ibm_acquires_vivisimo?cm_mmc=RSS-_-IT-_-63-_-blog_1737 Data discovery and exploration - IBM acquires Vivisimo]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=V-IBM-01&gt;[http://www-03.ibm.com/press/us/en/pressrelease/37491.wss IBM Advances Big Data Analytics with Acquisition of Vivisimo]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=V-IBM-02&gt;[http://techcrunch.com/2012/04/25/ibm-acquires-enterprise-search-software-company-vivisimo-to-boost-big-data-analytics/ IBM Acquires Enterprise Search Software Company Vivisimo To Boost Big Data Analytics]&lt;/ref&gt; On 29 May 2012, the acquisition was completed.&lt;ref name="acq-anncmt" /&gt;

==History==
Vivisimo was founded in 2000 by a trio of computer science researchers at [[Carnegie Mellon University]] - Chris Palmer, Jerome Pesenti, and Raul Valdes-Perez. The name was taken from the Spanish root ''vivo'' meaning "lively" or "clever," with the Spanish suffix -''isimo'' indicating a superlative.  Earlier marketing tied this to the company's older tagline, "bright, lively, and intelligent."

In October 2008, Vivisimo was awarded the contract to power the search portion of FirstGov.gov (now called [[USA.gov]]), the official web portal of the [[United States federal government]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://searchenginewatch.com/showPage.html?page=3551226 |title=Vivisimo and MSN to Power FirstGov |accessdate=2007-12-27 |publisher=[[Search Engine Watch]]|date=2005-09-26|author=Gary Price}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The company was first funded by its founders, [[Innovation Works]], and SBIR grants from the [[National Science Foundation]]. Its products are used by a wide variety of websites, companies, and government agencies.

On 25 April 2012, IBM announced its intention to acquire Vivisimo for an undisclosed sum.&lt;ref name="V-IBM-01"/&gt; IBM announced it would incorporate Vivisimo’s technology into its big data platform. On 29 May 2012, the acquisition was completed.&lt;ref name="acq-anncmt" /&gt;

==Products==
Velocity is sold as an installed or hosted application to enterprises, governments, and [[OEM]]s. Vivisimo provides professional services, acknowledging that enterprise search in complex corporate environments benefits from the shared experience of similar deployments elsewhere.

Velocity's [[social search]] features allow users to contribute to organizational content by tagging, voting, annotating and sharing search results. The contributions are instantly indexed in new searches, which  helps faster collaboration throughout the enterprise.

==Product Awards==
* InfoWorld 2008 Technology of the Year - Best Enterprise Search&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.infoworld.com/slideshow/2008/01/145-2008_technology-4.html |title=2008 Technology of the Year Awards: Data Management |accessdate=2007-12-27 |publisher=InfoWorld}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* InfoWorld 2007 Technology of the Year - Best Enterprise Search&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.infoworld.com/slideshow/2007/01/27-2007_technology-2.html |title=2007 Technology of the Year Awards: Data Management |accessdate=2007-12-27 |publisher=InfoWorld}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* InfoWorld 2006 Technology of the Year - Best Enterprise Search&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.infoworld.com/article/06/01/02/01FEtoycm_1.html?s=feature |title=Wanted: Methods for moving mountains of content |accessdate=2007-12-27 |publisher=InfoWorld | author=Mike Heck |date=2006-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Network Computing Editor's Choice - Enterprise Search Review&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.networkcomputing.com/channels/enterpriseapps/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=199905064&amp;pgno=13 |title=Analysis: Enterprise Search |accessdate=2007-12-27 |publisher=Network Computing | author=Ben DuPont |date=2007-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Clusty]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

===Reviews===
* [http://www.infoworld.com/article/05/05/23/21TCvelocity_1.html Vivisimo Brings Structure to the Enterprise]
* [http://www.infoworld.com/article/06/09/08/37TCvelocity_1.html Vivisimo Velocity Races Ahead of the Search Pack]
* [http://searchenginewatch.com/searchday/article.php/3415071 Connection with Vivisimo]

{{Pittsburgh Corporations}}

[[Category:Internet companies of the United States]]
[[Category:IBM acquisitions]]</text>
      <sha1>9ui8c7tlc1kyzvoefvzi5m4o4zv74bz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>