<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Web science</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7777747</id>
    <revision>
      <id>561057545</id>
      <parentid>556701997</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-22T12:55:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Qwertyus</username>
        <id>196471</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Features and Goals */ Shouldn't that be "the interwebs are the brain of the mankinds"? (rm)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Human Behavior Co-constituting the Web.png|thumb|450px]]

'''Web science''' is the socio-technical science that investigates how the [[World Wide Web]] evolves given the regulations, technology and content imposed, engineered and contributed, respectively, as an effect of human behavior and how the Web vice versa affects human behavior.
An earlier definition was given by American computer scientist [[Ben Shneiderman]]: "Web Science" is a term that refers to processing the information available on the web in similar terms to those applied to natural environment.&lt;ref&gt;Ben Shneiderman. 2007. Web science: a provocative invitation to computer science. Commun. ACM 50, 6 (June 2007), 25-27. DOI=10.1145/1247001.1247022 http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1247001.1247022&lt;/ref&gt;

== Features and Goals ==
Web science has a multidisciplinary base.&lt;ref&gt;James Hendler, Nigel Shadbolt, Wendy Hall, Tim Berners-Lee, and Daniel Weitzner. 2008. Web science: an interdisciplinary approach to understanding the web. Commun. ACM 51, 7 (July 2008), 60-69. DOI=10.1145/1364782.1364798 http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1364782.1364798&lt;/ref&gt; One can draw an analogy between Web Science and Technology (WebST) and Brain Science and Engineering (BSC) as they both tackle complex network structures at different levels of abstraction and deal with data/information/knowledge flows internally as well as in conjunction with the surroundings. Yet WebST differs from BSC because it interacts with completely autonomous and massively parallel human populations. A fundamental question for WebST is in what ways the Web has to evolve to best serve human beings.&lt;ref&gt;http://eng.webst.kaist.ac.kr/content.php?db=_intro/ Division of Web Science and Technology, KAIST, Korea&lt;/ref&gt;

== Interests ==
There are different groups&lt;ref&gt;http://tw.rpi.edu/web/wsrc Web Science Research Center at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, NY&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://eng.webst.kaist.ac.kr/ Division of Web Science and Technology, KAIST, Korea&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://west.uni-koblenz.de/ Institute for Web Science and Technologies, University of Koblenz-Landau]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ebusiness-unibw.org/ E-Business and Web Science Research Group at Bundeswehr University Munich]&lt;/ref&gt; and initiatives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nesta.org.uk/areas_of_work/public_services_lab/past_projects_public_services_lab/web_science_research_initiative Web Science Research Initiative (WSRI)]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Related major conferences ==
* ACM Web Science Conference:  http://www.websci13.org/program/
* International World Wide Web Conference (WWW): http://www2013.org/
* International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media (ICWSM): http://www.icwsm.org/2013/
* The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI): http://chi2013.acm.org/

== See also ==
* [[Web Science Trust]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.slideshare.net/webscikorea/why-do-we-need-web-science-research Why do we need web science research]
* [http://www.nowpublishers.com/product.aspx?product=WEB&amp;doi=1800000001 A Framework for Web Science]
* [http://www.w3.org/2007/Talks/1018-websci-mit-tbl/ Talk on web science] by [[W3C]]
* [http://west.uni-koblenz.de/mws MSc on Web Science at Institute WeST, University of Koblenz-Landau, Germany]
* [http://www-typo3.cs.ucl.ac.uk/admissions/msc_web_science/ MSc on Web Science and Big Data Analytics at University College London, UK]

{{Semantic Web}}



[[Category:World Wide Web]]


{{Internet-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>a02tjr6jve1zd4yed27pye8sx359k5r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>