<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Wikipedia:WikiProject Red Link Recovery/RLRL</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>30065496</id>
    <revision>
      <id>559775523</id>
      <parentid>557855456</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-13T20:30:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Topbanana</username>
        <id>20151</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>New Suggestions - Renamed Countries</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This page is for the discussion of the '''Red Link Recovery Live''' tool, hosted on [[WP:LABS|Tool Labs]] at [http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/RLRL/ http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/RLRL/].
-----
== Ideas for new data sets ==

* Pinyin vs Wade-Giles transliteration of oriental languages (ie [http://oclccjk.lib.uci.edu/pycywg.htm])
* Try triple-metaphone for enhanced accuracy of foreign language titles
* Generally, a weighted Levenshtein distance
* Abbreviations in general (ltd/ltd./limited)
* Removal of disambiguation features
* Names with alternate spellings (Mohammed, Muhammad)
* More homonyns and homoglyphs
** [http://www.unicode.org/Public/security/revision-04/confusables.txt http://www.unicode.org/Public/security/revision-04/confusables.txt]
* Specialised number handler in double metaphone
* All the tricks used in the [http://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Extension:Lucene-search Mediawiki Lucene-search], as discussed [http://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/User:Rainman/search_internals here]
** Word-order swapping
** Ignoring stop-words
** Context-free synonyms [http://svn.wikimedia.org/viewvc/mediawiki/trunk/lucene-search-2/resources/dict/wordnet-en.txt.gz?revision=40558&amp;view=co this list]
** ''Linguistic rephrasing (Politics of Africa -&gt; African Politics)'' - tried, Jan 2011 - initial results look good.
* Latin prefixes as separate or hyphenated words "non-sequitur", "anti personnel"

- [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 22:34, 15 December 2010 (UTC)

: Also:
: * Careless positional nunbers .. 2rd, 23nd, 55d
: * Nouns vs verbs;  sprint, sprinting, sprinter
: * Inferred links.  If A-&gt;B, is A may be a likely alternate target for a red link on B
: - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 23:42, 20 November 2011 (UTC)

== Stats terms ==
Can you explain some of the terms in the ''stats'' screen?
*Lost
*Live results
*Links vs Titles?

Also, how does Update Stats work?

Great tool.
[[User:Welsh|welsh]] ([[User talk:Welsh|talk]]) 09:13, 19 December 2010 (UTC)

* 'Lost' is a catch-all status for suggestions that aren't New, Checked, Old or Fixed.  So far it's not seen much use other than during the process of adding or removing new data-sets from RLRL.  Suggestions for a better term to use are welcome - the best I can come up with is 'out of play'.
* 'Live results' are those generated on-demand when the [http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/RLRL/checkpage.php check a specific page] tool is used.  The emphasis in producing the live results is on generating many reasonably plausible suggestions using whichever methods can be run quickly, as opposed to the far more selective and time-consuming methods used to generate the pre-prepared suggestions.
* 'Links' and 'Titles' refers to whether the text of a red link or the title of an existing article has been modified to produce the suggested match - it's a bit of an artificial distinction to be honest.  They're tracked separately as I'm trying to measure the difference in the accuracy of article titles compared to the accuracy of wikilinked.  I beleive that more 'thought' goes into choosing the title of an article than into choosing a portion of text within an article or link, and that I can use this fact to further fine-tune future sets of suggestions.
* 'Update Stats' - Before any suggestion is displayed, checks are run to make sure that the original red link still exists, that it is not now blue and that the suggested new target for it still exists.  The 'update stats' makes exactly the same checks, but applies them to every 'in play' (new, checked or old) suggestion in the system.
: Happy to elaborate, and very glad that you and others are finding the system useful. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 14:02, 19 December 2010 (UTC)

== Check page updated, 2010-12-23 ==

I have corrected a problem in one of the main algorithms used on the 'check page' tool.  Suggestions for titles in eastern-european and asian languages should now be much more accurate. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 18:43, 23 December 2010 (UTC)

== New suggestions - genitives ==

800 or so new suggestions posted.  This is a new technique, comparing noun and genitive forms of country names to try and match links and titles such as [[Guatemalan politics]] and [[Politics of Guatemala]].   - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 22:55, 8 January 2011 (UTC)

: This set is completed now (578 good suggestions, 182 bad ones, &gt;75% success).  While initially run with continent, country and U.S. state name pairs (i.e.  Africa/African, Iraq/Iraqi, Texas/Texan), it strikes me that there are many other classes of words that are commonly used in possessive form - consider Socialism/Socialist, Philosophy/Philosophical, Mathematics/Mathematical, Religion/Religious.  Now I've been trying to hunt down any useful list of such words and am drawing a blank.  Nor can I come up with any even remotely useful set of rules for detecting or generating the possessive form of English language words.  Anyone got any ideas ? - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 13:51, 14 August 2011 (UTC)

== New suggestions - honorifics ==

1100 or so new suggestions posted.  These suggestions have been generated by removing the honorific 'Sir' from the start of red links and checking what remains against existing article titles.  If anyone can find and link the relevant [[WP:MoS|manual of style]] section or spinoff, that'd be a big help, ta. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 22:03, 27 May 2011 (UTC)
:[[MOS:HONORIFICS]] - [[User:Welsh|welsh]] ([[User talk:Welsh|talk]]) 16:51, 6 August 2011 (UTC)

:: Ah, thanks - the very thing.  I only wish I were wiser having read it.  My understanding is that the use of 'Sir' in an article title is basically optional.  Oh well - at least marrying up instances of omitted/present honorifics in links and article titles will assist in any future standardisation. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 20:57, 6 August 2011 (UTC)

== New suggestions - ampersands ==

1620 new suggestions involving the expansion of ampersands (&amp;'s) in titles and red links into the word 'and'.  Initial check seems good, think this one'll be a keeper. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 13:40, 14 August 2011 (UTC)

== New suggestions - unspecified counties ==

1920 new suggestions.  Where there's a red link in the form 'Place, Some County, State', the middle bit has been removed and the results matched against article titles.  Horrible, I know ;)  Almost certainly &lt;50% accurate and never to be generated again, but there'll be some useful red link fixes and missing disambig pages for sure. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 15:13, 14 August 2011 (UTC)

: This set isn't working well - almost every match seems to be a missing disambiguation page :( - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 14:27, 28 August 2011 (UTC)

== New suggestions - leading the's ==

10000 new suggestions involving removing a leading 'The' from red links.  Results seem modestly good. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 14:47, 15 August 2011 (UTC)

== Suggestion likeliness updated ==
I've revamped the algorithm used to estimate the likely correctness of any given suggestion, largely because the old one was ranking the "unspecified counties" set unduly highly.  Hopefully this will push the 'better' suggestions to the top of whatever list(s) people are working through. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 10:46, 28 August 2011 (UTC)

== New suggestions - Limited companies ==

A small set of links and titles ending with Ltd/Ltd./Limited - if it works well, I'll add in some additional suffixes.  Corp/Corp./Corporation, Co/Co./Company, Inc/Inc/Incorporated and so forth - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 14:24, 28 August 2011 (UTC)
: Three more sets of these posted - all small sets, all look to be useful. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]])#

== Autofix javascript updated ==

I've made some minor improvements to the autofix javascript at [[User:Topbanana/RLRL SR Utility.js]].  If you use autofix links and are finding that the search and replace is matching things it should not, you may need to refresh your browsers copy of the file.  To do this, click on the 'preferencers' link on any Wikipedia page, then 'appearance', then the 'Custom JavaScript' link for your selected skin.  Follow the instructions at the top of the page there. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 16:27, 28 August 2011 (UTC)

== New suggestions - Dash-like characters ==

A set of 1100 new suggestions generated by equating the various unicode dash-like characters. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 22:00, 30 August 2011 (UTC)

== Cross-wiki support ==

I'm in the process of modifying RLRL to support other Wikimedia projects (Wiktionary, Wikisource and so forth) and more usefully, other languages.  Apologies if I break any on the English/Wikipedia processing as I do so. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 21:31, 11 September 2011 (UTC)
: This proceeds well; RLRL is now set up for the English-language Wiktionary and Wikiquote sites, and the French- and German- language Wikipediae.  What's now needed are some guinea pigs.  I'll contact [[:fr:Projet:Restauration lien rouge|Restauration lien rouge]] for the former, but cannot find a German- language equivaent of this project.  An initial check shows that Wiktionary has very different editing policies from Wikipedia, and therefore might need careful consideration.
:So, questions:
* Are any [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Red Link Recovery]] members even remotely active on other WikiMedia projects?
* Does ayone have any proficiency in ither languages?
: Ta. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 06:30, 16 September 2011 (UTC)

::I have made a couple of edits so far on deWiki. As I am about to do some travelling I will lie low for a week or so, but I will then do a batch of 50 and see if there is any fallout. [[User:Agathoclea|Agathoclea]] ([[User talk:Agathoclea|talk]]) 05:58, 29 September 2011 (UTC)

::: That's great, thanks. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 06:25, 29 September 2011 (UTC)

== Checkpage changes ==
I've made some significant changes to the "check a specific page" tool - t should give the same results as before but now be dramatically quicker to return results.  If anyone notices it behaving oddly, please let me know. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 06:33, 16 September 2011 (UTC)

== New suggestions - Templates ==

A set of 1700 new suggestions.  These are red links into namespace 10 (the template namespace) matched against existing template names by brute force.  In essence, the [[levenshtein distance]] each pair of 30000 candidate red links and 300000 candidate templates was calculated, and those with an edit distance of 1 retained as suggestions.  Entries where the entire edit consisted of numerals were suppressed.

Although far less elegant than other approaches, the brute-force Levenshtein has a greater chance of finding a suggestion for an arbitrary red link than other methods.  Of course, this means a resulting decrease in the likelihood of the suggestion being correct, but I can see potential for its use. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 21:26, 19 September 2011 (UTC)

==Domains==
I love this tool and think it's great - quick question though - I notice that there are datasets for LGBT, doctor who, and (I think) maritime warfare - what are the actions I'd take if I wanted to do something similar for the disability project?  [[User:Failedwizard|Failedwizard]] ([[User talk:Failedwizard|talk]]) 16:58, 1 October 2011 (UTC)

: Welcome on board, Failedwizard.  Posting here's as good a method as any ;)  I'm still tinkering with the system used to generate the domain-specific sets;  hopefully I'll have all the rough edges knocked off the process in the next few days an can offer the service to any and all Wikiprojects that would like their own list.  For now:

* [[:category:Disability_articles_by_quality]] contains:
**  494 articles which contain:
*** 1412 red links.

: Suggested fixes for 51 of these are now available in RLRL. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 18:54, 1 October 2011 (UTC)
You star! [[User:Failedwizard|Failedwizard]] ([[User talk:Failedwizard|talk]]) 19:34, 1 October 2011 (UTC)
::Fabulous, thank you so much... have fixed all the ones that seemed sensible...(will come back to manually look at the others) by the way - is this an open-source thing that people can help out with...? my code writing is better than my wiki-fu...   and the other quick question was - would it be possible to get the breakdown of, well, which of the 1412 red links are in which of the 494 articles? [[User:Failedwizard|Failedwizard]] ([[User talk:Failedwizard|talk]]) 21:09, 1 October 2011 (UTC)

::: RLRL runs on the [[Toolserver]] and is available under the [[AGPLv3]].  Happy to share - most of the fun's in the generation of the suggestions rather than the tool to store and serve them up.  I'll post up a report on those red links in the next day or two, no problem. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 21:49, 1 October 2011 (UTC)

::: Redlink report posted at [[User:Failedwizard/Disability redlinks]].  Enjoy ;) - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 10:49, 2 October 2011 (UTC)
:Awesome, and still more awesome...  *rolls up sleeves*  [[User:Failedwizard|Failedwizard]] ([[User talk:Failedwizard|talk]]) 12:58, 2 October 2011 (UTC)

==Toolbox bugs==
# autofix is not working for me to correct the links in the articles. I have to manually change the redlinks that are spelled incorrectly. (redirect autofix works, though)
# An option to check for this suggestion is completely wrong. Currently changing something means right and not changing is wrong. This leaves no room for maybe and it is non-intuitive. (At least for me, viewing something without changing it should not be construed as it is wrong.)
# checking minor fix and unchecking watch this page would be appreciated
[[User:TStein|TStein]] ([[User talk:TStein|talk]]) 05:37, 9 October 2011 (UTC)

: Hi there TStein.
:# I'll need to wait until I'm home from my hols to check why autofix isn't working for you. 
:# Suggestions that have been looked at two or three times without being fixed are marked as 'old' rather than 'wrong'.  This is deliberate distinction;  the 'cost' of someone checking a suggestion is large compared to the cost of generating it.  If a suggestion has been shown a few times and not been fixed, best to skip it and move on.  I do check the logs every month or two and correct the any obvious 'queue draining' activity.:# Good idea about the checkboxes on redirects - that annoys me also.  Again, I'll be able to check the scripts involved when back home.
: - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 12:43, 10 October 2011 (UTC)

:: Thanks for the response. I don't know if you have had a chance to work on #1 but it still doesn't work for me. (That isn't a real problem, it doesn't really bother me.) As far as number 2, I am not sure what I was trying to say there. I probably edited the sentence too many times and got confused. What inspired it, though was that sometimes I would go through a fair amount of work to investigate whether the recommended fix was good or not and then find out that it was not a good fix. In that case, I thought that an option to say that this suggestion is wrong would help so that other people wouldn't have to duplicate my work.

:: Finally, there is one more way that you may be able to improve this. In physics the vast majority of red-links by far are biographies and the suggestions are almost never correct (if ever). If it was possible (say by looking for a biography template or such) could you give an option to not count biographies? [[User:TStein|TStein]] ([[User talk:TStein|talk]]) 04:34, 12 October 2011 (UTC)

== Housekeeping ==

I've removed around 8500 of the least-likely suggestions from the 2010 lists to try and aid in getting them closed off. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 19:47, 13 November 2011 (UTC)

== Bank error in your favour, collect £100 ==

Found and fixed an accounting error on the stats page.  After 18 months, just shy of 74000 red links have been recovered.  Of the pre-calculated suggestions that have been processed, 86.65% were 'correct' enough to result in a fix.  Not to shabby :) -[[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 18:38, 20 January 2012 (UTC)

== Stats update ==

Just noting that last night we passed the 50,000 red links fixed mark on the pre-calculated set of suggestions in the [http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/RLRL/ Red Link Recovery Live] tool.  Adding in the 27,000 red links fixed using the [http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/RLRL/checkpage.php suggestions generated on demand], this represents a significant contribution towards improving Wikipedia.

Over the life of the Red Link Recovery Project, we've now fixed over 425,000 red links - at current rates we'll reach a half a million towards the end of next year.  Good job all. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 11:30, 6 March 2012 (UTC)

==Not working==

Is this thing broken, or is there something wrong with my browser? It's been working fine the past couple of weeks, but now the 'list of red links with alternate targets' is giving me the same three (already fixed) links over and over. Same with the lists of specific red links. What's going on? [[User:DoctorKubla|DoctorKubla]] ([[User talk:DoctorKubla|talk]]) 19:59, 28 March 2012 (UTC)

: Howdy, Doc.  The [[toolserver]] on which RLRL runs is partially offline for an update right now.   It's been off for 10 or so days now;  hopefully it'll be fixed in the next few days.  When it is, the tool'll be back to normal.  - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 10:36, 29 March 2012 (UTC)

:: The system's now (mostly) back online - it'll take a few days to catch up with he last week or so's updates to the live database. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 08:25, 4 April 2012 (UTC)

== Comma'd names ==

How about ''Comma'd names''. eg Bloggs, Fred -&gt; Fred Bloggs? [[User:Welsh|welsh]] ([[User talk:Welsh|talk]]) 06:49, 9 September 2012 (UTC)

: Nice idea - I've popped up a set of 700 or so suggestions generated using this method.  If it scores well, a more aggressive run should find another thousand or so.  - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 15:32, 9 September 2012 (UTC)

== Unlikely bracket spacing==

How about ''redlinks with unlikely spacing around brackets''? Usually an open bracket is preceded by a space and a close bracket followed by a space (unless it is at the end of the link. Also an open bracket is rarely followed by a space. Maybe this should be in the ''unlikely links'' tool instead, as this could be fixed even if there is no bluelink solution. [[User:Welsh|welsh]] ([[User talk:Welsh|talk]]) 07:47, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

: Nice one.  I've added it to the unlikely links tool (as [http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/unlikely/?check=24 Spaces near brackets]) immediately.   A trial of matching red links against titles by adding or removing spaces was tried in 2006/07 with fairly poor results, but incorporating a little more knowledge about oddly places spaces might yield better results.  I've added it to my todo list, cheers. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 10:09, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

::That's good. How about brackets with no spaces before or after as relevant? eg Fred(singer). Maybe again as an unlikely links list [[User:Welsh|welsh]] ([[User talk:Welsh|talk]]) 23:01, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

::: Have added [http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/unlikely/?check=25 missing spaces near brackets] to supplement the (renamed) [http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/unlikely/?check=24 extra spaces near brackets] above.  Mixed results I'd say; not sure if any simple rule defines what's a normal character to follow a close bracket. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 08:47, 16 October 2012 (UTC)

:::: A closer look indicates problems with neither the suggested rule or the English-language, but rather a fairly large number of poorly punctuated article and redirect titles.  I've added functionality tot he Unlikely tool to help hunt these down. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 20:59, 17 October 2012 (UTC)

::::: Okay, I've come up with a test for this that's slightly better than awful.  There are still a good few 'correct' titles in the set, but the check is now at least borderline useful. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 22:50, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

== AUTOFIX now offered for red links on templates ==
Several of the upcoming datasets focus on broken links within templates.  Often, fixing such red links on a single template corrects all instances of it - once of course Mediawiki catches up and propagates the change.  To help solve such cases, an AUTOFIX will now always be offered for links on templates.  Please do remember to check 'what links here' for the red link 48  hours later if you can, just in case the link existed independently on one or more articles also. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 10:26, 4 December 2012 (UTC)

== RLRL moved to Tool Labs ==
The new [[WP:LABS|Tool Labs]] environment will be replacing the Toolserver by the end of 2014.  I've moved RLRL over ahead of schedule, and it can now be found at [http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/RLRL/ http://tools.wmflabs.org/tb-dev/RLRL/].  Kindly report any oddities here. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 15:44, 1 June 2013 (UTC)

== New Suggestions - Renamed Countries ==
I've posted a small set  of suggestions (~250 entries) generated by using previous names of countries (per [[Geographical renaming]]).  I've no idea how useful these will turn out to be. - [[User:Topbanana|TB]] ([[User talk:Topbanana|talk]]) 20:30, 13 June 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>lge78l4uf6zcn5383vrxaprkt7rv60x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>