<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Programming with Big Data in R</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>39795929</id>
    <revision>
      <id>563088570</id>
      <parentid>563084735</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-06T10:11:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>188.98.216.174</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Programming with Big Data in R */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">===[[Programming with Big Data in R]]===
{{REMOVE THIS TEMPLATE WHEN CLOSING THIS AfD|T}}

:{{la|Programming with Big Data in R}} – (&lt;includeonly&gt;[[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Programming with Big Data in R|View AfD]]&lt;/includeonly&gt;&lt;noinclude&gt;[[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Log/2013 July 4#{{anchorencode:Programming with Big Data in R}}|View log]]&lt;/noinclude&gt;{{int:dot-separator}} &lt;span class="plainlinks"&gt;[http://toolserver.org/~snottywong/cgi-bin/votecounter.cgi?page=Wikipedia:Articles_for_deletion/Programming_with_Big_Data_in_R Stats]&lt;/span&gt;)
:({{Find sources|Programming with Big Data in R}})

* Lots of references but which of them actually demonstrate that this software is notable outside the narrow world of statisticians? &amp;mdash; [[User:RHaworth|RHaworth]] ([[User talk:RHaworth|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/RHaworth|contribs]]) 21:27, 27 June 2013 (UTC)

* &lt;big&gt;'''Keep'''&lt;/big&gt;. pbdR is series of packages(technically not a software) and is expanding continuously after it's apperance in october 2012.Recently it appeared on Google summer of code for mentoring a project . link: http://rwiki.sciviews.org/doku.php?id=developers:projects:gsoc2013:mpiprofiler and it has been selected for mentoring : your proof :http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/project/google/gsoc2013/igaurav/30001 . So it is making it's way out of narrow world of statisticians to public. [[User:igauravsehrawat|igauravsehrawat]]  &lt;span style="font-size: smaller;" class="autosigned"&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 14:12, 28 June 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; 
:: '''Question''': is it correct that you are doing a GSoC project mentored by pbdR, i.e. you are affiliated with it? --[[Special:Contributions/188.98.216.174|188.98.216.174]] ([[User talk:188.98.216.174|talk]]) 10:11, 6 July 2013 (UTC)

&lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
* :&lt;small class="delsort-notice"&gt;Note:  This debate has been included in the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Deletion sorting/Computing|list of Computing-related deletion discussions]]. [[User:Gene93k|• Gene93k]] ([[User talk:Gene93k|talk]]) 15:21, 28 June 2013 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
* :&lt;small class="delsort-notice"&gt;Note:  This debate has been included in the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Deletion sorting/Software|list of Software-related deletion discussions]]. [[User:Gene93k|• Gene93k]] ([[User talk:Gene93k|talk]]) 15:21, 28 June 2013 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

* &lt;big&gt;'''Keep'''&lt;/big&gt;. pbdR is also interested by HPC community; however, common inaccurate impression of pbdR and Rmpi can be fount at http://www.open-mpi.org/community/lists/users/2013/02/21466.php. Wikipedia should be a perfect place to distinguish and educate this. [[User:Wccsnow|Wccsnow]] ([[User talk:Wccsnow|talk]]) 01:16, 1 July 2013 (UTC)
:: '''Question:''' Would you please '''disclose''' whether you happen to be affiliated with pdbR? Your name indicates you might be Wei-Chen Chen. I've seen you promote this package and his articles all over Wikipedia... --[[Special:Contributions/188.98.216.174|188.98.216.174]] ([[User talk:188.98.216.174|talk]]) 09:10, 6 July 2013 (UTC)

*'''Keep''' There is no WP policy that states an article needs to be notable outside a given specialty. Instead the real criterion is whether (1) there are multiple independent in-depth reliable sources and (2) the article has surmountable problems. The article itself is well-written and well-cited. Most of the citations specifically about pbdMPI are primary, so the main question is whether there are RS available. Reference 25 is a tutorial by Raim, who I think is independent of the authors and reference 26, the CRAN task view by Eddelbuettel is almost certainly independent. The tutorial goes into a great deal of depth about pbdMPI and the task view has a paragraph about it, which is marginal for the in-depth criterion. Thus notability is marginal, but I am inclined toward keep because (1) a CRAN task view is a short list of the best R packages for a task and the presence of pbdMPI on the list indicates notability by itself and (2) notability for this new R package will only grow over time. Marginal notability and an article with no major problems suggests keeping the article. --[[User:Mark viking|Mark viking]] ([[User talk:Mark viking|talk]]) 22:20, 3 July 2013 (UTC)
&lt;hr style="width:55%;" /&gt;
:&lt;span style="color:#FF4F00;"&gt;'''[[WP:RELIST|Relisted]] to generate a more thorough discussion so a clearer consensus may be reached.'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
:&lt;small&gt;Please add new comments below this notice. Thanks, [[User:Mark Arsten|Mark Arsten]] ([[User talk:Mark Arsten|talk]]) 20:19, 4 July 2013 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- from Template:Relist --&gt;[[Category:Relisted AfD debates|{{SUBPAGENAME}}]]
&lt;hr style="width:55%;" /&gt;

* '''Keep''' although weak for me. Indeed, just because there is a narrow community of notability is not by itself grounds for deletion. The article does however, need to show it is notable by reliable sources outside of the group that produced it.  There are all sorts of packages promoted by their own developers, and Wikipedia is not the place to promote them using assertions of those same developers. I agree with above arguments that notability is marginal but seems more likely than not to stand the test of time. However, I think the article itself has huge problems. Parts are OK but other parts include a HOWTO which might not belong. Worse is the over-use of inline raw URL links. Generally the body of the article should ''not'' have the raw URL links, but be in English with wikilinks on first use of each related term. If a term is not notable enough for its own Wikipedia article, then do not link it in the article, but put in external links section of the article on the term that it describes. The section order is also not up to standard. But those can be worked on if it stays. [[User:W Nowicki|W Nowicki]] ([[User talk:W Nowicki|talk]]) 20:18, 5 July 2013 (UTC)

* '''Delete'''. The article seems to have a strong advertisement bias (see above for the COI question), and we shouldn't start documenting all R packages on Wikipedia. It could probably be '''merged''' into some R related article, too. "Appeared in Sept. 2012" certainly does not indicate this is widely adopted yet, is it? --[[Special:Contributions/188.98.216.174|188.98.216.174]] ([[User talk:188.98.216.174|talk]]) 09:15, 6 July 2013 (UTC)
: I've just done a pass over the article, removing a lot of unrelated references (e.g. citing R; but since R has it's own wikipedia article, we don't need references for its existence!). Now very little references remain, in particular I didn't notice much ''independent'' third-party references on pdbR. [http://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=2565186978612607332&amp;as_sdt=2005&amp;sciodt=0,5 Google Scholar doesn't find any either]. So I'd say delete it for now, and maybe re-add it in 1-2 years when the test of time has proven it to be a commonly used package.  --[[Special:Contributions/188.98.216.174|188.98.216.174]] ([[User talk:188.98.216.174|talk]]) 10:11, 6 July 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>nuosgainpf0gg3qo3o3ps8vdwi02s0h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>