<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Wikipedia:Wikipedia Signpost/2007-12-10/Technology report</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>14553205</id>
    <revision>
      <id>366540982</id>
      <parentid>185249357</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-07T11:23:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Signpost Book Bot</username>
        <id>12464849</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Updating post page for [[Wikipedia:Wikipedia Signpost|Wikipedia Signpost]] ([[WP:BOT|BOT]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;{{Wikipedia:Wikipedia Signpost/Templates/Long-image}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;
__NOTOC__
__NOEDITSECTION__
&lt;h2 style="margin-right:60px;"&gt;Bugs, Repairs, and Internal Operational News&lt;/h2&gt;
:&lt;small&gt;By [[User:ais523|ais523]], [[10 December]], [[2007]]&lt;/small&gt;

This is a summary of recent technology and site configuration changes that affect the English Wikipedia. Note that not all changes described here are necessarily live as of press time; the English Wikipedia is currently running version {{CURRENTVERSION}}, and changes to the software with a version number higher than that will not yet be active. Configuration changes and changes to interface messages, however, become active immediately.

=== Fixed bugs ===
* A bug that accidentally caused an extraneous colon and space to show up on the deletion confirmation screen when a default deletion reason was given was fixed. ([[rev:28073|r28073]], [[bugzilla:12178|bug 12178]])
* It seems that the tentative fix for the UNIQ bug that was still being tested at press time last week did work ([[Wikipedia:Wikipedia Signpost/2007-12-03/Software issues|''see related story'']]). ([[rev:28004|r28004]], [[bugzilla:12154|bug 12154]])
* The history display for a page no longer says "Revision history" as a subtitle, because that information is already present in the main title. ([[rev:28137|r28137]], [[bugzilla:11993|bug 11993]])
* A fix was added that speeds up loading times by several minutes on Internet Explorer 5 on Mac OS 9. ([[rev:28192|r28192]], [[bugzilla:12055|bug 12055]])
* The paging (next 50/previous 50) links on [[Special:Linksearch]] now work in some situations where they failed before (for instance, if "mailto:" is used as the search term). ([[rev:28208|r28208]], [[bugzilla:12107|bug 12107]])

=== New features ===
* The 'Related changes' option ([[Special:Recentchangeslinked]]) now has an RSS feed; in particular, if a page is being used as a public watchlist, this provides a way to get an RSS feed for that watchlist. ([[rev:28274|r28274]], [[bugzilla:943|bug 943]])

=== Configuration changes ===
* The Gadgets extension ([[mw:Extension:Gadgets]]) was enabled on the English Wikipedia. The extension allows administrators to add JavaScript and CSS (user scripts and user styles) as preferences on [[Special:Preferences]], in a new 'Gadgets' section. (The procedure for administrators to add new gadgets is somewhat complicated, and explained on the extension page.) Currently, the gadgets that have been added are [[Wikipedia:Tools/Navigation popups|navigation popups]], [[Wikipedia:Tools/Disable access keys|a gadget to disable access keys]], and a gadget to open external links in a new tab or window. ([[bugzilla:12190|bug 12190]])

=== Breaking software changes ===
* The messages [[MediaWiki:Searchsize]] and [[MediaWiki:Searchscore]] have been replaced with [[MediaWiki:Lucene-resultsize]] and [[MediaWiki:Lucene-searchscore]], to allow for better control over localisation (the message is given a number formatted according to the relevant language rather than a plain number), so any customisations there need to be repeated. ([[rev:28141|r28141]]/[[rev:28181|r28181]], [[bugzilla:10869|bug 10869]])

=== Other technology news ===
* A change [[Wikipedia:Village Pump (technical)#Rollback for regular users|was scheduled to the software]] that would allow use of rollback to all users, not just administrators. There are new rate limits in the software to limit the rate at which non-administrators can use rollback, although they are currently irrelevant because non-administrators can't use rollback anyway. Following some discussion about the change (both supporting and opposing the change), this change was reverted; the limits are still present but non-admin rollback will not now be enabled without consensus on an individual wiki. A discussion about the matter here on the English Wikipedia is being held at [[Wikipedia:Rollback for non-administrators]]. (change made in [[rev:28193|r28193]], reverted in [[rev:28248|r28248]])

=== Ongoing news ===
*Internationalisation has been continuing as normal; help is always appreciated! See [[mw:Localisation statistics]] for how complete the translations of languages you know are, and post any updates to [[mediazilla:|bugzilla]] or use [[betawiki:|Betawiki]].


&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Wikipedia:Wikipedia Signpost/Templates/Footer|{{BASEPAGENAME}}|2007-12-03|2007-12-17|{{SUBPAGENAME}}}}
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
[[Category:Wikipedia Signpost archives 2007-12]]</text>
      <sha1>bkdjvmgzssp4m4te7z5cg63rhuu64yz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>