<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Wikipedia:WikiProject WikipediaWeekly/CurrentTranscriptions/Episode6</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>8135471</id>
    <revision>
      <id>94125035</id>
      <parentid>94119019</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-12-13T20:25:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EdJohnston</username>
        <id>1521335</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* WikiWorld cartoons */ Another typo in name of cartoon</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Episode 6==

;Participants
*Host: [[User:Fuzheado|Fuzheado]] (F)
*Panel: [[User:Tawker|Tawker]] (T), [[User:Tdxiang|Tdxiang]] (X), [[User:Kelly Martin|Kelly Martin]] (K), [[User:SushiGeek|SushiGeek]] (S), [[User:Chacor]] (C), [[User:Messedrocker]] (M).

----
'''T:''' This is Wikipedia Weekly Episode 6, for the week of November 20, 2006. 

'''F:''' Welcome to another episode of the Wikipedia Weekly. I'm your host Andrew Lih, also known as user [[User:Fuzheado]] on the English Wikipedia. So we're doing something new this week, with a record seven panelists from around the world thanks to a new version of Skype. I'm happy to welcome [[User:Tawker|Tawker]] from Vancouver, Canada.

'''T:''' Hi there.

'''F:''' We have from [[Singapore]], [[User:Tdxiang|Tdxiang]].

'''X:''' Hey, hi, nice to be here.

'''F:''' And we also have [[User:NSLE]] or Chacor.

'''C:''' Hello, nice to be here again.

'''F:''' And from the United States, from the state in New Jersey we have [[User:Messedrocker]], also known as James.

'''M:''' Hello.

'''F:''' And in Illinois we have Kelly Martin.

'''K:''' Good evening, or morning.

'''F:''' And from the state of Wisconsin we have [[User:SushiGeek|SushiGeek]], or User:1ne.

'''S:''' Hello.

===China blocking===

'''F:''' So thanks for joining us, we've got a record seven folks - so let's get right to the news we've got. Obviously one of the bigger stories in the news is the unblocking, re-blocking of Chinese Wikipedia. So yesterday in China between 9 AM and 10 AM there were lots of reports of people not being able to access Wikipedia, pretty much across the country that's the case at this point. And we're just kind of in a holding pattern to see whether this will open up again, but this is typical of a lot of blocks in China, they take some time to shake out. 

'''S:''' Yeah, five years ago they did this with the New York Times, now they're doing this with Wikipedia. Five years they'll be doing it to somebody else, just watch. 

'''F:''' Yeah, you know, these things, no-one really knows exactly why they happen, and we were talking before about how even the Chinese government does not acknowledge that they explicitly block sites.

'''C:''' Yeah, RSF ([[Reporters Without Borders|Reporters sans frontières]]) have covered this story, and right now there is they are saying it is not possible to tell whether it is available because the authorities have changed their minds or because of technical problems, that's what RSF are saying.

'''F:''' Right. I mean, the interesting thing about how China blocks these sites is that you don't ever quite know whether it's a technical problem or whether it's something actively being blocked. And that's something pretty unique to China: if you look at other regimes that block sites, like Saudi Arabia, they use off-the-shelf blocking software that actually puts up a screen that says the equivalent of "The Kingdom of [[Saudi Arabia]] has blocked this site because it falls into the category of porn," or falls into the category of something like that. The [[China|PRC]] blocking methods just bring you a connection reset error, or something that you might possibly see as a network problem or something like that.

'''S:''' Yeah, you might think it's an error.

'''F:''' Right, and that's why it's always hard to pinpoint these things and usually you have to contact about 10 or 15 of your friends to check it out from where they are, what [[Internet Service Provider|ISP]] you're using using, what city are you in... so in that sense, its a tough thing to nail down in terms of why these blocks are happening and where they are happening.

'''T:''' Well, it's very hodgepodge as far as I've seen, the [[Great Firewall of China]] isn't really one central piece of software - it's various pieces of software for various regions and really is sort of a hacked together piece of software, sort of like [[MediaWiki]] itself. It's definitely very informal in a lot of places, and there's just a wide degree of variation just between one location and another ISP, and things can really change a lot.

'''F:''' Right.

'''S:''' Oh, I have a question.

'''F:''' Sure.

'''S:''' Does this block apply to [[Macau]] and [[Hong Kong]]?

'''F:''' Absolutely does not. It's a good question, I mean, a lot of people still don't quite know how the arrangement works with Hong Kong and Macau, which are technically [[Special Administrative Region|special administrative regions]]. They are a completely different telecom system and they have their [[Internet]] completely unfiltered. They don't have to worry about it. 

In fact, I think last week we talked a little bit about the contributions from Hong Kong and Taiwan and I think the majority of contributions to Wikipedia, at least according to the stats that Kelly Martin put up, were from Hong Kong, like 26% or something like that. Taiwan was 24%. 

'''K:''' Yeah, roughly half the contributions to the zh: Wiki come from either Hong Kong or Taiwan, United States being a distant third.

'''F:''' Right. So right before the block happened yesterday, we actually reached a record in terms of how many new users registered in 24 hours on Chinese Wikipedia, and it was just over 1800, I think. It was 1,823, so that's on average one person per minute was registered on Chinese Wikipedia which was huge, but then that block got put in and suddenly we dropped we back down. I think the average now is 700 per day. That's still pretty high - that's above the German Wikipedia - but it's still far off from 1,800 that we hit at the peak.

'''T:''' Well the big thing with the accounts now is that a lot of [[Tor]] proxies are now blocked 'anonymous only'. So if you have an account on Wikipedia, it will let you do pretty much everything that you can do before, you're not affected by the block on the Tor proxy, the open proxy. So it opened up a lot of freedom to a lot of folks to use that method to bypass the firewall.

'''K:''' If you have an account on a project too, you can register an account for another person while logged in. It's not very well know; you go to Special, the user login, while already logged, and then the create another account for someone. It's a way that, if someone wants an account but doesn't have one, and they're in a position where they have to use one of the proxies that blocks anonymous users, they can still get an account. Most people don't know that one.

'''T:''' Yeah, that's a handy feature to say the least, and just an other big thing... I'm just taking a look at Andrew's [http://blog.andrewlih.com blog] here: 

:&lt;small&gt;[Excerpt from [http://www.andrewlih.com/blog/2006/11/17/understanding-wikipedias-re-block/ this] post]:&lt;/small&gt;''I do not know the details about the website you mentioned. The Chinese [PRC] government actively supports and promotes the development of Internet. By 2005, there have been over 123 million Internet users and 788,000 websites in China. China has become the second largest country for Internet in the world. We oversee the Internet according to laws, this is also what every country in the world does commonly.''

It seems to be the first time that Andrew's pointed out that the Chinese government really doesn't mention Wikipedia much in transcripts, and it's sort of an official deny of Wikipedia, that I'm pretty sure is bogus but it's just sort of interesting seeing that come out.

'''F:''' Yeah, I mean, pretty much they just don't comment on anything related to blocking because, 1) they don't have to, and 2)-

'''T:''' -it doesn't exist-

'''F:''' -yeah, it doesn't exist and nothing good can ever come from talking about blocking, I guess I can see their point about that. So we're going to keep an eye on it on the mailing lists. There's been some, I guess, mixed feelings about the ''Reporters sans frontières'' with how they've been reporting this. I tend to agree with folks who criticize with RSF and other folks who say, "whenever things like these happen, RSF comes around and almost gloats about it," saying, you know, "this a lesson for companies that you can stand up to China and get your way." I don't think that's productive. 

'''M:''' Nah. Well these businesses, their interest is making money short-term for now. I mean, unless they were to profit specifically from teaching China a lesson, then they really have no interest in doing it because it would just cost them money.

'''F:''' Right. I don't think you can take a lesson from a nonprofit and apply it  to a publicly traded company that are responsible to shareholders, it's not fair. 

'''M:''' Yeah. I mean, while I don't really support a company like [[Google]] giving this blocking technology to China, you know their object is to make a profit and they're going to think, you know, "there's billions of dollars in China that we could make and we aren't making, so let's go do this in China."

'''F:''' Yeah, well Google didn't give any technology, I think most-

'''M:''' No, no they didn't, I didn't mean it that way, I mean the search engine...

'''F:''' Yeah, in terms of Google playing ball with censoring their own search results inside China, like the Google.cn site, there's been some criticism there.

'''T:''' Anyways, we've got a lot more to cover on this episode. Unfortunately we're trying to keep this under 10 hours today, I know we're run a bit long in the last few things.

===Wiki search engine===

'''T:''' One of the new things is that apparently our search engine, that previously sucked - like, a lot - has finally sped up. Just coming in from Wikizine, newly-created articles can be found a lot faster by using the wiki search function - our new server now works full-time to create the search index so all wikis can be re-indexed every about thirty hours. Updating before was kind of slow because unfortunately we just didn't have the resources dedicated to searching... and it's sped things up, but I'd still say our on-site search probably needs a little bit of work. Sometimes, it's still not quite as effective as going into Google and throwing in "Wikipedia", or Yahoo, or whatever--

'''M:''' Yes, in my opinion nothing will be superior to Google, but then again, Google's business is developing search engines - that is not what MediaWiki is. MediaWiki's goal is not to develop a search engine; it's to develop a content-hosting service software, so if we were to combine the efforts of Google and make a search engine and the efforts of MediaWiki to make a content-storage Wiki then we could get something very nice out of it.

'''K:''' To be fair, the [[Lucene]] search engine that we're using is a pretty good product actually, we're just not using it very well. It's because it's a hunk of [[Java (programming language)|java code]]... it was written by [[Apache]] for integration with the Apache framework, and it doesn't get along that well with the [[.php]] that this system is written in and it's not great for indexing into databases-- articles--- to text that's stored in the really weird format that we store our articles... that MediaWiki stores articles in, if you've ever dug into it, you'd realise that they're stored in sometimes in compressed format or they're stored in these different formats that don't look at all like text. So it's... a lot of the challenge is getting a product that was designed for one thing to "talk" with another product that was ''not'' designed to "talk" with it at all. Uhm, and the problem with Google's technology is that Google is not going to open-source it, and one of our founding principles with the [[Wikimedia Foundation]] is that there will be no non-free software used for our production process for the purpose of delivering content, and so, Google's search engine, as great as it might be, isn't free, and thus, therefore, we can't use it.

'''T:''' Same with Yahoo! and pretty much every other search engine. 'Cause that's your business, essentially... it's your algorithm.

'''F:''' Well, there is two complaints I would have, one-- well, not complaints, observations-- one is that maybe, these other search engines like Google work so well that there is not a compelling case for folks to try to fix the problem inside Wikipedia, but also, the other thing is when you do a search in Wikipedia, when it comes back, the first half of the screen gives no useful information! So, if I did a [[Special:Search/cat mba|search on]] "cat mba", for example, if you look, the results start... maybe around 400, 500 pixels down on the screen. And I can only see three search results after doing the search on Wikipedia. So I think we need to help redesign the search results. If you look on Google, if you do a Google search you can see seven search results.

'''T:''' Same with Yahoo!, you get a lot more bang for your buck in terms of screen real estate with specialised search engines... something we definitely should take a look at.

'''F:''' Yeah, usability-wise we need to work on that.

'''M:''' One thing we should do is have, like, an open-source effort to develop a really good search engine. Really good open-source search engine.

'''K:''' Well, there already are good open-source search engines, we just aren't using them. And we're not using them as well as we could. Lucene's much more pwerful than you see, because the way we're using Lucene doesn't really take full advantage of Lucene.

===Wiki text hard to parse?===

'''F:''' Hey, Kelly, let me ask you a question: Does the problem that we have with getting a real true parser for wiki-markup, is that related to that as well?

'''K:''' Probably not, the parser issue is a different story entirely, although in a way, it would be because... my personal feeling, this is my attitude on this, is that we should be storing wiki articles in [[.xml]], and then we could leverage all this different xml content-management engines that are out there to do search, to do metadata extraction, but we're not; we're storing articles in wiki text. Wiki text is a truly horrendous markup language, uhm, one of the things that... I may get a little geeky on you here, in programming languages there's a thing that we call... there's these classes of languages that're known because it's easy to parse... there's one class called the "LL" and one class called "LR" and I'm not going to bore you with why they are called that, but the simpler a language is, they have this 
suffix and then there's a digit, which tells you how many characters you have to be able to look ahead you in order to parse. Wiki text is not in LL(n) for any n nor is it in LR(n) for any n. In order to parse Wiki text you might have to go all the way to the end of the article just to understand what the character you're looking at right now is.  That is a design defect, it's the result of the fact that wiki text has been cobbled together. Over the course of the last five years we've added things to it because they'd be convenient, and no-one thought about the implications for processing. So when you have that million-byte article, and you'd laugh at me, but we have a couple that are coming. There was recently an administrative page that was over a quarter-megabyte in length, it has to read that whole article into the system memory to process it. In fact it has to pass over it *repeatedly* because of the way the parser is written.  This makes parsing extremely slow, so it discourages trying to do things on parsed wiki text. 

'''F''': Yeah, and it makes it hard to make tools based around this too, because you basically just get this (what you might call) a gigantic if-then-else statement that parses wiki text and then transplant that or dissect that.

'''K''': It's very difficult to do any kind of work on wiki text, at least, in the *full* wiki text. There are a lot of shortcuts you can take to do a mostly as good enough for the job right now basis, but doing a full wikitext parser is really hard. On top of which is the fact that there isn't really a specification for wiki text either, there's just a reference implementation. And to be quite honest, no-one really understands how it works. 

'''F''': I think Tawker and I covered this in Episode 1, I believe. We talked about how Google has this Summer of Code program, where they get really smart kids to work on projects, and this past summer we had one student work on creating a parser for wiki text. And at Wikimania where they all presented their results he basically just told the audience of techies, 'I give up! It can't be done. Right now it's impossible', and everyone agreed with him. It was pretty much this disaster where we don't know what to do.  If you wanted to make it easier, you'd have to go through all the wiki pages and alter the wiki markup to something more regular, and it would be really horrible. 

'''K''': It's actually not as hard as it sounds, because it's the long tail thing, and you can probably parse 80% of the wiki text with a relatively simple parser. So you write that simpler parser. There is the universal wiki markup project that's going out there and Wikimedia has not participated in that as much as it probably should, considering that it's the largest and most prominent wiki on the net, but there is a project to develop a universal markup for wikis, and hopefully the markup that comes out of that will be a lot more parseable. I have a feeling that they'll probably come out with something that can be parsed by a standard XSLT parser, which would be really quite nice, because that would leverage a lot of existing code.

'''F''': With that, we'll declare the end of the geek section of the podcast, which got a little deeper than we wanted but it's important, I mean. I'm not sure how much we can move on without getting a better parser in Wikipedia. 

===WikiWorld cartoons===

'''F''': So our next story is WikiWorld from Greg Williams of the Tampa Tribune. This is an interesting story of an illustrator and designer for the Tampa Tribune newspaper, and he was such a huge fan of Wikipedia that he just started sketching cartoons in his spare time. And he's come out with some great cartoons on several Wikipedia articles. So I think at this point he's released four cartoons, and they're on Doctor Seuss, Hammerspace, Pet Skunk, and Tony Clifton, which are really great, and I actually saw these in the Wikimedia Foundation offices a few months' back. It was just kind of held for a while, and now I'm glad he's actually released them to the world.  These kind of remind you of Sunday morning or Ripley's Believe it or Not type of cartoons that used to show up. I'm not sure they still do that.

'''K''': It is! They still do those. My favorite of these cartoons is definitely the Hammerspace one, although the Doctor Seuss one is good too. It's actually kind of interesting because people started adding these cartoons to the articles that they're drawn from. He has used actually the opening text or selections of text from the articles to letter the cartoons. And there were people that were actually adding the cartoons to the articles because he has released them under a Creative Commons License that allows their use on the projects. Then other people were removing them because they're really intrusive on the articles.

'''X''': They're not exactly relevant and if they were to have pictures they should have pictures related to the subject that's being discussed, as opposed to basically a made-up picture of the article. It's not exactly relevant. 

'''S''': Well they're great I think for sort of an external Wikizine, sort of an external newsletter, sort of a lighter view of Wikipedia.    

'''X''': Kind of like spoken Wiki News only it's like a comic.

'''K''': It doesn't really have the value that the spoken Wiki does. The spoken wiki actually allows people who can't read a screen because of a disability or a capability allows them to listen to a recorded version which gives us a broader audience. This is more along the lines of 'this is cute, this is interesting, this is funny'.  It would be a great merchandising option. I think a lot of people would pay to have those on T-shirts.

'''F''': Absolutely, I think it'd be wonderful to have them on T-shirts. If you look at the Hammerspace one, as Kelly mentioned, it's one of the more interesting ones. It's a four-panel cartoon with a cartoon monkey as the main character. And if you don't know what Hammerspace is, it says 'Hammerspace is a fan-envisioned, extra-dimensional, instantly accessible storage area. In fiction, the concept is jokingly used to explain how characters in animation, comics and games are capable of producing objects out of thin air.  So, it shows a monkey pulling a cartoon hammer out of nowhere. So you might have seen these in like, Bugs Bunny or any type of cartoons. And it's a really fun way of seeing the text that you might have entered into the Wikipedia article showing up in a professional-looking cartoon. That's just the great thing about free content.   

'''C''': For those that want to have a look at this, I'm just mentioning that they're available in Commons.

'''F''': Right, they're in Wiki Commons under Creative Commons Share-Alike Attribution License.

'''X''': Look for Greg Williams, that's what they're sorted under. 

'''T''': As usual, we'll put a note in the show notes, of course.

'''F''': We'll put a note in the show notes about it. So I think Danny had mentioned that there's more in the pipeline, and it'll be great to see those coming out.

===Board reorganization===

'''F''': Our next story is 'Board Reorganization'. So Anthere, the current Foundation chair, has provided more information in a long post to the foundation mailing list about the proposed board reorganization, the outcome of the board retreat, and the foundation and chapters.  So Kelly, what do you think about the new announcement from Anthere?

'''K''': Well, it's a rather long announcement and I admit that I haven't had a chance to read it as deeply as I'd like but it's good to see the board finally doing something to improve its organization and be a little bit more responsive to  the needs that exist for an organization of this size that has gone from being a few people meeting in Jimmy's living room probably to a million-dollar-plus-a-year charity that runs one of the most prominent sites on the internet. 
The board seems to be adapting to having an executive director, which is still somewhat a new thing for them (they've only had one since June). They're now holding a weekly executive director's meeting between Brad and whichever board members can find their way to attend which will probably in most cases just be Anthere and whoever else is interested in the topics of the day  but it's good to see that kind of interaction between the executive and the board. They are also going to try to continue to have the monthly meetings for discussing Board issues, which is probably about the right rate. It would be nice if they could get a bit less frequent. In most non-profit organizations of this  nature the board meets quarterly or even annually.  The degree of involvement that has been expected of board members for the Wikimedia Foundation is unusually high and has probably made it difficult for them to recruit the right people for the board.  Especially with the topic of board expansion on the horizon it's important that they do something to reduce the degree of pain that a potential board member would be feeling if they chose to accept the position.

'''F''': Yeah Kelly, I think you touched on something which is pretty significant, which is that there is still this kind of tension between what is board and what is executive, and as you said this board that we have for the Wikimedia Foundation acts much more executively than most boards of non-profits.

'''K''': Oh yes, definitely more along the lines of an executive entity. And that's largely because there hasn't been a separate executive director. When Jimbo was still board president he was handling a lot of the executive duties himself and there wasn't really seen to be that much a division between Jimbo the person who makes things happen and Jimbo the president of the board, or the board as opposed to Jimbo.  A lot of people didn't see a distinction between Jimbo and the board as a whole. To some degree there was some truth to that because originally we had two board members that were essentially *silent*, and they were expected to vote Jimbo's way in all matters. Michael Davis, however, has ceased to be silent and has taken a very active role in the organization which I think is a very  positive thing for the Foundation. 

And with Tim Shell resigning at the end of the year, which is another thing that was recently announced, there will be no silent or mostly silent board members (Tim has never been very active) and that will bring the board to a fully-active [state], hopefully a much more dynamic board  that will be more able to focus on the strategic issues, because they will be able to push the day-to-day executive issues onto Brad and whoever they authorize Brad to hire. ('''Someone''': Danny?). Well Danny is certainly part of that equation. Danny obviously works with Brad and gets a great deal of the things done. In fact Danny is probably the person who gets the most things done on a day-to-day basis. But it's Brad's job to make sure those things get done and it's Brad's responsibility. But the main thing is that now it's Brad's reponsibility, it's not Jimbo's responsibility like it used to be and it's not the board's responsibility on a day-to-day basis.  The board can behave more like a normal non-profit board and start looking at strategic planning, and not waste its time on, 'Geez, how are we going to get through next week?'

'''-- transcript ends at 25:07 --'''

[Full length of this episode is 58:29.  Your help with further transcription is invited. ]

&lt;small&gt;The following text is the raw output produce by [[Dragon NaturallySpeaking]], and needs extensive copyediting. Please consider improving it yourself, or take its content with '''''extreme''''' caution. &lt;/small&gt;
----

;From 25 minutes
Can behave like a normal reports are looking at strategic planning and not waste time and cease related straight right money on announcement was also Grecian of the committee led by grads and an Oscar for a process in Rotterdam and Jean Bart whose the person from tennis that's to find aid and other executive director and that's can be merged in search the folksy I will be and I eyed I haven't heard much about what kind of sit with a great sharia if the report has specified criteria for what it wants what he considers to be a eighth and appropriate executive director of its leading a server at an Oscar in &amp; sound discretion to come up with those criteria, Oscar was a anonymous taken was the one that was a service or cursor runner-up in the four elections in this is one of the I voted for him so I'm &amp; think of Leviticus restatement like a light sound in interesting committee the inclusion of the of one of her friends and chemist at the Bennett could sponsor of what the media over the years by providing God and with and in tanks and other services and in the eye and skin hosting location, what will they interest is the ideas that I don't having good idea but they're how there can be looking for executive director who they have in mind are falling certainly part of the issues can be what's the ultimate location for Wicca media foundation if it's to the a in the basis infused in Florida that servant in effect the search for incentive for the eyeing that that may have positives and negatives a moving the moving the Borg are living the foundation stone of the location could be tricky although not really they can actually move the entire offices to love the Pasadena Estates friends bring since interesting problems in unsafe after reincorporate Dom or there could be difficult is that the nonprofit status ignominy were within United States and all that had to do is maintain one person in the Ford area who can act as a as a is an agency meant to be Jimbo saw his year in stare for Michael who also was there or to be a hired the Turner's services to do this for a relatively small amount for your time so was use was little things on Kerry mentions in the policy of the ivory may recover the executor or to serve shy there's also there is some discussion about board expansion strategy but entered it and go into details on and so it is that we can conclude that the board will probably be something to family don't do what you found eyed my impression is that there is still a lot of this disagreement among most within the warden with the other vested parties which is invalid the presence of some of the larger chapter organizations in other people who have a strong interest on interest money things he mentions it's the bylaws are going to be rewritten C. D. with inconsistencies between Lafayette with the official bylaws says in the actual practices of the foundation pound anywhere you should read the bylaw aside will realize that the bylaws don't really relate that well to is the meantime that the foundation has been running to listen harder of the bylaws found this would be a problem if this is the stock corporation or memory Corp. but the young foundation is neither and it's really it's as long as the board is happy to as you can do about it going on there is one sticking point about how in the bylaws they were still mentioned of membership yes goodbye was doing to mention members and there is a mechanism to its use amid the fortitude to members of form and paid membership fee to become a member asked a line laws as right did it in the bylaws into my understanding I did is in dispute is whether you're no person or one for I successfully completed a cost alarmed on right now the is as low forms of listed on the the form found is never in the form are threenever a hound and impeding the members of the Durban to find so Londoners of the million dollars in area or its $.20 exit is that there's that's that's what see a lot of what is being discussed there is at the form of the bylaws are written by Al by Alex Roche technically it was it via when the foundation was set velvet with consulting the Jimmy and with the others and to the words really revisited much after that and I was in 2000 and 20,003 year 2002 and it's now 2006 and has been revisited all in yours this machine so dramatically listen a situation where the foundation and its written causes a tiny ketchup with the lightning's piece the community rated system of Cisco most relations were killed away around with organization beads you will or Lisa Strachan of follow the masses as the they're moving forward and rubbing off in the thing to does to her corrections and is for immaturity CE in a day and night makes it very difficult

;From 30 minutes
What security do that in each IEC those of us due to have been involved in English the graffiti know how much that process is hurting cats in the mold like that out by 800 projects if this becomes it it's amazing that anything all begun the unveils a discussion of the seamen and there mentions the advisory Board Powell Bush's internal about its refers to a previous discussion on it there's been talk for quite a long time now adding a divisive work with them but a lot of disagreement as to what with the purpose of having a marriage of order who should be on for what it will do I think a lot of this comes down to the fact at the media foundation has always been a nonprofit system run by people who actually no idea how to run nonprofit time they've done a year and a job in a time that they don't have the years there is this isn't that much on experience there and they don't understand what they're doing and so they been begging it was it works okay odds of the of blood in the random columns to does the whole thing of the violence is an example on the ends that I think a lot of of the Druids were really brought this to a head was the was the a virus audit eyes and I'm proud and see there responsible the file certain tax returns improve their impact out for is a nonprofit entity in the iris will periodically audit you to make sure that you're doing with those the doing and velvety heads and issues there and don't I'll think anyone lies not in not yeah I know we're doing I'm glad to the interrogation is doing an eye itself it hired as Cemetery people and have a is making sure doesn't not the iris in writing as I was going to say like the standards of the Liang agreed to hold practice is affirmed in agenda will improve over time like each carry terraces very informal in the like a people who were yes nitrogen knowledge now after Kim Jong resigns me yet his replacing it with a totally active board and were during the eye and each of the things that work and as I will be better over time the a lot of bomb to the La Quinta years that Schieffer the icy visitors into some sling from most of these issues I'm also any there's a lot of that load is well mania want to get everything done time you know this turn of the question of their previous apps on again or bring much of a method previous episode where Jason Calla cast was trying to is that adds my question is when you changes were nonprofit is looking he he iris regulation for nonprofits is my conclusion that he would not end as a reason for them for the meeting is a content delivery getting to the the primary function with the media foundation is to publish no information is a generally accepted crap this a Internet publishers to seem to use advertising is a sponsoring getting my conclusion that these the deeds of the online publication of the encyclopedia that is the width of the dictionary that all the other private projects would ended generation at ready to be considered primary revenue by the irises of the siege of the primary and secondary revenue and/or I think it's related and unrelated revenues of related revenue is it's consistent with your primary purpose for existing in miles on the latest in a serious sewing T-shirts in your actually a know out of a yeah I'm and HIV awareness station you're selling T-shirts to raise money that's not related to the IT market of the it's letting hours as if had let a the advertising since that's the way you make money and in publishing it would be considered finding you can have valid leaving their a unlimited witch of inhabitants of the two thirds of your revenue can come from from I married it from your related activity there is quality the excellent workout located in that it tax them as American tax logging how it will not lost even more it and then you'd be coming ice I first had filed a news overturns a felt artist returns I fouled corporation returns not interest are the leading lights at me yeah but founded in inherently at odds is the way the latest night it would be at a we might the validation might have to structure itself differently if it were going to never ties and direction it might be mistaken into establish a rust or a perhaps the private foundation of public candidates to my hectic cream with one component in head to immature interrelationships between them ended the night the different tax handling like the IE would not fundamentally change to the rule denying an organization of where this is going to a sergeant is sushi mentioned telecast in Riyadh on a think out an assist announced a lot this past week that he's resigned from AOL so use along with AOL and the

;From 35 minutes
Disclosure people it's not because he's come to join with you to yeah I to our knowledge so I don't Wanna imagine that no sense Mr. town the you a number of us are not in art in our very I'm turned to her decision comment on the offensive comments in the eye I comment on his lifetime it's my blog in my, was it doesn't get it and in Google a lot of it is that's like a lot of people who are in the Internet content delivery you like you can people you can't rant them is like a goal are prodded like a liking to eat 350 paper he mean he can't just say that it's a feuding assay identity to eat 350 fans and at crates of goods you can't insanity to you 250 have visited time to know so well that's their calculus ago so the what it is her title as is the people who work in industry everything is about impressions ease-of-use and in what you mean he isn't about Saddam a gig in people are going to Wicca media Tom to get the somewhere else they're not going there to their going there for the content and the delivery just won't be this image the advertising will owe sure their experience and union plants that I think the time to monetize the media like that into a length of the well that's it's good to be interesting to see how these foundation matters shakeout missed a lot of meetings to have with the board members and I a lot or consultation and actually a thing on terror and Erik Moeller who is the Secretary executive secretary have made a plea to everyone they're not getting a lot of feedback all these things so yes that's of course it's digital to stork every so often the board gets on the whole on its a fire lit under it for some reason any thumbs-up of the all these great claims about as they do for example in Jane and it was January of a sex they had the day had the big meeting where they didn't cannot announce all the committees the other chapter committed a special practice committee on a thing for you those committees were for never did anything it's not November at the finest immediate ever do anything fund-raising has never done anything at the blogs that he talked about something with the Taliban are no of he has a press which generates you should select to the light one can't of 1% with media's revenue in its class example dismissed in the ongoing wound embarrassment of the calm low of the a cycle of a committee that this committee responsible for branding in aren't going to trademark in all the other aspects of of the how with immediate preserves its intellectual property interests not in the encyclopedia or the template in its limit in the name to Wicca media foundation went immediately to keep you name out in the logos that are used that committee has never been able before now it is its remarkable considering of the Army needs to see people out there estimating that would permit with the tedious it has a brand value in the billions of dollars that we have no mechanism to defend its crew writes that aspects, recognized by Mike is going to send and arena bureaucracy and setting up the committees have a personal variety feelings is that it got needs her to do any doing anything they should be dissolved as it is any thinking is that it into atheism cases these are companies or committees was the board said it was going to form and may never get you the is the follow-through never where yelled is not in a failed hasn't been formed to fail so I think either they need to daily to rationalize all this a pencil to the to keep them from a as the the logic to the fact is that you know what you can do to wait works and raised in successful is by people still selecting and getting motivated for different reasons in these committees have to do the job that's kind of like the view is just not part of the nature of how what you politicized it doesn't appeal to the time people who were already with comedians most cases very or here's the catch there are some shouts would should not work meetings and could do the thing to do them without quitting a job's this visit had insisted a the figure argument for building at the executive quickly we shouldn't have board members try to fill the sings with volunteers that we'd be really do need a budget of some significant funds you higher folks who can do that says yes that's is needs that's that of the major conclusions that come out of the least of my mind isn't a need time of professional staff to run the organization and do the things anything is a mother calls the debt is that this meant the deadbeat communities with their a stencil a strong preference for self-selection in flat or

;From 40 minutes
Sheng and Tom on the other qualities that many diseases won't countenance of the wicked Shia town is inconsistent with aid in to see it as it consoles a committee music and it is all standing consultants like there and it's not an end to the disintegration to view a not to solve but we will leave I'm sure we talking a lot more in the sprockets and suits were speaking about money and how much money is being brought in for Virginia foundation there is an interesting mention on the Suncoast saying that the immediate foundation received by paid fell 40 2025 US dollars for the month of October which is about $10,000 a week and they noted that this is the highest amount ever when there is no fundraisers of this is a guest from the little message that someone might see about donating a help in the preview of the fund-raising is well we had our gay gay gay host of looked advertising and with media and the cost asked if everybody am sure knows in the archives of the fall thing about funding streamflow with the yen against some of the gained lots of attention and a lot of other yelled of this sort of that motivated people that made few donations first in a thing to think of my civil $42,000 a sound like a lot of people a lot of money for life evils the shadows of the suit for those of you may never make them a 21 year on it is not enough money to run the foundation I'm $42,000 the early case to staff costs of the existing staff against does not in begin to cover the Haute going to monthly hosting charges might as you know represent either the time foundation has to raise calm in order to make its Basie budgets needs -- he raised nearly 100 at least $100,000 a month so that that is so forth that the outlook for a third of what they need for routine ivory senses I city may sell lot more than that during a fund-raising drive in and inside you certainly need one in the cave ran out of money and falling short goals and all that in how does we do here keep running I guess I'm asking him to grow the foundation is not running short on money to fund a snakes and has us in the beacon on the need to now on Dave that fortunate in that the last couple fundraisers have been much more successful than expected on the flipside the entire grant base tired other people of a very full-time staff of the part-time bookkeeper like it's fair to say that at least two more full-time positions would be completely warranted this point at least in Honduras if not more than either needs to be a least a pavilion where the bookkeeper there needs to be probably a professional CFO of professional CIL Reseda some or someone else to handle broader ranges to a broader range of chemical response to listen Brian currently covers common and probably also a being good at the feet of launcher for near into a professional fundraiser will monitor and report to the list is out there who've never visited the donation pages of the immediate foundation right out highly recommend that it's actually really interesting to read other blogs because as each person donates to pay pelvic and the little comment on the inside is green of and it's really so that is very inspiring to read what people write out their personal you see lots of students donating 10 or $20 a use in ISO by term paper you 20 bucks to a including sometimes less to say I can afford lunch this week but I'm giving you 20 bucks a butt is really great seeing folks say you know for some I'm ever used at a is great and give a hundred bucks and a pair thousand I'm not until I say I somehow works are you know I did he know where I'm been I'm I'm probably going to go increase in selling a missile used with media with Keady heavily over and it's saved me from a mean I I also complain you read my blog you complained about situation for the work he has failed to provide information and it worked out the many cases insufficient to the answers I've been looking for calm blood and the crazies that fund-raising success he is his promising first as you for a nine on fur trim it is no fun racer I. I. was the first in the room near there is going to be a fundraiser of last month and are seeking last bedtime because critics is heading there is no time Friday I guess they didn't hold which is probably just as well because Larry was was something hit lists banging his time in these his fundraiser went very well understanding calm may be waiting in slap the election since the positives and every people who are otherwise be standing under the

;From 45 minutes
Cecil spent on something else is that that's our election season is over so you will cut to the nation voted in by the Ike I would think that we wouldn't coincide with it comes to much is it a universe of which he could use is much bigger than the ones where free this is in it again overlapped the investors because of people who have committed to open to free time can end the people like me who start of an open-source development edited for a long lot longer than I've been around with the abuse and even exist on evident when I was an open-source and it's just as I see this as an extension of what I was doing and I was one of people involved in the nutritional velvety yell in indirectly because of comments I made about how did he feel sorry for documents in its side in the Al so we view to blame for a crappy jute your system yeah I apparently how old I was in the the sum of the sum the early documentation's discussions in Baghdad else is a suite at the time it embeds the weak a license for documentation problems in the present physical the is not a soccer nation that's right so it's this is a way see it yells the chart before Siddiqui owned to be something it was a good forest of a deputy at the own hour try to force a deity of the something you find or so can write a new one ends eventually but that's not write the with the license is something the with the key via licensing this make an awful unique touch life driven of license this go from there need me to life in a friendly fun to the own on that's that's a loaded word of K. I. now I know thanks for the a sore neck stories about Steward Susan B. new steward selections in the end looks at the likely date for elections the 25th of November a they're still not sure that it is convenient for the all existing sewers only to reapply a wished remain a steward which I'm sure we'll come personal Islamorada no end the rules procedures or missile discussion a better hurry up there is only a light of the seven days before it starts so that's not the cells after you have some more the if you do not know instant words are basically people who have them access to reduce our costectomy mediate projects example if they need to them if there is a small community development and how we can clean the air fares, the way and last attempt is very poor a steward for getting an important administrator to clean up to where it are rather storage taken neutral will basically every once in a while there is a steward elections pages to insist his opponents to know what happens project prefers a administrator person nominated in many ranch anyways with different about this to election is that it's time at only more erratic systems to attest to reconfirm that they have to have taken with the Canadian office that they are 18 years old and that day came at a wrote stereo identity to well written the staff Sergeant Randy cannot write need and yeah they wanted to get Steward Lott is in detail the ride for the Stewart last has a lie up so I don't a 18 years old but of the Holland Tunnel to the camera I the to pay attorney at a UNIX in ancient pioneer for adjournment of the ancient airport sign if I the 18 or older in the real light i surreal is a really interesting requirement on I know a lot of people will be upset because it rules out SJ as possible steward because it essays is remarkably in a close is to use real-life identity .extreme EPS SJ I do not mean I don't mean CM and yeah I mean estimate incline in bone can climb a knee as as a I'd solicit the is department is imposed by Brad because Grant once you have once and know who these people are intimate a invalid most of their people to its was uncivil I have the nerve Brad Patrick is that the executive director and general counsel for the immediate fantasy says because I steward actions can have our legal consequences and 70 will move to Vietnam accountable for their actions in order to be able to basically for the highest manpower and I'm looking the examination of storage to have every field how in the biggest thing to Steward said as the steward's hand axes to check user across dad is the check user is widely known is the often spoken this being the only I'm on

;From 50 minutes
Oval action on with media event are looking them in the community to tell anything else described to trick users allows the fine IP numbers right is a lot terrifying out when the blood IT number user is using or what users are using IP number this could be this ago the potentially very in kerosene or eating and I in in the most ashamed case goods near the results on the arrest or inning in extreme cases the sons of the death sentence to the people laugh about that obviously had situation like that a few months ago involving a thing if how are you so reacts there on say there was an incident involving edits almonds that were made about the day is is a death penalty offense he told the king of filing and there were some some was a vandalism to an article about some Thai environment in which a smoke that leave the king and there were people who want to know a true head was responsible for those submitted it is inhibited it had been the eye person ally in the information to suit the young to the officials in title and it is for execute the response so it is aimed is not a light responsibility is a very serious for sons of the just goes to keep their fingers out of and develop projects as I was up and requesting snide and exhibiting are responsible tonight do that on and off and we'll see you see someone popped into IRC channel and say something weird going on is their steward around the sysop me for an hour to something so you will see this across the stewards how early elections to the point of November let's see how that goes with it shorter stories but they're not urgent soon as the next week would like to give so thanks out to two users who have answered a call for transcription of users read on the end Jesse W. have graciously transcribe post of tubal episodes and to the list of the surviving the special of us in some of I believe so yes her yeah, it's a pretty big challenge I know the rest of us yeah at times anything had been held there in deathly a big thumbs up to the people who may happen this week and believe that people in this elevator and so involved that really makes things a lot easier for us doing this young people are involved and people are interested in people like you to deathly make our jobs one easier Johnson City jobs but if it yesterday news is that we do entrench himself know of a Valeri Center in view it should be interesting to the folks who said this is probably the most in-depth of interview with Larry of houses and use of forms to fund them linked off of the special purpose of one page on giving him in the also have the transcripts for us and five from light and we could be a know in current page of goal be no handed to them dad anywhere in pesky Pennsylvania in Pennsylvania, was it me.  Now you tell us somebody yet it were investigating how on her and four mills and the extent in a vision for the Nickleby Nolan and you application saying that he had an MBA and he sent them harder dollars to the old mill a hundred more hours a heat get a executive MBA and they also fling the year 3.5 grade-point the this happiness canceled these very general lawsuit against her diploma mill and a use these standing on sure it's a snow that's pretty much are the to log are things to this article came to my attention the consumers of realism such as whether Judy the leader and I is yelling to lightly harmful to him in the out but this article's been out with the case of December 2000 for a dismissal because there is some discussion about so whether was sufficiently sourcing manipulation within the next multiple references and that is to get the NBA ago when his favorite pictures the gap during a mortar more complex on the to the this is known by deleting the your eagle in yes there is a stats article I most thin air claims against category I shall

;From 55 minutes
For a dealer covered city of that there is so the people like cats like Socks presents the Clintons can't in them a Canadian parliamentary cats if you're familiar with the induce the tradition of there being cats loosen about the Parliament to keep my status of the like to is some facilities that are real some of them or fall are fictitious but there is wickedly it is actually have a 23 pages on cats and it is a full subcategory of historical guess I'm a just more little earnings were wickedly it has cut rates in other places might not consider time I have no perfect is also an article that leads they sparkled on things -- no will go to your how to with a degree are beautiful sure if will you do that this is interesting there is a is a list of unaccredited institutions of higher learning you which was a red eye that all I ivory no time board back in board was backed pretty back in May 2004 in ozone of the folks in work on its written pointless if you regardless of back into those more it but it was list of diploma mills said and someone said that's not neutral we need to renew the fees list of cannot institutions of higher learning was like I couldn't argue out of you that's probably true of the the SSL started in the bliss is grooming were engrossed as the solidly find anything out and used it as a specified menu in share of the slaves let us know that in fact to having it back to us and to wrap things up on Bikini weekly.com we have our nice little comments we got a fee of weekly@theweekly.com join the car in which he earnings the Kia WP: weekly apparently is our new shark at that's just gotten a sovereignty of active air there's lots of ways to get in touch indefinitely this on death really need your feedback and intolerant if you're just of the fine inch think it is a shelving Joseph Livermore voices different viewpoints different physical voices so the snow to and country popular belief screening and you are genes how but it helps now at Jason town of the nominating plot 80 the IMF relating to a end-of-life in 80 yes.  Here five need and like the asked me if they film and live convene and think him there and will not of when I and save the of that here to you as I said in closing on I of and have it like live convene in with a a lengthy the of the have of of him who</text>
      <sha1>lm7a6tue4bixtc6gncmnai1e6js40px</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>