<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Silence is Defeat</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>975431</id>
    <revision>
      <id>357571380</id>
      <parentid>16760688</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-04-22T06:31:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SmackBot</username>
        <id>433328</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor></minor>
      <comment>moved [[Wikipedia:Votes for deletion/Silence is Defeat]] to [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Silence is Defeat]]: Move VfD to AfD.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Silence is Defeat]]: Spam for an [http://www.google.com/search?&amp;q=link:www.silenceisdefeat.org insignificant] website with a grand [http://www.alexa.com/data/details/?url=silenceisdefeat.org Alexa ranking of 5,672,943]. [[User:Mirv|&amp;#8212;No-One]][[User talk:Mirv|&amp;nbsp;''Jones'']] [[Special:Emailuser/Mirv|&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;]] 00:44, 11 Sep 2004 (UTC)
*'''Delete'''. An ultra-primitive site offers free access to Open Source software operating from a student dorm and solicits donations for themselves and for a sacked buddy hacker. [[User:Mikkalai|Mikkalai]] 00:52, 11 Sep 2004 (UTC)
*'''Delete'''. - [[User:Evil saltine|Evil saltine]] 02:28, 11 Sep 2004 (UTC)
*403 google hits, only the first few of which refer to the software.  I'm surprised Google even managed to index this one.  '''Delete''', not notable.  --[[User:Ardonik|Ardonik]].[[User talk:Ardonik|talk()]] 02:50, Sep 11, 2004 (UTC)
*'''Delete''' -- not notable.
*Delete: Advertising for a non-notable website. [[User:Geogre|Geogre]] 12:57, 11 Sep 2004 (UTC)
*'''Delete''', same as above. [[User:Crimmer|crimmer]] 17:45, Sep 11, 2004 (UTC)
*'''Delete.'''&amp;#8202;Non-notable computer. [[User:Gwalla|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]] &amp;mdash; [[User:Gwalla|Gwalla]] | [[User talk:Gwalla|Talk]] 23:28, 11 Sep 2004 (UTC)
*'''Keep'''? Where does it say they're operating from a student dorm?  An [[ARIN]] [[whois]] indicates the server is in a [http://www.sagonet.com/datacenter/ pretty big data center].  Also, where does it say that the donation money is going towards a “sacked buddy hacker”?  One more thing – what makes other [[shell account]] providers ([[Super Dimension Fortress]], [[Metawire]]) notable that excludes them?  I don't have much experience with Wikipedia, aside from being a daily user.  I only added this entry because I've been using their service for a long while and I thought it belonged with the others.  I apologize if I've wasted any time.
**What's that? : ''"Hairball, of HBX Networks, is facing 1,918 years in prison for crimes that were committed over his public access Unix system by an unknown user. Please give him some support and visit http://helpmike.org."'' ... and go to "donate" link there. [[User:Mikkalai|Mikkalai]] 06:48, 13 Sep 2004 (UTC)
**You might be right, they are good guys (but when someone asks no give him money for "free service" he provides, I become suspicious. Is their money-asking activity legal, BTW?). But still, two-buddy operation hardly deserves place in encyclopedia, unless you prove that they provide significant inpact on community.  [[User:Mikkalai|Mikkalai]] 07:05, 13 Sep 2004 (UTC)
**Fair enough.  However, about the free account stuff... there are two meathods one can use to join.  The second involves using snail mail and is perfectly free.  That's how I joined.  They're just trying to tie online users to a physical address, I think.  To protect themselves, perhaps?  Anyway, they should make things more clear.
*'''Delete''' - advert - [[User:Texture|&lt;font color=red&gt;T&amp;#949;x&lt;/font&gt;]][[User Talk:Texture|&lt;font color=blue&gt;&amp;#964;&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:Texture|&lt;font color=red&gt;ur&amp;#949;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;!-- TANSTAAFL --&gt;]] 20:05, 14 Sep 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>eqsfedd903u0emfw3scbe4x3m4lp743</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>