<?xml version="1.0" ?><page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" version="0.8">
    <title>Yahoo Sherpa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32859399</id>
    <revision>
      <id>534754613</id>
      <parentid>527197925</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-01-25T02:01:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sigje</username>
        <id>8645443</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Software
| name                   = Sherpa
| logo                   = 
| screenshot             =
| caption                =
| developer              = [[Yahoo! Inc.]]
| status                 = Active
| programming language   = [[C++ (programming language)|C++]], [[PHP]]
| operating system       = [[Linux]]
| genre                  = [[key-value store]]
}}

'''Sherpa''' is [[Yahoo!]]'s next-generation [[cloud storage]] [[Computing platform|platform]]. It is a hosted, distributed and geographically replicated key-value [[data store]]. It is a [[NoSQL (concept)|NoSQL]] solution that has been developed by Yahoo!, to address scalability, availability, and [[Latency (engineering)|latency]] needs of Yahoo! websites. Sherpa has capabilities such as elastic growth, multi-tenancy, global footprint for local low-latency access, asynchronous replication, [[Representational_state_transfer|REST]]-based web service APIs, novel per-record consistency knobs, high availability, compression, secondary indexes, and record-level replication.

== Architecture ==
Sherpa is a multi-tenant system. An application can store data in a table, which is a collection of records. A table is [[Shard (database architecture)|shard]]ed into smaller pieces called tablets. Data is sharded based on the [[Hash function|hash value]] of the key, or range partitioned. Tablets are stored on nodes referred to as storage units. A software routing layer keeps track of mapping between applications tablets and storage units. Applications send requests to the router, which forwards them to the correct storage unit based on the tablet map. Clients can get/set/delete, and scan records via unique record primary keys.

== Data model ==
'''Sherpa''''s data model is a key-value store where data is stored as [[JSON]] [[Binary large object|blob]]s. Data is organized in tables where primary key uniqueness can be enforced, but other than that, there are no fixed schemas. It supports single-table scans with predicates. Customers can choose a variety of table types: distributed hash table, distributed ordered table, and mastered and merging tables. Application-specific access patterns determine the suitability of each table type. Query patterns affect key definition.

== Features ==
=== Scalability ===
Sherpa scales by partitioning data. In Sherpa, data partitions are called "tablets". Each customer-defined table is partitioned into tablets. Therefore, tablets are both units of work assignment and tenancy. Each tablet contains a range of records.  Sherpa can scale to very large numbers of tables, tablets and records.

=== Elasticity ===
The system scales horizontally as newer machines are added, with no downtime to applications. Other elasticity operations include data partition assignment, reassignment and splitting.

=== Fault-tolerance ===
Data is automatically replicated to multiple nodes for [[Fault-tolerant design|fault tolerance]]. [[Replication (computer science)|Replication]] across multiple data centers is supported. Single-node failure is transparent to the applications. Sherpa relied on a reliable transaction message [[Enterprise service bus|bus]] for replicating transactions. This message bus guarantees at-least-once delivery of transaction messages.

=== Tunable consistency ===
'''Sherpa''' supports different levels of consistency, ranging from per-record timeline consistency where all writes are serialized to a master copy, to [[eventual consistency]].

=== Selective record replication ===
Replication [[granularity]] is at the record level, as well as table level.

=== Backup ===
The Backup feature allows for multiple old copies of the full table to be saved in [[Online and offline|offline]] storage. From this offline storage, customers may retrieve old versions of individual records.

=== Secondary indexes ===
Many applications need to access data via non-primary key data fields.  '''Sherpa''' supports asynchronous secondary indexes.

== References ==
&lt;!--- See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.141.68&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf PNUTS architecture]
* [http://developer.yahoo.com/blogs/ydn/posts/2010/06/sherpa_update/ Sherpa update]
* [http://developer.yahoo.com/blogs/ydn/posts/2009/06/sherpa/ Yahoo Developer Network]
* [http://developer.yahoo.com/blogs/ydn/posts/2011/09/sherpa-grows-and-scales-in-2011/ Sherpa growth and scale]

&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;





[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Cloud storage gateways]]
[[Category:Yahoo! products]]</text>
      <sha1>9t6q2beiqh5zm25i60a765npvkdamq5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>